Hey guys, tonight we begin with the
Hey guys, tonight we begin with the delightfully dysfunctional world of the
delightfully dysfunctional world of the
delightfully dysfunctional world of the ancient Greek gods. A pantheon so
ancient Greek gods. A pantheon so
ancient Greek gods. A pantheon so powerful, so dramatic, and so
powerful, so dramatic, and so
powerful, so dramatic, and so emotionally unstable.
emotionally unstable.
emotionally unstable. So before you get comfortable, take a
So before you get comfortable, take a
So before you get comfortable, take a moment to like the video and subscribe,
moment to like the video and subscribe,
moment to like the video and subscribe, but only if you genuinely enjoy what I
but only if you genuinely enjoy what I
but only if you genuinely enjoy what I do here. And let me know in the comments
do here. And let me know in the comments
do here. And let me know in the comments where you're tuning in from and what
where you're tuning in from and what
where you're tuning in from and what time it is for you. It's always
time it is for you. It's always
time it is for you. It's always fascinating to see who's joining us from
fascinating to see who's joining us from
fascinating to see who's joining us from around the world.
around the world.
around the world. Now, dim the lights. Maybe turn on a fan
Now, dim the lights. Maybe turn on a fan
Now, dim the lights. Maybe turn on a fan for that soft background hum. And let's
for that soft background hum. And let's
for that soft background hum. And let's ease into tonight's journey together.
ease into tonight's journey together.
ease into tonight's journey together. Let's begin with the big guy himself,
Let's begin with the big guy himself,
Let's begin with the big guy himself, Zeus, god of the sky, ruler of Olympus,
Zeus, god of the sky, ruler of Olympus,
Zeus, god of the sky, ruler of Olympus, and walking proof that absolute power
and walking proof that absolute power
and walking proof that absolute power absolutely fries your sense of
absolutely fries your sense of
absolutely fries your sense of boundaries.
boundaries.
boundaries. Zeus was the youngest son of Cronis and
Zeus was the youngest son of Cronis and
Zeus was the youngest son of Cronis and Ria. His dad, like all great fathers,
Ria. His dad, like all great fathers,
Ria. His dad, like all great fathers, had a habit of swallowing his children
had a habit of swallowing his children
had a habit of swallowing his children whole to prevent them from overthrowing
whole to prevent them from overthrowing
whole to prevent them from overthrowing him. romantic.
him. romantic.
him. romantic. Fortunately, Ria saved baby Zeus by
Fortunately, Ria saved baby Zeus by
Fortunately, Ria saved baby Zeus by tricking Cronis with a rock in a
tricking Cronis with a rock in a
tricking Cronis with a rock in a blanket, which tells you a lot about how
blanket, which tells you a lot about how
blanket, which tells you a lot about how closely this guy paid attention. Once
closely this guy paid attention. Once
closely this guy paid attention. Once Zeus grew up, he led a divine rebellion
Zeus grew up, he led a divine rebellion
Zeus grew up, he led a divine rebellion against Cronis, sliced open his father's
against Cronis, sliced open his father's
against Cronis, sliced open his father's stomach, Freud would have a field day,
stomach, Freud would have a field day,
stomach, Freud would have a field day, and freed his siblings, Poseidon, Hades,
and freed his siblings, Poseidon, Hades,
and freed his siblings, Poseidon, Hades, Hia, Hestia, and Deita. Boom. The
Hia, Hestia, and Deita. Boom. The
Hia, Hestia, and Deita. Boom. The original dysfunctional family was born.
original dysfunctional family was born.
original dysfunctional family was born. After the gods won the war against the
After the gods won the war against the
After the gods won the war against the titans, Zeus became king. He ruled the
titans, Zeus became king. He ruled the
titans, Zeus became king. He ruled the heavens, controlled thunder and
heavens, controlled thunder and
heavens, controlled thunder and lightning, and was in charge of cosmic
lightning, and was in charge of cosmic
lightning, and was in charge of cosmic order, justice, and oaths. In theory,
order, justice, and oaths. In theory,
order, justice, and oaths. In theory, that is. In practice, Zeus spent most of
that is. In practice, Zeus spent most of
that is. In practice, Zeus spent most of his time transforming into various
his time transforming into various
his time transforming into various animals and seducing anything with a
animals and seducing anything with a
animals and seducing anything with a pulse. Swans, bulls, eagles, golden
pulse. Swans, bulls, eagles, golden
pulse. Swans, bulls, eagles, golden mist. The man had no chill and no
mist. The man had no chill and no
mist. The man had no chill and no consistent moral code. Imagine your
consistent moral code. Imagine your
consistent moral code. Imagine your country's Supreme Court justice turning
country's Supreme Court justice turning
country's Supreme Court justice turning into a goose to flirt with civilians.
into a goose to flirt with civilians.
into a goose to flirt with civilians. That's Zeus, but with more lightning.
That's Zeus, but with more lightning.
That's Zeus, but with more lightning. His love life was an open- source
His love life was an open- source
His love life was an open- source disaster. He married his sister, Hia,
disaster. He married his sister, Hia,
disaster. He married his sister, Hia, which went about as well as you'd
which went about as well as you'd
which went about as well as you'd expect. He had dozens of affairs with
expect. He had dozens of affairs with
expect. He had dozens of affairs with goddesses, nymphs, mortals, and probably
goddesses, nymphs, mortals, and probably
goddesses, nymphs, mortals, and probably one or two house plants.
one or two house plants.
one or two house plants. The result, an overwhelming number of
The result, an overwhelming number of
The result, an overwhelming number of demigod children, many of whom had
demigod children, many of whom had
demigod children, many of whom had serious parental abandonment issues and
serious parental abandonment issues and
serious parental abandonment issues and accidentally founded entire mythologies.
accidentally founded entire mythologies.
accidentally founded entire mythologies. But despite all that, Zeus wasn't
But despite all that, Zeus wasn't
But despite all that, Zeus wasn't entirely chaotic. When he wasn't
entirely chaotic. When he wasn't
entirely chaotic. When he wasn't cheating or chucking lightning bolts at
cheating or chucking lightning bolts at
cheating or chucking lightning bolts at mortals who didn't offer proper
mortals who didn't offer proper
mortals who didn't offer proper sacrifices, he did act as the cosmic
sacrifices, he did act as the cosmic
sacrifices, he did act as the cosmic referee. He enforced oaths, upheld law,
referee. He enforced oaths, upheld law,
referee. He enforced oaths, upheld law, and occasionally punished people for
and occasionally punished people for
and occasionally punished people for being more arrogant than he was, which
being more arrogant than he was, which
being more arrogant than he was, which frankly took effort.
frankly took effort.
frankly took effort. Zeus was respected, feared, and
Zeus was respected, feared, and
Zeus was respected, feared, and constantly causing PR nightmares for
constantly causing PR nightmares for
constantly causing PR nightmares for Olympus. He had power, presence, and
Olympus. He had power, presence, and
Olympus. He had power, presence, and zero understanding of personal space. He
zero understanding of personal space. He
zero understanding of personal space. He was both protector and predator, judge,
was both protector and predator, judge,
was both protector and predator, judge, and joke, the ultimate divine
and joke, the ultimate divine
and joke, the ultimate divine contradiction.
contradiction.
contradiction. Hia is technically the goddess of
Hia is technically the goddess of
Hia is technically the goddess of marriage, family, and childbirth, which
marriage, family, and childbirth, which
marriage, family, and childbirth, which is ironic because her own marriage is an
is ironic because her own marriage is an
is ironic because her own marriage is an absolute dumpster fire in a golden
absolute dumpster fire in a golden
absolute dumpster fire in a golden chariot. She's Zeus's wife, also his
chariot. She's Zeus's wife, also his
chariot. She's Zeus's wife, also his sister, because, you know, mythology.
sister, because, you know, mythology.
sister, because, you know, mythology. Their wedding was supposed to be the
Their wedding was supposed to be the
Their wedding was supposed to be the divine ideal of sacred union. Instead,
divine ideal of sacred union. Instead,
divine ideal of sacred union. Instead, it turned into a centuries long soap
it turned into a centuries long soap
it turned into a centuries long soap opera filled with infidelity, revenge,
opera filled with infidelity, revenge,
opera filled with infidelity, revenge, and a shocking number of people turned
and a shocking number of people turned
and a shocking number of people turned into animals or trees or stone.
into animals or trees or stone.
into animals or trees or stone. Hera is powerful, the undisputed queen
Hera is powerful, the undisputed queen
Hera is powerful, the undisputed queen of the gods. But her power mostly
of the gods. But her power mostly
of the gods. But her power mostly expresses itself in one very specific
expresses itself in one very specific
expresses itself in one very specific way. Vengeance.
way. Vengeance.
way. Vengeance. Not on Zeus, of course. No, that would
Not on Zeus, of course. No, that would
Not on Zeus, of course. No, that would be too simple. Here's Fury is laser
be too simple. Here's Fury is laser
be too simple. Here's Fury is laser focused on the women Zeus seduces, or
focused on the women Zeus seduces, or
focused on the women Zeus seduces, or let's be honest, outright kidnaps and
let's be honest, outright kidnaps and
let's be honest, outright kidnaps and their unfortunate children. She once
their unfortunate children. She once
their unfortunate children. She once turned a woman into a cow, cursed
turned a woman into a cow, cursed
turned a woman into a cow, cursed another to only speak in echoes, and in
another to only speak in echoes, and in
another to only speak in echoes, and in one particularly cruel moment tried to
one particularly cruel moment tried to
one particularly cruel moment tried to kill baby Hercules with a pair of
kill baby Hercules with a pair of
kill baby Hercules with a pair of serpents. That was literally his baby.
serpents. That was literally his baby.
serpents. That was literally his baby. Hers, no. His still? Nope. It's hard to
Hers, no. His still? Nope. It's hard to
Hers, no. His still? Nope. It's hard to blame her entirely. Imagine being the
blame her entirely. Imagine being the
blame her entirely. Imagine being the goddess of marriage while your husband
goddess of marriage while your husband
goddess of marriage while your husband is out here inventing new forms of
is out here inventing new forms of
is out here inventing new forms of animal-based flirtation. But still, her
animal-based flirtation. But still, her
animal-based flirtation. But still, her divine coping mechanisms often included
divine coping mechanisms often included
divine coping mechanisms often included eternal curses and elaborate
eternal curses and elaborate
eternal curses and elaborate punishments.
punishments.
punishments. Therapy wasn't a thing in ancient
Therapy wasn't a thing in ancient
Therapy wasn't a thing in ancient Greece, so revenge was the next best
Greece, so revenge was the next best
Greece, so revenge was the next best option. Yet, despite all that, Hia
option. Yet, despite all that, Hia
option. Yet, despite all that, Hia wasn't just a celestial grudgeholder.
wasn't just a celestial grudgeholder.
wasn't just a celestial grudgeholder. She also protected women in childbirth,
She also protected women in childbirth,
She also protected women in childbirth, upheld the sanctity of marriage
upheld the sanctity of marriage
upheld the sanctity of marriage theoretically, and punished oaths broken
theoretically, and punished oaths broken
theoretically, and punished oaths broken by mortals. She had temples, priests,
by mortals. She had temples, priests,
by mortals. She had temples, priests, and a devoted cult. Following cities
and a devoted cult. Following cities
and a devoted cult. Following cities like Argos and Samos worshiped her as a
like Argos and Samos worshiped her as a
like Argos and Samos worshiped her as a major force of divine order.
major force of divine order.
major force of divine order. In short, Ha was the goddess you prayed
In short, Ha was the goddess you prayed
In short, Ha was the goddess you prayed to when your husband was faithful and
to when your husband was faithful and
to when your husband was faithful and the one who probably sent a plague when
the one who probably sent a plague when
the one who probably sent a plague when he wasn't.
he wasn't.
he wasn't. She's a fascinating paradox, the
She's a fascinating paradox, the
She's a fascinating paradox, the embodiment of female dignity and power
embodiment of female dignity and power
embodiment of female dignity and power in a system that constantly humiliated
in a system that constantly humiliated
in a system that constantly humiliated her.
her.
her. Her story isn't just about jealousy.
Her story isn't just about jealousy.
Her story isn't just about jealousy. It's about a woman who was supposed to
It's about a woman who was supposed to
It's about a woman who was supposed to symbolize unity while holding Olympus
symbolize unity while holding Olympus
symbolize unity while holding Olympus together with pure spite and decorative
together with pure spite and decorative
together with pure spite and decorative fury. Poseidon was the god of the sea,
fury. Poseidon was the god of the sea,
fury. Poseidon was the god of the sea, earthquakes, storms, and for some
earthquakes, storms, and for some
earthquakes, storms, and for some reason, horses.
reason, horses.
reason, horses. because nothing says ocean god like a
because nothing says ocean god like a
because nothing says ocean god like a herd of galloping stallions.
herd of galloping stallions.
herd of galloping stallions. But hey, mythology, he was one of the
But hey, mythology, he was one of the
But hey, mythology, he was one of the three main brothers. Zeus got the sky,
three main brothers. Zeus got the sky,
three main brothers. Zeus got the sky, Hades got the underworld, and Poseidon
Hades got the underworld, and Poseidon
Hades got the underworld, and Poseidon got everything wet, which suited him
got everything wet, which suited him
got everything wet, which suited him just fine. He ruled over the vast
just fine. He ruled over the vast
just fine. He ruled over the vast oceans, commanded sea creatures, both
oceans, commanded sea creatures, both
oceans, commanded sea creatures, both beautiful and nightmarish, and wielded a
beautiful and nightmarish, and wielded a
beautiful and nightmarish, and wielded a massive trident, not just a pointy fork,
massive trident, not just a pointy fork,
massive trident, not just a pointy fork, but a three-pronged divine rage stick
but a three-pronged divine rage stick
but a three-pronged divine rage stick capable of leveling entire cities.
capable of leveling entire cities.
capable of leveling entire cities. Poseidon was revered and feared in equal
Poseidon was revered and feared in equal
Poseidon was revered and feared in equal measure. Sailors prayed to him for safe
measure. Sailors prayed to him for safe
measure. Sailors prayed to him for safe passage. Fishermen made offerings.
passage. Fishermen made offerings.
passage. Fishermen made offerings. Citybuilders asked his permission before
Citybuilders asked his permission before
Citybuilders asked his permission before putting anything too close to the
putting anything too close to the
putting anything too close to the shoreline, lest it become beachfront
shoreline, lest it become beachfront
shoreline, lest it become beachfront property by accident.
property by accident.
property by accident. But let's be honest, Poseidon had
But let's be honest, Poseidon had
But let's be honest, Poseidon had issues. Big crashing tidal wavesized
issues. Big crashing tidal wavesized
issues. Big crashing tidal wavesized emotional issues. He was the classic
emotional issues. He was the classic
emotional issues. He was the classic unpredictable uncle. Sometimes generous,
unpredictable uncle. Sometimes generous,
unpredictable uncle. Sometimes generous, sometimes devastating, always a bit
sometimes devastating, always a bit
sometimes devastating, always a bit salty. One moment he's creating islands,
salty. One moment he's creating islands,
salty. One moment he's creating islands, the next he's flooding your crops
the next he's flooding your crops
the next he's flooding your crops because someone forgot to thank him
because someone forgot to thank him
because someone forgot to thank him during a sacrificial goat ceremony. He
during a sacrificial goat ceremony. He
during a sacrificial goat ceremony. He once struck the ground so hard with his
once struck the ground so hard with his
once struck the ground so hard with his trident that he caused an earthquake
trident that he caused an earthquake
trident that he caused an earthquake just because he lost a city naming
just because he lost a city naming
just because he lost a city naming contest to Athena.
contest to Athena.
contest to Athena. Seriously,
Seriously,
Seriously, she gave Athens an olive tree. He
she gave Athens an olive tree. He
she gave Athens an olive tree. He offered a saltwater spring. The people
offered a saltwater spring. The people
offered a saltwater spring. The people chose olives. He chose vengeance. That's
chose olives. He chose vengeance. That's
chose olives. He chose vengeance. That's Poseidon in a nutshell. He also had a
Poseidon in a nutshell. He also had a
Poseidon in a nutshell. He also had a rather complicated love life. There were
rather complicated love life. There were
rather complicated love life. There were nymphs, mortals, even one incident
nymphs, mortals, even one incident
nymphs, mortals, even one incident involving Medusa, which ended with her
involving Medusa, which ended with her
involving Medusa, which ended with her getting snake hair and a monster label
getting snake hair and a monster label
getting snake hair and a monster label and him walking away without
and him walking away without
and him walking away without consequences.
consequences.
consequences. Classic.
Classic.
Classic. Despite all that, Poseidon wasn't just a
Despite all that, Poseidon wasn't just a
Despite all that, Poseidon wasn't just a stormy brute. He was a protector of
stormy brute. He was a protector of
stormy brute. He was a protector of seafarers, a builder of cities, and in
seafarers, a builder of cities, and in
seafarers, a builder of cities, and in his calmer moments, a god of prosperity
his calmer moments, a god of prosperity
his calmer moments, a god of prosperity and fertility.
and fertility.
and fertility. He was essential to ancient Greek life,
He was essential to ancient Greek life,
He was essential to ancient Greek life, especially for a culture so dependent on
especially for a culture so dependent on
especially for a culture so dependent on the sea. But like the ocean itself, he
the sea. But like the ocean itself, he
the sea. But like the ocean itself, he was always one storm away from reminding
was always one storm away from reminding
was always one storm away from reminding everyone who was really in charge. Hades
everyone who was really in charge. Hades
everyone who was really in charge. Hades is the god of the underworld. Not hell
is the god of the underworld. Not hell
is the god of the underworld. Not hell exactly, but a vast, gloomy realm where
exactly, but a vast, gloomy realm where
exactly, but a vast, gloomy realm where all souls eventually clock out for
all souls eventually clock out for
all souls eventually clock out for eternity. Contrary to modern pop
eternity. Contrary to modern pop
eternity. Contrary to modern pop culture, Hades wasn't evil. He wasn't
culture, Hades wasn't evil. He wasn't
culture, Hades wasn't evil. He wasn't even particularly cruel. He was just
even particularly cruel. He was just
even particularly cruel. He was just incredibly tired of everyone.
incredibly tired of everyone.
incredibly tired of everyone. While Zeus got the sky and Poseidon got
While Zeus got the sky and Poseidon got
While Zeus got the sky and Poseidon got the seas, Hades drew the short straw and
the seas, Hades drew the short straw and
the seas, Hades drew the short straw and got stuck managing the ancient Greek
got stuck managing the ancient Greek
got stuck managing the ancient Greek version of customer service for the
version of customer service for the
version of customer service for the dead. For eternity in darkness,
dead. For eternity in darkness,
dead. For eternity in darkness, surrounded by whailing, Hades ruled the
surrounded by whailing, Hades ruled the
surrounded by whailing, Hades ruled the underworld with a quiet, brooding
underworld with a quiet, brooding
underworld with a quiet, brooding authority. He wasn't flashy. He wasn't
authority. He wasn't flashy. He wasn't
authority. He wasn't flashy. He wasn't loud. He didn't throw lightning or crash
loud. He didn't throw lightning or crash
loud. He didn't throw lightning or crash weddings. He just showed up to work
weddings. He just showed up to work
weddings. He just showed up to work every day managing the logistics of
every day managing the logistics of
every day managing the logistics of eternity and making sure souls didn't
eternity and making sure souls didn't
eternity and making sure souls didn't sneak out the back. The ultimate middle
sneak out the back. The ultimate middle
sneak out the back. The ultimate middle manager. His domain was called Hades,
manager. His domain was called Hades,
manager. His domain was called Hades, too, because apparently naming a kingdom
too, because apparently naming a kingdom
too, because apparently naming a kingdom after yourself wasn't a red flag back
after yourself wasn't a red flag back
after yourself wasn't a red flag back then. It had sections for the heroic
then. It had sections for the heroic
then. It had sections for the heroic Elysium, the average Asphodel, and the
Elysium, the average Asphodel, and the
Elysium, the average Asphodel, and the truly awful Tartarus, ancient Greece's
truly awful Tartarus, ancient Greece's
truly awful Tartarus, ancient Greece's version of a very long detention. And
version of a very long detention. And
version of a very long detention. And guess who had to oversee all of it?
guess who had to oversee all of it?
guess who had to oversee all of it? That's right, Hades, the Goth workaholic
That's right, Hades, the Goth workaholic
That's right, Hades, the Goth workaholic of the gods. Now, about Pesphanany. Yes,
of the gods. Now, about Pesphanany. Yes,
of the gods. Now, about Pesphanany. Yes, he kidnapped her. Not great. Definitely
he kidnapped her. Not great. Definitely
he kidnapped her. Not great. Definitely problematic. But also, and Greek
problematic. But also, and Greek
problematic. But also, and Greek mythology is nothing if not
mythology is nothing if not
mythology is nothing if not inconsistent, they actually grew into a
inconsistent, they actually grew into a
inconsistent, they actually grew into a functional, weirdly stable marriage. She
functional, weirdly stable marriage. She
functional, weirdly stable marriage. She spent half the year with him, bringing
spent half the year with him, bringing
spent half the year with him, bringing life to the underworld and the other
life to the underworld and the other
life to the underworld and the other half on Earth, causing spring. It's less
half on Earth, causing spring. It's less
half on Earth, causing spring. It's less romance, more mythological time share.
romance, more mythological time share.
romance, more mythological time share. Hades was also the original pet dad. His
Hades was also the original pet dad. His
Hades was also the original pet dad. His dog, Cerberus, had three heads, a
dog, Cerberus, had three heads, a
dog, Cerberus, had three heads, a temper, and zero obedience training.
temper, and zero obedience training.
temper, and zero obedience training. But he kept souls in line mostly. Unlike
But he kept souls in line mostly. Unlike
But he kept souls in line mostly. Unlike his brothers, Hades didn't cheat, didn't
his brothers, Hades didn't cheat, didn't
his brothers, Hades didn't cheat, didn't rage, and didn't crave the spotlight.
rage, and didn't crave the spotlight.
rage, and didn't crave the spotlight. That's probably why ancient Greeks
That's probably why ancient Greeks
That's probably why ancient Greeks rarely built temples for him. They were
rarely built temples for him. They were
rarely built temples for him. They were terrified of attracting his attention.
terrified of attracting his attention.
terrified of attracting his attention. He was the quiet, grim uncle you didn't
He was the quiet, grim uncle you didn't
He was the quiet, grim uncle you didn't invite to the party, but still respected
invite to the party, but still respected
invite to the party, but still respected from a safe, polite distance.
from a safe, polite distance.
from a safe, polite distance. Athena is the goddess of wisdom, war
Athena is the goddess of wisdom, war
Athena is the goddess of wisdom, war strategy, handiccrafts, and staying 10
strategy, handiccrafts, and staying 10
strategy, handiccrafts, and staying 10 steps ahead of everyone without breaking
steps ahead of everyone without breaking
steps ahead of everyone without breaking a sweat. She's basically the divine
a sweat. She's basically the divine
a sweat. She's basically the divine embodiment of logic in a world full of
embodiment of logic in a world full of
embodiment of logic in a world full of emotional wrecks with lightning bolts.
emotional wrecks with lightning bolts.
emotional wrecks with lightning bolts. Her birth alone is enough to give Freud
Her birth alone is enough to give Freud
Her birth alone is enough to give Freud nightmares. Zeus, after swallowing her
nightmares. Zeus, after swallowing her
nightmares. Zeus, after swallowing her pregnant mother, Matis, because
pregnant mother, Matis, because
pregnant mother, Matis, because prophecy, of course, developed a
prophecy, of course, developed a
prophecy, of course, developed a splitting headache. Instead of aspirin,
splitting headache. Instead of aspirin,
splitting headache. Instead of aspirin, he got a hammer to the skull. And out
he got a hammer to the skull. And out
he got a hammer to the skull. And out popped Athena, fully grown, fully
popped Athena, fully grown, fully
popped Athena, fully grown, fully armored, and fully unimpressed with
armored, and fully unimpressed with
armored, and fully unimpressed with everyone. From day one, Athena made it
everyone. From day one, Athena made it
everyone. From day one, Athena made it clear she was not here for nonsense.
clear she was not here for nonsense.
clear she was not here for nonsense. Unlike her warhappy brother, Aries,
Unlike her warhappy brother, Aries,
Unlike her warhappy brother, Aries, Athena viewed conflict like a
Athena viewed conflict like a
Athena viewed conflict like a chessboard, something to be analyzed,
chessboard, something to be analyzed,
chessboard, something to be analyzed, controlled, and won with minimal
controlled, and won with minimal
controlled, and won with minimal shouting and maximum efficiency. If Aris
shouting and maximum efficiency. If Aris
shouting and maximum efficiency. If Aris was a chaotic bar fight, Athena was a
was a chaotic bar fight, Athena was a
was a chaotic bar fight, Athena was a war room with spreadsheets. She's also
war room with spreadsheets. She's also
war room with spreadsheets. She's also the goddess of crafts, which might seem
the goddess of crafts, which might seem
the goddess of crafts, which might seem out of place until you realize weaving
out of place until you realize weaving
out of place until you realize weaving in her hands was a battlefield.
in her hands was a battlefield.
in her hands was a battlefield. Just ask Arachnne, a mortal who dared
Just ask Arachnne, a mortal who dared
Just ask Arachnne, a mortal who dared challenge Athena to a weaving contest.
challenge Athena to a weaving contest.
challenge Athena to a weaving contest. Arachnne won technically, but was then
Arachnne won technically, but was then
Arachnne won technically, but was then turned into a spider for being a little
turned into a spider for being a little
turned into a spider for being a little too talented. Moral of the story, be
too talented. Moral of the story, be
too talented. Moral of the story, be humble or enjoy your new life in the
humble or enjoy your new life in the
humble or enjoy your new life in the corner of someone's ceiling.
corner of someone's ceiling.
corner of someone's ceiling. Athena stayed out of romance entirely.
Athena stayed out of romance entirely.
Athena stayed out of romance entirely. Unlike the rest of Olympus, she didn't
Unlike the rest of Olympus, she didn't
Unlike the rest of Olympus, she didn't seduce mortals, marry her brother, or
seduce mortals, marry her brother, or
seduce mortals, marry her brother, or transform into questionable animals. She
transform into questionable animals. She
transform into questionable animals. She simply had things to do. Cities to
simply had things to do. Cities to
simply had things to do. Cities to protect, heroes to advise, owls to
protect, heroes to advise, owls to
protect, heroes to advise, owls to raise.
raise.
raise. She guided Adysius home, helped Perseus
She guided Adysius home, helped Perseus
She guided Adysius home, helped Perseus behead Medusa, and probably edited the
behead Medusa, and probably edited the
behead Medusa, and probably edited the Iliad with a red pen.
Iliad with a red pen.
Iliad with a red pen. Athena is the goddess you'd want on your
Athena is the goddess you'd want on your
Athena is the goddess you'd want on your debate team, in your war council, or
debate team, in your war council, or
debate team, in your war council, or running your startup. She doesn't
running your startup. She doesn't
running your startup. She doesn't scream. She doesn't scheme. She simply
scream. She doesn't scheme. She simply
scream. She doesn't scheme. She simply outsmarts always.
outsmarts always.
outsmarts always. Aries was the Greek god of war,
Aries was the Greek god of war,
Aries was the Greek god of war, bloodshed, and punching first, thinking
bloodshed, and punching first, thinking
bloodshed, and punching first, thinking never. If Athena was war with a
never. If Athena was war with a
never. If Athena was war with a blueprint, Aris was war with a
blueprint, Aris was war with a
blueprint, Aris was war with a sledgehammer and poor impulse control.
sledgehammer and poor impulse control.
sledgehammer and poor impulse control. He represented the brutal raw chaos of
He represented the brutal raw chaos of
He represented the brutal raw chaos of battle. The part where screaming men
battle. The part where screaming men
battle. The part where screaming men charged into each other and no one
charged into each other and no one
charged into each other and no one really knew what was happening except
really knew what was happening except
really knew what was happening except that things were on fire and someone
that things were on fire and someone
that things were on fire and someone just lost a helmet.
just lost a helmet.
just lost a helmet. In short, if Aries shows up, things are
In short, if Aries shows up, things are
In short, if Aries shows up, things are about to get loud, violent, and deeply
about to get loud, violent, and deeply
about to get loud, violent, and deeply disorganized.
disorganized.
disorganized. Personalitywise,
Personalitywise,
Personalitywise, he wasn't exactly Olympus's favorite
he wasn't exactly Olympus's favorite
he wasn't exactly Olympus's favorite guest. Even his fellow gods didn't like
guest. Even his fellow gods didn't like
guest. Even his fellow gods didn't like him. Zeus once called him the most
him. Zeus once called him the most
him. Zeus once called him the most hateful of all the gods. And you know
hateful of all the gods. And you know
hateful of all the gods. And you know you've messed up when Zeus is calling
you've messed up when Zeus is calling
you've messed up when Zeus is calling you a problem. Aries was arrogant,
you a problem. Aries was arrogant,
you a problem. Aries was arrogant, hotheaded, and about as subtle as a
hotheaded, and about as subtle as a
hotheaded, and about as subtle as a flaming chariot. He wasn't particularly
flaming chariot. He wasn't particularly
flaming chariot. He wasn't particularly respected either. The Greeks admired
respected either. The Greeks admired
respected either. The Greeks admired strategy, restraint, and cleverness,
strategy, restraint, and cleverness,
strategy, restraint, and cleverness, things aris consistently failed to bring
things aris consistently failed to bring
things aris consistently failed to bring to the table. He didn't win battles with
to the table. He didn't win battles with
to the table. He didn't win battles with tactics. He just stormed in swinging.
tactics. He just stormed in swinging.
tactics. He just stormed in swinging. That worked occasionally, but more often
That worked occasionally, but more often
That worked occasionally, but more often than not, it left a trail of dead bodies
than not, it left a trail of dead bodies
than not, it left a trail of dead bodies and deeply annoyed allies. That said,
and deeply annoyed allies. That said,
and deeply annoyed allies. That said, Aris was still terrifying. He was the
Aris was still terrifying. He was the
Aris was still terrifying. He was the god of fear, literally. His sons were
god of fear, literally. His sons were
god of fear, literally. His sons were named Phobos and Daimos, aka Panic and
named Phobos and Daimos, aka Panic and
named Phobos and Daimos, aka Panic and Terror, and he loved being in the thick
Terror, and he loved being in the thick
Terror, and he loved being in the thick of a brawl. He also had an affair with
of a brawl. He also had an affair with
of a brawl. He also had an affair with Aphroditi, which sounds romantic until
Aphroditi, which sounds romantic until
Aphroditi, which sounds romantic until you remember it ended with him getting
you remember it ended with him getting
you remember it ended with him getting caught in an invisible net by her
caught in an invisible net by her
caught in an invisible net by her husband, Histus, and laughed at by the
husband, Histus, and laughed at by the
husband, Histus, and laughed at by the entire pantheon. Ancient Greek tabloids
entire pantheon. Ancient Greek tabloids
entire pantheon. Ancient Greek tabloids had a field day. In Roman mythology,
had a field day. In Roman mythology,
had a field day. In Roman mythology, Aries got a makeover as Mars, more
Aries got a makeover as Mars, more
Aries got a makeover as Mars, more disciplined, more honorable, less
disciplined, more honorable, less
disciplined, more honorable, less sweaty. But in Greece, he stayed the
sweaty. But in Greece, he stayed the
sweaty. But in Greece, he stayed the chaotic, muscle-bound avatar of
chaotic, muscle-bound avatar of
chaotic, muscle-bound avatar of violence. Still, Ahri had his moments.
violence. Still, Ahri had his moments.
violence. Still, Ahri had his moments. In times of actual war, he was feared
In times of actual war, he was feared
In times of actual war, he was feared and revered. Warriors made sacrifices to
and revered. Warriors made sacrifices to
and revered. Warriors made sacrifices to him, hoping he'd bring them strength, or
him, hoping he'd bring them strength, or
him, hoping he'd bring them strength, or at least ignore them for a while. And
at least ignore them for a while. And
at least ignore them for a while. And when he wasn't breaking things, he did
when he wasn't breaking things, he did
when he wasn't breaking things, he did ride a cool chariot pulled by fireb
ride a cool chariot pulled by fireb
ride a cool chariot pulled by fireb breathing horses, which earns him at
breathing horses, which earns him at
breathing horses, which earns him at least one style point.
least one style point.
least one style point. Aphroditi was the goddess of love,
Aphroditi was the goddess of love,
Aphroditi was the goddess of love, beauty, desire, and romantic messes with
beauty, desire, and romantic messes with
beauty, desire, and romantic messes with extremely high body counts. If you've
extremely high body counts. If you've
extremely high body counts. If you've ever seen someone fall in love way too
ever seen someone fall in love way too
ever seen someone fall in love way too fast with exactly the wrong person,
fast with exactly the wrong person,
fast with exactly the wrong person, congratulations. You've witnessed
congratulations. You've witnessed
congratulations. You've witnessed Aphrodites divine influence.
Aphrodites divine influence.
Aphrodites divine influence. There are two origin stories for her,
There are two origin stories for her,
There are two origin stories for her, depending on how much trauma you can
depending on how much trauma you can
depending on how much trauma you can stomach. In one version, she's the
stomach. In one version, she's the
stomach. In one version, she's the daughter of Zeus and Dion. In the older
daughter of Zeus and Dion. In the older
daughter of Zeus and Dion. In the older and frankly much weirder version, she's
and frankly much weirder version, she's
and frankly much weirder version, she's born from the seafoam that formed when
born from the seafoam that formed when
born from the seafoam that formed when Cronis chopped off Uranus's uh godly
Cronis chopped off Uranus's uh godly
Cronis chopped off Uranus's uh godly equipment and tossed it into the ocean.
equipment and tossed it into the ocean.
equipment and tossed it into the ocean. And yes, that's probably the least
And yes, that's probably the least
And yes, that's probably the least romantic origin ever assigned to the
romantic origin ever assigned to the
romantic origin ever assigned to the goddess of romance. Aphrodite was so
goddess of romance. Aphrodite was so
goddess of romance. Aphrodite was so stunningly beautiful that mortals and
stunningly beautiful that mortals and
stunningly beautiful that mortals and gods alike basically lost their ability
gods alike basically lost their ability
gods alike basically lost their ability to make good decisions in her presence.
to make good decisions in her presence.
to make good decisions in her presence. She had an actual magical belt, the
She had an actual magical belt, the
She had an actual magical belt, the cestus, that made her irresistible to
cestus, that made her irresistible to
cestus, that made her irresistible to anyone, which, let's be honest, is a
anyone, which, let's be honest, is a
anyone, which, let's be honest, is a mildly unfair advantage in the love
mildly unfair advantage in the love
mildly unfair advantage in the love department. Despite being the embodiment
department. Despite being the embodiment
department. Despite being the embodiment of desire, Aphrodite's own love life was
of desire, Aphrodite's own love life was
of desire, Aphrodite's own love life was complicated. She was married to
complicated. She was married to
complicated. She was married to Heristas, the hardworking god of fire
Heristas, the hardworking god of fire
Heristas, the hardworking god of fire and blacksmithing.
and blacksmithing.
and blacksmithing. But she famously preferred the company
But she famously preferred the company
But she famously preferred the company of Arri, the god of war, which tells you
of Arri, the god of war, which tells you
of Arri, the god of war, which tells you everything you need to know about her
everything you need to know about her
everything you need to know about her taste in men. Their affair was exposed
taste in men. Their affair was exposed
taste in men. Their affair was exposed when Heristas trapped them mid romance
when Heristas trapped them mid romance
when Heristas trapped them mid romance in a golden net and summoned the other
in a golden net and summoned the other
in a golden net and summoned the other gods to come take a look. Ancient
gods to come take a look. Ancient
gods to come take a look. Ancient Greece, where revenge and group
Greece, where revenge and group
Greece, where revenge and group humiliation were considered excellent
humiliation were considered excellent
humiliation were considered excellent conflict resolution.
conflict resolution.
conflict resolution. But Aphroditi wasn't all chaos and
But Aphroditi wasn't all chaos and
But Aphroditi wasn't all chaos and cheating. She had a softer side, too.
cheating. She had a softer side, too.
cheating. She had a softer side, too. She helped young lovers, presided over
She helped young lovers, presided over
She helped young lovers, presided over weddings, and brought beauty to the
weddings, and brought beauty to the
weddings, and brought beauty to the world. She was the goddess people prayed
world. She was the goddess people prayed
world. She was the goddess people prayed to before confessing a crush or trying
to before confessing a crush or trying
to before confessing a crush or trying to charm their way out of something
to charm their way out of something
to charm their way out of something stupid. Still, she wasn't above starting
stupid. Still, she wasn't above starting
stupid. Still, she wasn't above starting wars. She's the one who offered Helen of
wars. She's the one who offered Helen of
wars. She's the one who offered Helen of Troy to Paris, sparking the Trojan War.
Troy to Paris, sparking the Trojan War.
Troy to Paris, sparking the Trojan War. Why? Because she wanted to win a divine
Why? Because she wanted to win a divine
Why? Because she wanted to win a divine beauty contest.
beauty contest.
beauty contest. Yes, really. An entire civilization
Yes, really. An entire civilization
Yes, really. An entire civilization burned because Aphroditi wanted a golden
burned because Aphroditi wanted a golden
burned because Aphroditi wanted a golden apple that said to the fairest. She's
apple that said to the fairest. She's
apple that said to the fairest. She's the patron goddess of desire, not
the patron goddess of desire, not
the patron goddess of desire, not stability.
stability.
stability. Beautiful, intoxicating, and absolutely
Beautiful, intoxicating, and absolutely
Beautiful, intoxicating, and absolutely not interested in your relationship
not interested in your relationship
not interested in your relationship boundaries. Heristas was the god of
boundaries. Heristas was the god of
boundaries. Heristas was the god of fire, metalwork, craftsmanship, and
fire, metalwork, craftsmanship, and
fire, metalwork, craftsmanship, and being the only Olympian who actually had
being the only Olympian who actually had
being the only Olympian who actually had a job. While the rest of the gods were
a job. While the rest of the gods were
a job. While the rest of the gods were busy starting wars, chasing mortals, or
busy starting wars, chasing mortals, or
busy starting wars, chasing mortals, or throwing lightning like confetti, Histus
throwing lightning like confetti, Histus
throwing lightning like confetti, Histus was in the workshop, forging weapons,
was in the workshop, forging weapons,
was in the workshop, forging weapons, building palaces, and muttering under
building palaces, and muttering under
building palaces, and muttering under his breath. His origin story varies, but
his breath. His origin story varies, but
his breath. His origin story varies, but none of it is flattering.
none of it is flattering.
none of it is flattering. In one version, he's born deformed, and
In one version, he's born deformed, and
In one version, he's born deformed, and Ha, repulsed by his appearance, tosses
Ha, repulsed by his appearance, tosses
Ha, repulsed by his appearance, tosses him off Mount Olympus like unwanted
him off Mount Olympus like unwanted
him off Mount Olympus like unwanted luggage.
luggage.
luggage. In another, Zeus does the tossing after
In another, Zeus does the tossing after
In another, Zeus does the tossing after a family argument. Either way, the man
a family argument. Either way, the man
a family argument. Either way, the man falls from heaven, lands hard, and ends
falls from heaven, lands hard, and ends
falls from heaven, lands hard, and ends up with a permanent limp and probably
up with a permanent limp and probably
up with a permanent limp and probably some abandonment issues the size of
some abandonment issues the size of
some abandonment issues the size of Cree.
Cree.
Cree. Despite the rocky start, Hisus gets back
Despite the rocky start, Hisus gets back
Despite the rocky start, Hisus gets back to Olympus, not through forgiveness, but
to Olympus, not through forgiveness, but
to Olympus, not through forgiveness, but through leverage.
through leverage.
through leverage. He crafts Hia a magical golden throne,
He crafts Hia a magical golden throne,
He crafts Hia a magical golden throne, which surprise traps her. The gods beg
which surprise traps her. The gods beg
which surprise traps her. The gods beg him to return and free her. He agrees,
him to return and free her. He agrees,
him to return and free her. He agrees, but only if they let him back into the
but only if they let him back into the
but only if they let him back into the divine club. Negotiation nailed.
divine club. Negotiation nailed.
divine club. Negotiation nailed. Now back in Olympus, Heistas becomes the
Now back in Olympus, Heistas becomes the
Now back in Olympus, Heistas becomes the divine handyman. He forges Zeus's
divine handyman. He forges Zeus's
divine handyman. He forges Zeus's thunderbolts, Poseidon's trident,
thunderbolts, Poseidon's trident,
thunderbolts, Poseidon's trident, Achilles armor, and pretty much every
Achilles armor, and pretty much every
Achilles armor, and pretty much every magical item anyone brags about. If it
magical item anyone brags about. If it
magical item anyone brags about. If it glows, flies, or explodes, Heistas
glows, flies, or explodes, Heistas
glows, flies, or explodes, Heistas probably made it while working unpaid
probably made it while working unpaid
probably made it while working unpaid over time. And yet for all his
over time. And yet for all his
over time. And yet for all his brilliance he was consistently
brilliance he was consistently
brilliance he was consistently disrespected. His wife Aphrodite
disrespected. His wife Aphrodite
disrespected. His wife Aphrodite assigned not chosen famously cheated on
assigned not chosen famously cheated on
assigned not chosen famously cheated on him with aries. His family emotionally
him with aries. His family emotionally
him with aries. His family emotionally distant to put it kindly. His co-workers
distant to put it kindly. His co-workers
distant to put it kindly. His co-workers constantly breaking the stuff he just
constantly breaking the stuff he just
constantly breaking the stuff he just fixed. But Histas never lashed out like
fixed. But Histas never lashed out like
fixed. But Histas never lashed out like Aries or schemed like Hia. His revenge
Aries or schemed like Hia. His revenge
Aries or schemed like Hia. His revenge was creative, elegant, passive
was creative, elegant, passive
was creative, elegant, passive aggressive. Even that net he used to
aggressive. Even that net he used to
aggressive. Even that net he used to catch Aphroditi and Ari's mid affair.
catch Aphroditi and Ari's mid affair.
catch Aphroditi and Ari's mid affair. Artisan crafted and designed for maximum
Artisan crafted and designed for maximum
Artisan crafted and designed for maximum public humiliation. Practical and
public humiliation. Practical and
public humiliation. Practical and poetic. He's not glamorous. He doesn't
poetic. He's not glamorous. He doesn't
poetic. He's not glamorous. He doesn't sparkle. But he's the god who built
sparkle. But he's the god who built
sparkle. But he's the god who built Olympus. Literally,
Olympus. Literally,
Olympus. Literally, Histus is the unsung hero, the
Histus is the unsung hero, the
Histus is the unsung hero, the workingclass deity of the gods, the
workingclass deity of the gods, the
workingclass deity of the gods, the patron of blacksmiths, artisans,
patron of blacksmiths, artisans,
patron of blacksmiths, artisans, inventors, and anyone who's ever
inventors, and anyone who's ever
inventors, and anyone who's ever screamed at a malfunctioning machine and
screamed at a malfunctioning machine and
screamed at a malfunctioning machine and then fixed it with duct tape and rage.
then fixed it with duct tape and rage.
then fixed it with duct tape and rage. Hermes is the god of travelers,
Hermes is the god of travelers,
Hermes is the god of travelers, commerce, thieves, messaging, and
commerce, thieves, messaging, and
commerce, thieves, messaging, and suspiciously fast talking.
suspiciously fast talking.
suspiciously fast talking. He's the guy with winged sandals, a
He's the guy with winged sandals, a
He's the guy with winged sandals, a staff that probably came with no use,
staff that probably came with no use,
staff that probably came with no use, Emanuel, and an energy that screams,
Emanuel, and an energy that screams,
Emanuel, and an energy that screams, "I've already eaten three olives and
"I've already eaten three olives and
"I've already eaten three olives and lied twice today."
lied twice today."
lied twice today." Unlike most gods, Hermes hit the ground
Unlike most gods, Hermes hit the ground
Unlike most gods, Hermes hit the ground running, literally.
running, literally.
running, literally. On the day of his birth, he crawled out
On the day of his birth, he crawled out
On the day of his birth, he crawled out of his crib, stole Apollo's cattle,
of his crib, stole Apollo's cattle,
of his crib, stole Apollo's cattle, invented the liar using a tortoise
invented the liar using a tortoise
invented the liar using a tortoise shell, and then returned to his cradle
shell, and then returned to his cradle
shell, and then returned to his cradle before anyone noticed.
before anyone noticed.
before anyone noticed. That's day one.
That's day one.
That's day one. Most gods take centuries to cause that
Most gods take centuries to cause that
Most gods take centuries to cause that much chaos.
much chaos.
much chaos. Hermes needed about 6 hours. He's known
Hermes needed about 6 hours. He's known
Hermes needed about 6 hours. He's known as the messenger of the gods, but that's
as the messenger of the gods, but that's
as the messenger of the gods, but that's underelling it. He didn't just deliver
underelling it. He didn't just deliver
underelling it. He didn't just deliver messages. He smuggled souls into the
messages. He smuggled souls into the
messages. He smuggled souls into the underworld, guided heroes through enemy
underworld, guided heroes through enemy
underworld, guided heroes through enemy territory, and probably invented the
territory, and probably invented the
territory, and probably invented the divine version of express shipping. If
divine version of express shipping. If
divine version of express shipping. If there was trouble, Hermes was already
there was trouble, Hermes was already
there was trouble, Hermes was already two steps ahead of it, leaving behind a
two steps ahead of it, leaving behind a
two steps ahead of it, leaving behind a suspiciously vague alibi and a charming
suspiciously vague alibi and a charming
suspiciously vague alibi and a charming grin. He also served as the god of
grin. He also served as the god of
grin. He also served as the god of commerce and trade because nothing says
commerce and trade because nothing says
commerce and trade because nothing says trustworthy marketplace energy like the
trustworthy marketplace energy like the
trustworthy marketplace energy like the same guy who oversees thievery. Hermes
same guy who oversees thievery. Hermes
same guy who oversees thievery. Hermes represented negotiation, persuasion, and
represented negotiation, persuasion, and
represented negotiation, persuasion, and morally flexible entrepreneurship.
morally flexible entrepreneurship.
morally flexible entrepreneurship. Basically, the patron saint of salesmen,
Basically, the patron saint of salesmen,
Basically, the patron saint of salesmen, travelers, pickpockets, and anyone who's
travelers, pickpockets, and anyone who's
travelers, pickpockets, and anyone who's ever bartered at a flea market. But he
ever bartered at a flea market. But he
ever bartered at a flea market. But he wasn't just a charming rogue. Hermes was
wasn't just a charming rogue. Hermes was
wasn't just a charming rogue. Hermes was loyal when it counted. He helped Adysius
loyal when it counted. He helped Adysius
loyal when it counted. He helped Adysius outsmart Cersei. He gave Perseus the
outsmart Cersei. He gave Perseus the
outsmart Cersei. He gave Perseus the tools to behead Medusa. He even guided
tools to behead Medusa. He even guided
tools to behead Medusa. He even guided souls to the underworld with surprising
souls to the underworld with surprising
souls to the underworld with surprising tenderness, proving that beneath all
tenderness, proving that beneath all
tenderness, proving that beneath all that mischief, he had a job he took
that mischief, he had a job he took
that mischief, he had a job he took seriously.
seriously.
seriously. Hermes also had a signature accessory,
Hermes also had a signature accessory,
Hermes also had a signature accessory, the kaducius, a winged staff with two
the kaducius, a winged staff with two
the kaducius, a winged staff with two intertwined snakes. It's often confused
intertwined snakes. It's often confused
intertwined snakes. It's often confused with the symbol of medicine, which is
with the symbol of medicine, which is
with the symbol of medicine, which is ironic considering Hermes's primary
ironic considering Hermes's primary
ironic considering Hermes's primary qualifications were speed, lying, and
qualifications were speed, lying, and
qualifications were speed, lying, and professional boundary hopping. If
professional boundary hopping. If
professional boundary hopping. If Olympus had an IT department, Hermes
Olympus had an IT department, Hermes
Olympus had an IT department, Hermes would be the overcaffeinated tech guy
would be the overcaffeinated tech guy
would be the overcaffeinated tech guy who speaks in acronyms, solves your
who speaks in acronyms, solves your
who speaks in acronyms, solves your problems in 2 minutes, and then
problems in 2 minutes, and then
problems in 2 minutes, and then disappears to go optimize cloud
disappears to go optimize cloud
disappears to go optimize cloud functions, which may or may not involve
functions, which may or may not involve
functions, which may or may not involve stealing Zeus's wallet. He's clever,
stealing Zeus's wallet. He's clever,
stealing Zeus's wallet. He's clever, quick, unreliable, and deeply lovable.
quick, unreliable, and deeply lovable.
quick, unreliable, and deeply lovable. The god of getting things done, getting
The god of getting things done, getting
The god of getting things done, getting away with it, and not answering
away with it, and not answering
away with it, and not answering follow-up questions. Deita is the
follow-up questions. Deita is the
follow-up questions. Deita is the goddess of the harvest, agriculture,
goddess of the harvest, agriculture,
goddess of the harvest, agriculture, grain, and giving life to the world,
grain, and giving life to the world,
grain, and giving life to the world, provided she's in the mood. When Deita
provided she's in the mood. When Deita
provided she's in the mood. When Deita is happy, crops flourish, trees bear
is happy, crops flourish, trees bear
is happy, crops flourish, trees bear fruit, and the world blooms with
fruit, and the world blooms with
fruit, and the world blooms with abundance. When she's upset, well, say
abundance. When she's upset, well, say
abundance. When she's upset, well, say hello to winter, famine, and general
hello to winter, famine, and general
hello to winter, famine, and general withering disappointment. She's one of
withering disappointment. She's one of
withering disappointment. She's one of the quieter Olympians. Doesn't throw
the quieter Olympians. Doesn't throw
the quieter Olympians. Doesn't throw thunderbolts, doesn't start wars,
thunderbolts, doesn't start wars,
thunderbolts, doesn't start wars, doesn't turn people into animals. But
doesn't turn people into animals. But
doesn't turn people into animals. But don't mistake quiet for harmless. She
don't mistake quiet for harmless. She
don't mistake quiet for harmless. She can shut down the planet's food supply
can shut down the planet's food supply
can shut down the planet's food supply with one bad mood, which, as it turns
with one bad mood, which, as it turns
with one bad mood, which, as it turns out, she did. Enter Pesphanie, her
out, she did. Enter Pesphanie, her
out, she did. Enter Pesphanie, her beloved daughter, the literal
beloved daughter, the literal
beloved daughter, the literal flowerchild of Olympus. One day,
flowerchild of Olympus. One day,
flowerchild of Olympus. One day, Pesphanie is out picking flowers,
Pesphanie is out picking flowers,
Pesphanie is out picking flowers, minding her own mythological business,
minding her own mythological business,
minding her own mythological business, when the earth opens up, and Hades, god
when the earth opens up, and Hades, god
when the earth opens up, and Hades, god of the underworld and professional
of the underworld and professional
of the underworld and professional kidnapper, swoops in and abducts her.
kidnapper, swoops in and abducts her.
kidnapper, swoops in and abducts her. Classic Greek parenting crisis. Dea,
Classic Greek parenting crisis. Dea,
Classic Greek parenting crisis. Dea, understandably, loses her divine mind.
understandably, loses her divine mind.
understandably, loses her divine mind. She searches the earth in grief,
She searches the earth in grief,
She searches the earth in grief, refusing to let anything grow until her
refusing to let anything grow until her
refusing to let anything grow until her daughter is returned. Crops fail.
daughter is returned. Crops fail.
daughter is returned. Crops fail. Animals starve. Mortals beg for mercy.
Animals starve. Mortals beg for mercy.
Animals starve. Mortals beg for mercy. Demet's response. No pesphanany. No
Demet's response. No pesphanany. No
Demet's response. No pesphanany. No produce.
produce.
produce. Eventually, Zeus intervenes, mostly
Eventually, Zeus intervenes, mostly
Eventually, Zeus intervenes, mostly because the humans are dying and no
because the humans are dying and no
because the humans are dying and no one's getting any sacrifices.
one's getting any sacrifices.
one's getting any sacrifices. A deal is struck. Pesphanie will spend
A deal is struck. Pesphanie will spend
A deal is struck. Pesphanie will spend part of the year with Hades, part with
part of the year with Hades, part with
part of the year with Hades, part with Deita. And thus, the seasons are born.
Deita. And thus, the seasons are born.
Deita. And thus, the seasons are born. Spring and summer, Deita's happy. fall
Spring and summer, Deita's happy. fall
Spring and summer, Deita's happy. fall and winter. She's pouting. So yes, one
and winter. She's pouting. So yes, one
and winter. She's pouting. So yes, one of the most important natural cycles in
of the most important natural cycles in
of the most important natural cycles in human existence comes from Deita's
human existence comes from Deita's
human existence comes from Deita's seasonal mood swings. Global agriculture
seasonal mood swings. Global agriculture
seasonal mood swings. Global agriculture powered by maternal grief and emotional
powered by maternal grief and emotional
powered by maternal grief and emotional blackmail. Mythology at its finest.
blackmail. Mythology at its finest.
blackmail. Mythology at its finest. Deita also had a strong sense of
Deita also had a strong sense of
Deita also had a strong sense of justice. She once taught humans how to
justice. She once taught humans how to
justice. She once taught humans how to grow wheat and build civilizations,
grow wheat and build civilizations,
grow wheat and build civilizations, then turned around and burned a royal
then turned around and burned a royal
then turned around and burned a royal baby because the parents interrupted her
baby because the parents interrupted her
baby because the parents interrupted her mid ritual. It's a fine line between
mid ritual. It's a fine line between
mid ritual. It's a fine line between goddess of life and terrifying earth
goddess of life and terrifying earth
goddess of life and terrifying earth witch. But at her core, Deita represents
witch. But at her core, Deita represents
witch. But at her core, Deita represents nurture, resilience, and the sacred bond
nurture, resilience, and the sacred bond
nurture, resilience, and the sacred bond between mother and child. She brings
between mother and child. She brings
between mother and child. She brings life from the ground and takes it away
life from the ground and takes it away
life from the ground and takes it away just as easily. Dianisis is the god of
just as easily. Dianisis is the god of
just as easily. Dianisis is the god of wine, realry, fertility, theater,
wine, realry, fertility, theater,
wine, realry, fertility, theater, madness, and those questionable
madness, and those questionable
madness, and those questionable decisions you make after your third
decisions you make after your third
decisions you make after your third glass of whatever he's pouring. He's the
glass of whatever he's pouring. He's the
glass of whatever he's pouring. He's the divine embodiment of yolo, wrapped in
divine embodiment of yolo, wrapped in
divine embodiment of yolo, wrapped in ivy, slightly intoxicated, and possibly
ivy, slightly intoxicated, and possibly
ivy, slightly intoxicated, and possibly summoning a panther. Born under very
summoning a panther. Born under very
summoning a panther. Born under very dramatic circumstances, Dionis started
dramatic circumstances, Dionis started
dramatic circumstances, Dionis started life as the child of Zeus and a mortal
life as the child of Zeus and a mortal
life as the child of Zeus and a mortal woman, Semile.
woman, Semile.
woman, Semile. When Hera found out, because of course
When Hera found out, because of course
When Hera found out, because of course she did, she tricked Semile into asking
she did, she tricked Semile into asking
she did, she tricked Semile into asking Zeus to reveal his true godly form.
Zeus to reveal his true godly form.
Zeus to reveal his true godly form. Spoiler, it vaporized her. Zeus, ever
Spoiler, it vaporized her. Zeus, ever
Spoiler, it vaporized her. Zeus, ever the problem solver, stitched the unborn
the problem solver, stitched the unborn
the problem solver, stitched the unborn Dionis into his thigh and carried him to
Dionis into his thigh and carried him to
Dionis into his thigh and carried him to term. Yes, thigh pregnancy.
term. Yes, thigh pregnancy.
term. Yes, thigh pregnancy. Greek mythology, where nothing is weird
Greek mythology, where nothing is weird
Greek mythology, where nothing is weird enough to question.
enough to question.
enough to question. Dianisis grew up wandering the earth,
Dianisis grew up wandering the earth,
Dianisis grew up wandering the earth, spreading wine- makingaking, chaotic
spreading wine- makingaking, chaotic
spreading wine- makingaking, chaotic joy, and mild existential dread. He was
joy, and mild existential dread. He was
joy, and mild existential dread. He was followed by a rowdy entourage of saters,
followed by a rowdy entourage of saters,
followed by a rowdy entourage of saters, maynads, and woodland party crashes, a
maynads, and woodland party crashes, a
maynads, and woodland party crashes, a traveling circus of ecstasy, and
traveling circus of ecstasy, and
traveling circus of ecstasy, and potential property damage. His worship
potential property damage. His worship
potential property damage. His worship wasn't just about fun and grapes.
wasn't just about fun and grapes.
wasn't just about fun and grapes. Dionian rituals involved letting go of
Dionian rituals involved letting go of
Dionian rituals involved letting go of your identity, your inhibitions, and
your identity, your inhibitions, and
your identity, your inhibitions, and sometimes your clothes. His festivals
sometimes your clothes. His festivals
sometimes your clothes. His festivals were wild, immersive, and often involved
were wild, immersive, and often involved
were wild, immersive, and often involved masks, theater, and very questionable
masks, theater, and very questionable
masks, theater, and very questionable decisions under the stars.
decisions under the stars.
decisions under the stars. Think Burning Man, but with divine
Think Burning Man, but with divine
Think Burning Man, but with divine consequences.
consequences. But Dionis wasn't all fun and fermented
But Dionis wasn't all fun and fermented
But Dionis wasn't all fun and fermented joy. He had a temper, a very theatrical
joy. He had a temper, a very theatrical
joy. He had a temper, a very theatrical one. If you mocked him, refused his
one. If you mocked him, refused his
one. If you mocked him, refused his worship, or interrupted his vibe, things
worship, or interrupted his vibe, things
worship, or interrupted his vibe, things got weird.
got weird.
got weird. One king who banned his cult was driven
One king who banned his cult was driven
One king who banned his cult was driven mad and dismembered by his own people.
mad and dismembered by his own people.
mad and dismembered by his own people. Another was turned into a dolphin. He
Another was turned into a dolphin. He
Another was turned into a dolphin. He didn't do light punishment. He did
didn't do light punishment. He did
didn't do light punishment. He did statement punishments. Yet he was also
statement punishments. Yet he was also
statement punishments. Yet he was also deeply compassionate, especially to
deeply compassionate, especially to
deeply compassionate, especially to outcasts, misfits, and those outside
outcasts, misfits, and those outside
outcasts, misfits, and those outside polite society. He gave comfort to the
polite society. He gave comfort to the
polite society. He gave comfort to the broken, voice to the silenced, and
broken, voice to the silenced, and
broken, voice to the silenced, and occasionally transformed people into
occasionally transformed people into
occasionally transformed people into vines, which is probably symbolic of
vines, which is probably symbolic of
vines, which is probably symbolic of something.
something.
something. Dianisis is the paradox of divine
Dianisis is the paradox of divine
Dianisis is the paradox of divine liberation and chaos. He's joy and
liberation and chaos. He's joy and
liberation and chaos. He's joy and destruction, art and madness. The god
destruction, art and madness. The god
destruction, art and madness. The god who blesses you with creativity one
who blesses you with creativity one
who blesses you with creativity one moment and has you dancing barefoot in a
moment and has you dancing barefoot in a
moment and has you dancing barefoot in a vineyard the next, questioning your life
vineyard the next, questioning your life
vineyard the next, questioning your life choices.
choices.
choices. Artemus is the goddess of the hunt,
Artemus is the goddess of the hunt,
Artemus is the goddess of the hunt, wilderness, wild animals, and the moon.
wilderness, wild animals, and the moon.
wilderness, wild animals, and the moon. She's also the goddess of no, I will not
She's also the goddess of no, I will not
She's also the goddess of no, I will not explain myself, and yes, that was a
explain myself, and yes, that was a
explain myself, and yes, that was a threat. Often depicted with a bow in one
threat. Often depicted with a bow in one
threat. Often depicted with a bow in one hand and zero tolerance in the other,
hand and zero tolerance in the other,
hand and zero tolerance in the other, Artemis is one of the few Olympians who
Artemis is one of the few Olympians who
Artemis is one of the few Olympians who didn't need thunderbolts or love
didn't need thunderbolts or love
didn't need thunderbolts or love potions. She had precision, discipline,
potions. She had precision, discipline,
potions. She had precision, discipline, and a pack of divine wolves.
and a pack of divine wolves.
and a pack of divine wolves. Twin sister to Apollo, Artemis arrived
Twin sister to Apollo, Artemis arrived
Twin sister to Apollo, Artemis arrived in this world in typical overachiever
in this world in typical overachiever
in this world in typical overachiever fashion. She helped deliver her own
fashion. She helped deliver her own
fashion. She helped deliver her own brother shortly after her own birth.
brother shortly after her own birth.
brother shortly after her own birth. From that moment forward, she was done
From that moment forward, she was done
From that moment forward, she was done with men. She swore off marriage,
with men. She swore off marriage,
with men. She swore off marriage, romance, and anything remotely
romance, and anything remotely
romance, and anything remotely resembling emotional vulnerability.
resembling emotional vulnerability.
resembling emotional vulnerability. Instead, she roamed forests, hunted
Instead, she roamed forests, hunted
Instead, she roamed forests, hunted stags, and surrounded herself with a
stags, and surrounded herself with a
stags, and surrounded herself with a loyal band of maiden followers who all
loyal band of maiden followers who all
loyal band of maiden followers who all shared her love for nature and
shared her love for nature and
shared her love for nature and disinterest in drama.
disinterest in drama.
disinterest in drama. Artemis is best known for her purity,
Artemis is best known for her purity,
Artemis is best known for her purity, not in a Victorian fainting couch way,
not in a Victorian fainting couch way,
not in a Victorian fainting couch way, but more in the touch me and I turn you
but more in the touch me and I turn you
but more in the touch me and I turn you into a deer way.
into a deer way.
into a deer way. Take Action for instance, a hunter who
Take Action for instance, a hunter who
Take Action for instance, a hunter who accidentally stumbled upon her bathing.
accidentally stumbled upon her bathing.
accidentally stumbled upon her bathing. Rather than calmly explain boundaries,
Rather than calmly explain boundaries,
Rather than calmly explain boundaries, she transformed him into a stag and let
she transformed him into a stag and let
she transformed him into a stag and let his own dogs tear him apart.
his own dogs tear him apart.
his own dogs tear him apart. Message received.
Message received.
Message received. She was fiercely protective, especially
She was fiercely protective, especially
She was fiercely protective, especially of women and children. While many
of women and children. While many
of women and children. While many Olympian gods treated mortals like chess
Olympian gods treated mortals like chess
Olympian gods treated mortals like chess pieces or dating apps, Artemis acted as
pieces or dating apps, Artemis acted as
pieces or dating apps, Artemis acted as a divine shield for the vulnerable. She
a divine shield for the vulnerable. She
a divine shield for the vulnerable. She punished those who disrespected sacred
punished those who disrespected sacred
punished those who disrespected sacred nature or harmed the innocent. And her
nature or harmed the innocent. And her
nature or harmed the innocent. And her vengeance was swift, poetic, and usually
vengeance was swift, poetic, and usually
vengeance was swift, poetic, and usually fatal. As a moon goddess, she
fatal. As a moon goddess, she
fatal. As a moon goddess, she represented calm, clarity, and mystery.
represented calm, clarity, and mystery.
represented calm, clarity, and mystery. She brought light to the night and
She brought light to the night and
She brought light to the night and guided travelers through darkness,
guided travelers through darkness,
guided travelers through darkness, metaphorically, and literally. If Apollo
metaphorically, and literally. If Apollo
metaphorically, and literally. If Apollo was the sun's blinding brilliance,
was the sun's blinding brilliance,
was the sun's blinding brilliance, Artemis was the moon's cold, focused
Artemis was the moon's cold, focused
Artemis was the moon's cold, focused stare. Less warmth, more watchfulness.
stare. Less warmth, more watchfulness.
stare. Less warmth, more watchfulness. She wasn't flashy, but she didn't need
She wasn't flashy, but she didn't need
She wasn't flashy, but she didn't need to be. Artemis had presence. You didn't
to be. Artemis had presence. You didn't
to be. Artemis had presence. You didn't challenge her. You didn't flirt with
challenge her. You didn't flirt with
challenge her. You didn't flirt with her. You just hoped she wasn't aiming in
her. You just hoped she wasn't aiming in
her. You just hoped she wasn't aiming in your direction. In modern terms, Artemis
your direction. In modern terms, Artemis
your direction. In modern terms, Artemis is the original independent woman.
is the original independent woman.
is the original independent woman. Fierce, free, and entirely uninterested
Fierce, free, and entirely uninterested
Fierce, free, and entirely uninterested in what you think of her. She didn't
in what you think of her. She didn't
in what you think of her. She didn't live in Olympus. She ran in the woods.
live in Olympus. She ran in the woods.
live in Olympus. She ran in the woods. Apollo is the god of the sun, music,
Apollo is the god of the sun, music,
Apollo is the god of the sun, music, prophecy, healing, poetry, archery, and
prophecy, healing, poetry, archery, and
prophecy, healing, poetry, archery, and honestly, at this point, just assume he
honestly, at this point, just assume he
honestly, at this point, just assume he put his name on every job opening on
put his name on every job opening on
put his name on every job opening on Mount Olympus. If the gods had linked
Mount Olympus. If the gods had linked
Mount Olympus. If the gods had linked in, Apollo's profile would crash the
in, Apollo's profile would crash the
in, Apollo's profile would crash the site. Twin brother of Artemis. Apollo is
site. Twin brother of Artemis. Apollo is
site. Twin brother of Artemis. Apollo is the shiny, radiant poster child of
the shiny, radiant poster child of
the shiny, radiant poster child of Olympus. Golden hair, golden liar,
Olympus. Golden hair, golden liar,
Olympus. Golden hair, golden liar, golden chariot. He's the reason we have
golden chariot. He's the reason we have
golden chariot. He's the reason we have daylight. according to Greek myth, as he
daylight. according to Greek myth, as he
daylight. according to Greek myth, as he literally drove the sun across the sky
literally drove the sun across the sky
literally drove the sun across the sky every day in a flaming chariot. No
every day in a flaming chariot. No
every day in a flaming chariot. No pressure if you're running late. But
pressure if you're running late. But
pressure if you're running late. But beneath all that brilliance lies a lot
beneath all that brilliance lies a lot
beneath all that brilliance lies a lot of
of
of feelings.
feelings.
feelings. Apollo is dramatic. He's emotional. He's
Apollo is dramatic. He's emotional. He's
Apollo is dramatic. He's emotional. He's the guy who sings ballads after a
the guy who sings ballads after a
the guy who sings ballads after a breakup and then curses the person who
breakup and then curses the person who
breakup and then curses the person who rejected him, literally. Ask Daphne. She
rejected him, literally. Ask Daphne. She
rejected him, literally. Ask Daphne. She turned into a tree just to get away from
turned into a tree just to get away from
turned into a tree just to get away from him.
him.
him. Apollo mourned her loss. Then turned her
Apollo mourned her loss. Then turned her
Apollo mourned her loss. Then turned her into a sacred symbol and wore her leaves
into a sacred symbol and wore her leaves
into a sacred symbol and wore her leaves as a crown because that's healthy. He's
as a crown because that's healthy. He's
as a crown because that's healthy. He's also the god of prophecy, which means he
also the god of prophecy, which means he
also the god of prophecy, which means he technically knows things will end badly
technically knows things will end badly
technically knows things will end badly and still gets upset when they do.
and still gets upset when they do.
and still gets upset when they do. Classic overachiever energy. He
Classic overachiever energy. He
Classic overachiever energy. He established the Oracle of Deli, where
established the Oracle of Deli, where
established the Oracle of Deli, where priestesses, fueled by divine madness,
priestesses, fueled by divine madness,
priestesses, fueled by divine madness, mumbled poetic riddles that somehow
mumbled poetic riddles that somehow
mumbled poetic riddles that somehow explained everyone's destiny. Very
explained everyone's destiny. Very
explained everyone's destiny. Very userfriendly.
userfriendly.
userfriendly. Apollo had a complicated relationship
Apollo had a complicated relationship
Apollo had a complicated relationship with love. He chased several mortals,
with love. He chased several mortals,
with love. He chased several mortals, was rejected by most, and reacted with
was rejected by most, and reacted with
was rejected by most, and reacted with varying degrees of poetic overkill. When
varying degrees of poetic overkill. When
varying degrees of poetic overkill. When a Spartan prince named Hyasinus died
a Spartan prince named Hyasinus died
a Spartan prince named Hyasinus died during a discus game, possibly from
during a discus game, possibly from
during a discus game, possibly from Apollo's own poorly thrown disc, he was
Apollo's own poorly thrown disc, he was
Apollo's own poorly thrown disc, he was so distraught he turned the boy into a
so distraught he turned the boy into a
so distraught he turned the boy into a flower, which is sweet if you ignore the
flower, which is sweet if you ignore the
flower, which is sweet if you ignore the blunt force trauma part. Despite all
blunt force trauma part. Despite all
blunt force trauma part. Despite all this, Apollo was also a healer. His son,
this, Apollo was also a healer. His son,
this, Apollo was also a healer. His son, Eskelepius, became the god of medicine,
Eskelepius, became the god of medicine,
Eskelepius, became the god of medicine, and Apollo himself could cure plagues or
and Apollo himself could cure plagues or
and Apollo himself could cure plagues or cause them, depending on how offended he
cause them, depending on how offended he
cause them, depending on how offended he felt that day. In short, Apollo was
felt that day. In short, Apollo was
felt that day. In short, Apollo was brilliance wrapped in insecurity, power
brilliance wrapped in insecurity, power
brilliance wrapped in insecurity, power dressed in poetry, and charm with a
dressed in poetry, and charm with a
dressed in poetry, and charm with a short fuse. The kind of god who'd write
short fuse. The kind of god who'd write
short fuse. The kind of god who'd write you a love song and then shoot you with
you a love song and then shoot you with
you a love song and then shoot you with an arrow if you didn't clap. Hestia is
an arrow if you didn't clap. Hestia is
an arrow if you didn't clap. Hestia is the goddess of the hearth, home, and
the goddess of the hearth, home, and
the goddess of the hearth, home, and domestic peace, which is ancient Greek
domestic peace, which is ancient Greek
domestic peace, which is ancient Greek for the only Olympian who didn't cause
for the only Olympian who didn't cause
for the only Olympian who didn't cause weekly international incidents.
weekly international incidents.
weekly international incidents. She was the eldest child of Cronis and
She was the eldest child of Cronis and
She was the eldest child of Cronis and Ria and also the first to be swallowed
Ria and also the first to be swallowed
Ria and also the first to be swallowed whole by her charmingly paranoid father.
whole by her charmingly paranoid father.
whole by her charmingly paranoid father. Later, she was the last to be vomited
Later, she was the last to be vomited
Later, she was the last to be vomited back up when Zeus overthrew him, which
back up when Zeus overthrew him, which
back up when Zeus overthrew him, which means technically she's both the oldest
means technically she's both the oldest
means technically she's both the oldest and youngest Olympian.
and youngest Olympian.
and youngest Olympian. Yes, Greek mythology is a funhouse
Yes, Greek mythology is a funhouse
Yes, Greek mythology is a funhouse mirror of logic. Unlike her more chaotic
mirror of logic. Unlike her more chaotic
mirror of logic. Unlike her more chaotic siblings, Hestia chose peace. She didn't
siblings, Hestia chose peace. She didn't
siblings, Hestia chose peace. She didn't participate in power struggles, didn't
participate in power struggles, didn't
participate in power struggles, didn't throw curses, didn't sleep with mortals,
throw curses, didn't sleep with mortals,
throw curses, didn't sleep with mortals, and didn't even throw shade. She was
and didn't even throw shade. She was
and didn't even throw shade. She was offered a throne on Olympus, shrugged
offered a throne on Olympus, shrugged
offered a throne on Olympus, shrugged politely, and gave it up to Dionis.
politely, and gave it up to Dionis.
politely, and gave it up to Dionis. Why? so she could tend the eternal flame
Why? so she could tend the eternal flame
Why? so she could tend the eternal flame and not get dragged into family drama.
and not get dragged into family drama.
and not get dragged into family drama. Queen behavior. She presided over the
Queen behavior. She presided over the
Queen behavior. She presided over the hearth, the center of every home,
hearth, the center of every home,
hearth, the center of every home, temple, and city. Wherever there was a
temple, and city. Wherever there was a
temple, and city. Wherever there was a flame burning for warmth, food, or
flame burning for warmth, food, or
flame burning for warmth, food, or ritual, Hestia was there in spirit. No
ritual, Hestia was there in spirit. No
ritual, Hestia was there in spirit. No temples in her name, no scandalous
temples in her name, no scandalous
temples in her name, no scandalous myths, just a quiet presence that made
myths, just a quiet presence that made
myths, just a quiet presence that made everything else work. The original
everything else work. The original
everything else work. The original background essential. She was also the
background essential. She was also the
background essential. She was also the goddess of hospitality. In a world where
goddess of hospitality. In a world where
goddess of hospitality. In a world where shelter and food meant survival, she
shelter and food meant survival, she
shelter and food meant survival, she represented the sacred duty of caring
represented the sacred duty of caring
represented the sacred duty of caring for guests. Invoking her meant your fire
for guests. Invoking her meant your fire
for guests. Invoking her meant your fire would stay lit, your bread wouldn't
would stay lit, your bread wouldn't
would stay lit, your bread wouldn't burn, and hopefully your relatives would
burn, and hopefully your relatives would
burn, and hopefully your relatives would leave on time. And unlike most
leave on time. And unlike most
leave on time. And unlike most Olympians, she didn't go around turning
Olympians, she didn't go around turning
Olympians, she didn't go around turning people into animals, inanimate objects,
people into animals, inanimate objects,
people into animals, inanimate objects, or ironic morality lessons.
or ironic morality lessons.
or ironic morality lessons. Hestia didn't need revenge. She had a
Hestia didn't need revenge. She had a
Hestia didn't need revenge. She had a well-swept floor and inner peace.
well-swept floor and inner peace.
well-swept floor and inner peace. Because of her, every meal began and
Because of her, every meal began and
Because of her, every meal began and ended with an offering. Every city had
ended with an offering. Every city had
ended with an offering. Every city had her flame burning in its heart. And
her flame burning in its heart. And
her flame burning in its heart. And every prayer circle probably had someone
every prayer circle probably had someone
every prayer circle probably had someone whispering, "Thank you for not being a
whispering, "Thank you for not being a
whispering, "Thank you for not being a handful." If the gods were a
handful." If the gods were a
handful." If the gods were a dysfunctional office, Zeus would be the
dysfunctional office, Zeus would be the
dysfunctional office, Zeus would be the CEO with boundary issues, Athena the
CEO with boundary issues, Athena the
CEO with boundary issues, Athena the overqualified strategist, Dionis the HR
overqualified strategist, Dionis the HR
overqualified strategist, Dionis the HR violation, and Hestia would be the calm
violation, and Hestia would be the calm
violation, and Hestia would be the calm office manager keeping the coffee warm
office manager keeping the coffee warm
office manager keeping the coffee warm and the lights on while everyone else
and the lights on while everyone else
and the lights on while everyone else argued about whose temple caught fire.
argued about whose temple caught fire.
argued about whose temple caught fire. Hestia reminds us that there's power in
Hestia reminds us that there's power in
Hestia reminds us that there's power in stillness, value in simplicity, and
stillness, value in simplicity, and
stillness, value in simplicity, and sometimes the most essential figure is
sometimes the most essential figure is
sometimes the most essential figure is the one who doesn't demand attention,
the one who doesn't demand attention,
the one who doesn't demand attention, but holds everything together.
but holds everything together.
but holds everything together. Pesphanany is one of the most
Pesphanany is one of the most
Pesphanany is one of the most fascinating figures in Greek mythology.
fascinating figures in Greek mythology.
fascinating figures in Greek mythology. A goddess with a split personality
A goddess with a split personality
A goddess with a split personality written directly into the seasons. She's
written directly into the seasons. She's
written directly into the seasons. She's the bloom of spring and the chill of
the bloom of spring and the chill of
the bloom of spring and the chill of death, life and decay,
death, life and decay,
death, life and decay, flower crown and iron throne. She's the
flower crown and iron throne. She's the
flower crown and iron throne. She's the daughter of Dita, goddess of the
daughter of Dita, goddess of the
daughter of Dita, goddess of the harvest, which already puts her in the
harvest, which already puts her in the
harvest, which already puts her in the realm of life and fertility. But then
realm of life and fertility. But then
realm of life and fertility. But then things took a turn, as they often do in
things took a turn, as they often do in
things took a turn, as they often do in Greek myth, when Hades, Lord of the
Greek myth, when Hades, Lord of the
Greek myth, when Hades, Lord of the underworld, saw her picking flowers and
underworld, saw her picking flowers and
underworld, saw her picking flowers and decided, "Wife material."
decided, "Wife material."
decided, "Wife material." He abducted her straight into the
He abducted her straight into the
He abducted her straight into the underworld. No discussion, no coffee
underworld. No discussion, no coffee
underworld. No discussion, no coffee first. Deita naturally was devastated.
first. Deita naturally was devastated.
first. Deita naturally was devastated. She scoured the earth and when no one
She scoured the earth and when no one
She scoured the earth and when no one told her where Pesphanie had gone, she
told her where Pesphanie had gone, she
told her where Pesphanie had gone, she shut down agriculture entirely. The
shut down agriculture entirely. The
shut down agriculture entirely. The result, global famine and an angry mob
result, global famine and an angry mob
result, global famine and an angry mob of hungry mortals. Eventually, Zeus
of hungry mortals. Eventually, Zeus
of hungry mortals. Eventually, Zeus intervened, not out of fatherly concern,
intervened, not out of fatherly concern,
intervened, not out of fatherly concern, but because no one was sacrificing
but because no one was sacrificing
but because no one was sacrificing anything while starving. A compromise
anything while starving. A compromise
anything while starving. A compromise was reached. Pesphanie could return if
was reached. Pesphanie could return if
was reached. Pesphanie could return if she hadn't eaten anything in the
she hadn't eaten anything in the
she hadn't eaten anything in the underworld, which of course she had. six
underworld, which of course she had. six
underworld, which of course she had. six pomegranate seeds, just enough to
pomegranate seeds, just enough to
pomegranate seeds, just enough to legally bind her to a part-time gig in
legally bind her to a part-time gig in
legally bind her to a part-time gig in the land of the dead. Thus began her
the land of the dead. Thus began her
the land of the dead. Thus began her dual role. Half the year on Earth with
dual role. Half the year on Earth with
dual role. Half the year on Earth with Deita, ushering in spring and summer,
Deita, ushering in spring and summer,
Deita, ushering in spring and summer, the other half with Hades in the
the other half with Hades in the
the other half with Hades in the underworld, giving us fall and winter.
underworld, giving us fall and winter.
underworld, giving us fall and winter. The ancient Greeks invented seasonal
The ancient Greeks invented seasonal
The ancient Greeks invented seasonal depression with a myth. But here's where
depression with a myth. But here's where
depression with a myth. But here's where things get interesting. Over time,
things get interesting. Over time,
things get interesting. Over time, Pesphanany embraced her role as queen of
Pesphanany embraced her role as queen of
Pesphanany embraced her role as queen of the dead. She wasn't just a sad
the dead. She wasn't just a sad
the dead. She wasn't just a sad kidnapped flower girl. She became a
kidnapped flower girl. She became a
kidnapped flower girl. She became a ruler, calm, firm, and quietly powerful.
ruler, calm, firm, and quietly powerful.
ruler, calm, firm, and quietly powerful. Mortals prayed to her for mercy, for
Mortals prayed to her for mercy, for
Mortals prayed to her for mercy, for safe passage, for understanding the
safe passage, for understanding the
safe passage, for understanding the balance between life and death. She
balance between life and death. She
balance between life and death. She represents transformation, not just
represents transformation, not just
represents transformation, not just seasonal, but emotional.
seasonal, but emotional.
seasonal, but emotional. The shift from innocence to strength,
The shift from innocence to strength,
The shift from innocence to strength, from being taken to taking control.
from being taken to taking control.
from being taken to taking control. Pesphanany is the goddess of duality.
Pesphanany is the goddess of duality.
Pesphanany is the goddess of duality. She walks through flowers and bones with
She walks through flowers and bones with
She walks through flowers and bones with equal grace. She's the reason flowers
equal grace. She's the reason flowers
equal grace. She's the reason flowers bloom and the reason they wilt. Before
bloom and the reason they wilt. Before
bloom and the reason they wilt. Before Psyche was even old enough to understand
Psyche was even old enough to understand
Psyche was even old enough to understand the word goddess, she was being compared
the word goddess, she was being compared
the word goddess, she was being compared to one. By the time she reached
to one. By the time she reached
to one. By the time she reached womanhood, statues of Aphroditi were
womanhood, statues of Aphroditi were
womanhood, statues of Aphroditi were gathering dust while mortals traveled
gathering dust while mortals traveled
gathering dust while mortals traveled miles just to glimpse the face of this
miles just to glimpse the face of this
miles just to glimpse the face of this mortal girl. Her beauty wasn't simply
mortal girl. Her beauty wasn't simply
mortal girl. Her beauty wasn't simply admired. It was worshiped. Entire crowds
admired. It was worshiped. Entire crowds
admired. It was worshiped. Entire crowds treated her as if she were Aphroditi,
treated her as if she were Aphroditi,
treated her as if she were Aphroditi, reincarnated in flesh and bone. People
reincarnated in flesh and bone. People
reincarnated in flesh and bone. People whispered that she must be divine, that
whispered that she must be divine, that
whispered that she must be divine, that no mortal woman could look like this by
no mortal woman could look like this by
no mortal woman could look like this by accident. But for Psyche, all the
accident. But for Psyche, all the
accident. But for Psyche, all the reverence felt hollow. She walked
reverence felt hollow. She walked
reverence felt hollow. She walked through cities and villages like a
through cities and villages like a
through cities and villages like a phantom, adored but untouched,
phantom, adored but untouched,
phantom, adored but untouched, celebrated but alone. No one dared to
celebrated but alone. No one dared to
celebrated but alone. No one dared to approach her with true affection. Men
approach her with true affection. Men
approach her with true affection. Men looked at her like a living painting,
looked at her like a living painting,
looked at her like a living painting, flawless, silent, untouchable.
flawless, silent, untouchable.
flawless, silent, untouchable. Even her family, though proud, grew
Even her family, though proud, grew
Even her family, though proud, grew uneasy. Her two sisters had married
uneasy. Her two sisters had married
uneasy. Her two sisters had married noble men, begun families, and lived the
noble men, begun families, and lived the
noble men, begun families, and lived the kind of grounded, warm lives that Psyche
kind of grounded, warm lives that Psyche
kind of grounded, warm lives that Psyche herself craved. But no suitor would dare
herself craved. But no suitor would dare
herself craved. But no suitor would dare to court a girl believed to be a rival
to court a girl believed to be a rival
to court a girl believed to be a rival of Aphrodite. And therein lay the
of Aphrodite. And therein lay the
of Aphrodite. And therein lay the danger. You see, the gods weren't fond
danger. You see, the gods weren't fond
danger. You see, the gods weren't fond of competition, especially Aphroditi.
of competition, especially Aphroditi.
of competition, especially Aphroditi. Watching her temples grow silent while
Watching her temples grow silent while
Watching her temples grow silent while mortals laid garlands at the feet of a
mortals laid garlands at the feet of a
mortals laid garlands at the feet of a mere girl made the goddess burn with
mere girl made the goddess burn with
mere girl made the goddess burn with divine rage. To her, Psyche wasn't a
divine rage. To her, Psyche wasn't a
divine rage. To her, Psyche wasn't a beautiful child. She was an insult
beautiful child. She was an insult
beautiful child. She was an insult carved into flesh. Yet Psyche knew none
carved into flesh. Yet Psyche knew none
carved into flesh. Yet Psyche knew none of this. She spent her days walking
of this. She spent her days walking
of this. She spent her days walking gardens alone, speaking to no one.
gardens alone, speaking to no one.
gardens alone, speaking to no one. She'd never felt a lover's touch or
She'd never felt a lover's touch or
She'd never felt a lover's touch or heard a whispered vow in the dark. Her
heard a whispered vow in the dark. Her
heard a whispered vow in the dark. Her beauty had become a curse, one that
beauty had become a curse, one that
beauty had become a curse, one that distanced her from the only thing she
distanced her from the only thing she
distanced her from the only thing she truly wanted, a soul that saw her, not
truly wanted, a soul that saw her, not
truly wanted, a soul that saw her, not just her face.
just her face.
just her face. She would stand by her window at dusk,
She would stand by her window at dusk,
She would stand by her window at dusk, watching the horizon fade and thinking
watching the horizon fade and thinking
watching the horizon fade and thinking perhaps this was her fate, to be loved
perhaps this was her fate, to be loved
perhaps this was her fate, to be loved by all, but held by none. No priest, no
by all, but held by none. No priest, no
by all, but held by none. No priest, no oracle, no stranger ever offered an
oracle, no stranger ever offered an
oracle, no stranger ever offered an answer until one day someone did. But it
answer until one day someone did. But it
answer until one day someone did. But it wasn't a man. It wasn't a priest. And it
wasn't a man. It wasn't a priest. And it
wasn't a man. It wasn't a priest. And it wasn't a mortal. It was a goddess. And
wasn't a mortal. It was a goddess. And
wasn't a mortal. It was a goddess. And she wasn't offering love. She was
she wasn't offering love. She was
she wasn't offering love. She was demanding revenge. On Mount Olympus,
demanding revenge. On Mount Olympus,
demanding revenge. On Mount Olympus, beauty was more than vanity. It was
beauty was more than vanity. It was
beauty was more than vanity. It was power. And no one wielded it like
power. And no one wielded it like
power. And no one wielded it like Aphroditi. She was the goddess of
Aphroditi. She was the goddess of
Aphroditi. She was the goddess of desire, of seduction, of divine charm.
desire, of seduction, of divine charm.
desire, of seduction, of divine charm. But lately, her temples echoed with
But lately, her temples echoed with
But lately, her temples echoed with emptiness. Her statue stood lonely
emptiness. Her statue stood lonely
emptiness. Her statue stood lonely beneath the sun. Why? Because mortals
beneath the sun. Why? Because mortals
beneath the sun. Why? Because mortals now knelt before a human girl, Psyche,
now knelt before a human girl, Psyche,
now knelt before a human girl, Psyche, as if she were the new goddess of love.
as if she were the new goddess of love.
as if she were the new goddess of love. To Aphrodite, this wasn't just
To Aphrodite, this wasn't just
To Aphrodite, this wasn't just offensive. It was treason.
offensive. It was treason.
offensive. It was treason. The goddess watched from her celestial
The goddess watched from her celestial
The goddess watched from her celestial perch, her envy twisting into hatred.
perch, her envy twisting into hatred.
perch, her envy twisting into hatred. She had destroyed kings for less. How
She had destroyed kings for less. How
She had destroyed kings for less. How dare a mortal girl steal her
dare a mortal girl steal her
dare a mortal girl steal her worshippers? How dare she exist as a
worshippers? How dare she exist as a
worshippers? How dare she exist as a living insult to divine beauty? And so
living insult to divine beauty? And so
living insult to divine beauty? And so Aphrodite did what goddesses do. She
Aphrodite did what goddesses do. She
Aphrodite did what goddesses do. She summoned her son, Aeros. Now Aeros
summoned her son, Aeros. Now Aeros
summoned her son, Aeros. Now Aeros wasn't just any deity. He was the god of
wasn't just any deity. He was the god of
wasn't just any deity. He was the god of love, yes, but not the soft, tender love
love, yes, but not the soft, tender love
love, yes, but not the soft, tender love mortals wrote poems about. No, Aeros
mortals wrote poems about. No, Aeros
mortals wrote poems about. No, Aeros dealt in chaos. He sparked passion where
dealt in chaos. He sparked passion where
dealt in chaos. He sparked passion where there should be none. He made kings fall
there should be none. He made kings fall
there should be none. He made kings fall for swindlers, queens for slaves,
for swindlers, queens for slaves,
for swindlers, queens for slaves, enemies for each other. His arrows
enemies for each other. His arrows
enemies for each other. His arrows didn't ask for permission. They
didn't ask for permission. They
didn't ask for permission. They shattered logic, loyalty, and sometimes
shattered logic, loyalty, and sometimes
shattered logic, loyalty, and sometimes entire empires.
entire empires.
entire empires. Aphrodites command was simple. Make
Aphrodites command was simple. Make
Aphrodites command was simple. Make Psyche fall in love with the most
Psyche fall in love with the most
Psyche fall in love with the most hideous, vile creature on Earth.
hideous, vile creature on Earth.
hideous, vile creature on Earth. Something monstrous. Something beneath
Something monstrous. Something beneath
Something monstrous. Something beneath even the worms.
even the worms.
even the worms. Let her feel what it's like to be mocked
Let her feel what it's like to be mocked
Let her feel what it's like to be mocked by love.
by love.
by love. Aeros, ever the obedient son, accepted.
Aeros, ever the obedient son, accepted.
Aeros, ever the obedient son, accepted. Bao slung over his back, quiver full of
Bao slung over his back, quiver full of
Bao slung over his back, quiver full of divine arrows. He descended to the
divine arrows. He descended to the
divine arrows. He descended to the mortal realm under the cover of
mortal realm under the cover of
mortal realm under the cover of moonlight. He found Psyche asleep in her
moonlight. He found Psyche asleep in her
moonlight. He found Psyche asleep in her chamber, candle light flickering across
chamber, candle light flickering across
chamber, candle light flickering across her features like water. She was
her features like water. She was
her features like water. She was beautiful, too beautiful. And Aeros, who
beautiful, too beautiful. And Aeros, who
beautiful, too beautiful. And Aeros, who had pierced a thousand hearts, felt his
had pierced a thousand hearts, felt his
had pierced a thousand hearts, felt his own skip a beat. This wasn't right. This
own skip a beat. This wasn't right. This
own skip a beat. This wasn't right. This wasn't part of the plan. Still, he
wasn't part of the plan. Still, he
wasn't part of the plan. Still, he reached for his arrow. But in his
reached for his arrow. But in his
reached for his arrow. But in his distraction, something went wrong. His
distraction, something went wrong. His
distraction, something went wrong. His hand slipped. The arrow pricricked his
hand slipped. The arrow pricricked his
hand slipped. The arrow pricricked his skin. Just a drop. But it was enough.
skin. Just a drop. But it was enough.
skin. Just a drop. But it was enough. The god of love had just fallen victim
The god of love had just fallen victim
The god of love had just fallen victim to his own power. And in that moment,
to his own power. And in that moment,
to his own power. And in that moment, fate shifted. For Aeros would no longer
fate shifted. For Aeros would no longer
fate shifted. For Aeros would no longer be his mother's weapon. He would be
be his mother's weapon. He would be
be his mother's weapon. He would be Psyche's silent protector. But neither
Psyche's silent protector. But neither
Psyche's silent protector. But neither of them knew what price the gods would
of them knew what price the gods would
of them knew what price the gods would demand for this forbidden affection. And
demand for this forbidden affection. And
demand for this forbidden affection. And Aphroditi would not forgive betrayal.
Aphroditi would not forgive betrayal.
Aphroditi would not forgive betrayal. Os vanished before psyche could stir
Os vanished before psyche could stir
Os vanished before psyche could stir from her sleep. The wound from his own
from her sleep. The wound from his own
from her sleep. The wound from his own arrow still warm on his skin. He had
arrow still warm on his skin. He had
arrow still warm on his skin. He had pierced countless hearts, but never once
pierced countless hearts, but never once
pierced countless hearts, but never once had he fallen prey to his own game. Now,
had he fallen prey to his own game. Now,
had he fallen prey to his own game. Now, with every beat of his heart, he felt a
with every beat of his heart, he felt a
with every beat of his heart, he felt a longing he didn't understand, a need to
longing he didn't understand, a need to
longing he didn't understand, a need to protect her, to cherish her, to hide her
protect her, to cherish her, to hide her
protect her, to cherish her, to hide her from the cruel eyes of Olympus.
from the cruel eyes of Olympus.
from the cruel eyes of Olympus. But protection came with sacrifice. He
But protection came with sacrifice. He
But protection came with sacrifice. He couldn't tell her the truth. If
couldn't tell her the truth. If
couldn't tell her the truth. If Aphrodite discovered he had disobeyed
Aphrodite discovered he had disobeyed
Aphrodite discovered he had disobeyed her, worse, that he had fallen in love,
her, worse, that he had fallen in love,
her, worse, that he had fallen in love, there would be no mercy. Not for him,
there would be no mercy. Not for him,
there would be no mercy. Not for him, not for Psyche.
not for Psyche.
not for Psyche. So, Aeros made a quiet vow. He would
So, Aeros made a quiet vow. He would
So, Aeros made a quiet vow. He would love her from the shadows. Meanwhile,
love her from the shadows. Meanwhile,
love her from the shadows. Meanwhile, Psyche's life grew stranger by the day.
Psyche's life grew stranger by the day.
Psyche's life grew stranger by the day. No suitors came. Her beauty, once a
No suitors came. Her beauty, once a
No suitors came. Her beauty, once a spectacle, now seemed cursed. Whispers
spectacle, now seemed cursed. Whispers
spectacle, now seemed cursed. Whispers of divine punishment swirled through the
of divine punishment swirled through the
of divine punishment swirled through the kingdom. Her father, desperate and
kingdom. Her father, desperate and
kingdom. Her father, desperate and afraid, consulted the oracle of Apollo,
afraid, consulted the oracle of Apollo,
afraid, consulted the oracle of Apollo, and the words returned were cruel. She
and the words returned were cruel. She
and the words returned were cruel. She shall not wed a mortal man. Instead, she
shall not wed a mortal man. Instead, she
shall not wed a mortal man. Instead, she will marry a monster, a beast feared
will marry a monster, a beast feared
will marry a monster, a beast feared even by the gods. Send her to the
even by the gods. Send her to the
even by the gods. Send her to the mountaintop, dressed as a bride. There,
mountaintop, dressed as a bride. There,
mountaintop, dressed as a bride. There, her fate awaits. Her family wept. Her
her fate awaits. Her family wept. Her
her fate awaits. Her family wept. Her sisters gasped, but Psyche stood still,
sisters gasped, but Psyche stood still,
sisters gasped, but Psyche stood still, silent, as if the wind had carved her
silent, as if the wind had carved her
silent, as if the wind had carved her into stone. A monster. This was her
into stone. A monster. This was her
into stone. A monster. This was her destiny. Not love, not choice, but
destiny. Not love, not choice, but
destiny. Not love, not choice, but sacrifice. Still she agreed, not out of
sacrifice. Still she agreed, not out of
sacrifice. Still she agreed, not out of courage, but out of resignation. She had
courage, but out of resignation. She had
courage, but out of resignation. She had been adored like a goddess, yet never
been adored like a goddess, yet never
been adored like a goddess, yet never touched by love. Perhaps this, this
touched by love. Perhaps this, this
touched by love. Perhaps this, this cruel, monstrous fate was simply
cruel, monstrous fate was simply
cruel, monstrous fate was simply balance.
balance.
balance. Aos watched from above, his heart
Aos watched from above, his heart
Aos watched from above, his heart twisting with guilt. He had meant to
twisting with guilt. He had meant to
twisting with guilt. He had meant to protect her, but now the gods had spun a
protect her, but now the gods had spun a
protect her, but now the gods had spun a web he couldn't untangle. If he
web he couldn't untangle. If he
web he couldn't untangle. If he intervened openly, his mother would
intervened openly, his mother would
intervened openly, his mother would know. But if he did nothing, Psyche
know. But if he did nothing, Psyche
know. But if he did nothing, Psyche would be lost. So he devised a plan. He
would be lost. So he devised a plan. He
would be lost. So he devised a plan. He would take her to a secret place, a
would take her to a secret place, a
would take her to a secret place, a hidden palace known only to him, cloaked
hidden palace known only to him, cloaked
hidden palace known only to him, cloaked in illusion and silence. He would love
in illusion and silence. He would love
in illusion and silence. He would love her, not as a god, but as a shadow. He
her, not as a god, but as a shadow. He
her, not as a god, but as a shadow. He would never show his face, never speak
would never show his face, never speak
would never show his face, never speak his name, and above all, he would never
his name, and above all, he would never
his name, and above all, he would never tell her the truth. Because if she knew
tell her the truth. Because if she knew
tell her the truth. Because if she knew who he was, who she was truly with,
who he was, who she was truly with,
who he was, who she was truly with, everything would shatter. Even the god
everything would shatter. Even the god
everything would shatter. Even the god of love was afraid of heartbreak. The
of love was afraid of heartbreak. The
of love was afraid of heartbreak. The wind was soft but strong as it carried
wind was soft but strong as it carried
wind was soft but strong as it carried Psyche away from the mountain peak. She
Psyche away from the mountain peak. She
Psyche away from the mountain peak. She had expected cold rock and nashing
had expected cold rock and nashing
had expected cold rock and nashing teeth. She had braced for a monster's
teeth. She had braced for a monster's
teeth. She had braced for a monster's roar, but instead silence,
roar, but instead silence,
roar, but instead silence, gentle, surreal silence.
gentle, surreal silence.
gentle, surreal silence. When she opened her eyes, she was no
When she opened her eyes, she was no
When she opened her eyes, she was no longer on the mountain. She stood in a
longer on the mountain. She stood in a
longer on the mountain. She stood in a meadow of glowing flowers, more radiant
meadow of glowing flowers, more radiant
meadow of glowing flowers, more radiant than any garden she had ever known. A
than any garden she had ever known. A
than any garden she had ever known. A path of polished stone wound through the
path of polished stone wound through the
path of polished stone wound through the field, leading to something impossible,
field, leading to something impossible,
field, leading to something impossible, a palace, grander than anything human
a palace, grander than anything human
a palace, grander than anything human hands could build. Its pillars
hands could build. Its pillars
hands could build. Its pillars shimmerred like moonlight on water. Its
shimmerred like moonlight on water. Its
shimmerred like moonlight on water. Its halls whispered her name without sound.
halls whispered her name without sound.
halls whispered her name without sound. Psyche stepped through the threshold,
Psyche stepped through the threshold,
Psyche stepped through the threshold, expecting fear, but finding peace.
expecting fear, but finding peace.
expecting fear, but finding peace. Servants she couldn't see guided her
Servants she couldn't see guided her
Servants she couldn't see guided her hands, washed her feet, placed robes
hands, washed her feet, placed robes
hands, washed her feet, placed robes upon her shoulders. Food appeared, warm
upon her shoulders. Food appeared, warm
upon her shoulders. Food appeared, warm and fragrant, though no one set the
and fragrant, though no one set the
and fragrant, though no one set the table. At night, a voice, deep, tender,
table. At night, a voice, deep, tender,
table. At night, a voice, deep, tender, and kind, spoke from the shadows.
and kind, spoke from the shadows.
and kind, spoke from the shadows. Do not be afraid. You are safe. This is
Do not be afraid. You are safe. This is
Do not be afraid. You are safe. This is your home. It was him, her unseen
your home. It was him, her unseen
your home. It was him, her unseen husband, the one the oracle had
husband, the one the oracle had
husband, the one the oracle had promised. But there was no snarling
promised. But there was no snarling
promised. But there was no snarling beast, no monstrous form, just a voice.
beast, no monstrous form, just a voice.
beast, no monstrous form, just a voice. And strangely, it didn't frighten her.
And strangely, it didn't frighten her.
And strangely, it didn't frighten her. He never revealed himself, not even in
He never revealed himself, not even in
He never revealed himself, not even in darkness. Each night he joined her in
darkness. Each night he joined her in
darkness. Each night he joined her in the quiet velvet of the bed chamber. He
the quiet velvet of the bed chamber. He
the quiet velvet of the bed chamber. He touched her face like a dream. He
touched her face like a dream. He
touched her face like a dream. He whispered laughter in her ear. And each
whispered laughter in her ear. And each
whispered laughter in her ear. And each morning, he was gone before the sun
morning, he was gone before the sun
morning, he was gone before the sun rose. She was falling fast. Love without
rose. She was falling fast. Love without
rose. She was falling fast. Love without sight, intimacy without form. Each word
sight, intimacy without form. Each word
sight, intimacy without form. Each word he spoke made her ache for more. But the
he spoke made her ache for more. But the
he spoke made her ache for more. But the one thing he always begged was this.
one thing he always begged was this.
one thing he always begged was this. Never try to see me. She asked once
Never try to see me. She asked once
Never try to see me. She asked once gently, "Why?" The voice tensed, "If you
gently, "Why?" The voice tensed, "If you
gently, "Why?" The voice tensed, "If you see me, I must leave you forever." And
see me, I must leave you forever." And
see me, I must leave you forever." And so she obeyed. But the mystery grew
so she obeyed. But the mystery grew
so she obeyed. But the mystery grew heavier with each passing day. How could
heavier with each passing day. How could
heavier with each passing day. How could such a kind, thoughtful man be the
such a kind, thoughtful man be the
such a kind, thoughtful man be the monster the oracle warned of? Why must
monster the oracle warned of? Why must
monster the oracle warned of? Why must love hide its face? And why, when she
love hide its face? And why, when she
love hide its face? And why, when she whispered her name, did he never whisper
whispered her name, did he never whisper
whispered her name, did he never whisper his? Psyche told herself it didn't
his? Psyche told herself it didn't
his? Psyche told herself it didn't matter, that she didn't need to know.
matter, that she didn't need to know.
matter, that she didn't need to know. But the human heart is a curious thing.
But the human heart is a curious thing.
But the human heart is a curious thing. And the seeds of doubt, once planted,
And the seeds of doubt, once planted,
And the seeds of doubt, once planted, never stay buried for long, especially
never stay buried for long, especially
never stay buried for long, especially when family comes to visit. and
when family comes to visit. and
when family comes to visit. and especially when sisters come bearing
especially when sisters come bearing
especially when sisters come bearing poison disguised as love. It had been
poison disguised as love. It had been
poison disguised as love. It had been weeks, perhaps months. Time moved
weeks, perhaps months. Time moved
weeks, perhaps months. Time moved strangely in the invisible palace.
strangely in the invisible palace.
strangely in the invisible palace. Psyche knew peace, laughter, luxury, and
Psyche knew peace, laughter, luxury, and
Psyche knew peace, laughter, luxury, and love. But she also knew isolation. No
love. But she also knew isolation. No
love. But she also knew isolation. No faces, no names, no truth, just a voice
faces, no names, no truth, just a voice
faces, no names, no truth, just a voice in the dark and shadows that kissed her
in the dark and shadows that kissed her
in the dark and shadows that kissed her lips. Then one morning, her husband's
lips. Then one morning, her husband's
lips. Then one morning, her husband's voice was different.
voice was different.
voice was different. Sorrow will follow if you see them, he
Sorrow will follow if you see them, he
Sorrow will follow if you see them, he said. See who? Your sisters. They
said. See who? Your sisters. They
said. See who? Your sisters. They believe they come out of love. But what
believe they come out of love. But what
believe they come out of love. But what they bring is ruin.
they bring is ruin.
they bring is ruin. Psyche's heart cracked. She missed them.
Psyche's heart cracked. She missed them.
Psyche's heart cracked. She missed them. Their teasing, their warmth, even their
Their teasing, their warmth, even their
Their teasing, their warmth, even their jealousy. They were her last connection
jealousy. They were her last connection
jealousy. They were her last connection to the mortal world, to the girl she
to the mortal world, to the girl she
to the mortal world, to the girl she used to be before gods and palaces and
used to be before gods and palaces and
used to be before gods and palaces and mystery husbands. She pleaded, "Let me
mystery husbands. She pleaded, "Let me
mystery husbands. She pleaded, "Let me see them, please. just once. Aos
see them, please. just once. Aos
see them, please. just once. Aos hesitated, but he could never deny her.
hesitated, but he could never deny her.
hesitated, but he could never deny her. He agreed with one warning. Do not let
He agreed with one warning. Do not let
He agreed with one warning. Do not let their words poison what we have. They
their words poison what we have. They
their words poison what we have. They will try to unravel your trust. You must
will try to unravel your trust. You must
will try to unravel your trust. You must not listen. And so the winds that once
not listen. And so the winds that once
not listen. And so the winds that once lifted Psyche carried her sisters to the
lifted Psyche carried her sisters to the
lifted Psyche carried her sisters to the garden gates of the invisible palace.
garden gates of the invisible palace.
garden gates of the invisible palace. When they saw her, they were stunned.
When they saw her, they were stunned.
When they saw her, they were stunned. She was alive, more than alive, radiant,
She was alive, more than alive, radiant,
She was alive, more than alive, radiant, draped in silks finer than any queen,
draped in silks finer than any queen,
draped in silks finer than any queen, her skin glowing like starlight.
her skin glowing like starlight.
her skin glowing like starlight. They embraced her, laughing nervously,
They embraced her, laughing nervously,
They embraced her, laughing nervously, hiding their envy beneath brittle
hiding their envy beneath brittle
hiding their envy beneath brittle smiles. "Where is your husband?" one
smiles. "Where is your husband?" one
smiles. "Where is your husband?" one asked. Psyche smiled. "He comes only at
asked. Psyche smiled. "He comes only at
asked. Psyche smiled. "He comes only at night. I've never seen him." The sisters
night. I've never seen him." The sisters
night. I've never seen him." The sisters froze. "You've never seen him?" she
froze. "You've never seen him?" she
froze. "You've never seen him?" she nodded. He won't let you see his face.
nodded. He won't let you see his face.
nodded. He won't let you see his face. The other gasped. What if he's hideous?
The other gasped. What if he's hideous?
The other gasped. What if he's hideous? A beast? Or worse, what if he's one of
A beast? Or worse, what if he's one of
A beast? Or worse, what if he's one of the gods using you and laughing behind
the gods using you and laughing behind
the gods using you and laughing behind your back?
your back?
your back? Their voices dripped with sweet concern,
Their voices dripped with sweet concern,
Their voices dripped with sweet concern, but Psyche felt the change. The old
but Psyche felt the change. The old
but Psyche felt the change. The old sibling rivalry was still there, now
sibling rivalry was still there, now
sibling rivalry was still there, now twisted into something darker.
twisted into something darker.
twisted into something darker. Jealousy sharpened their words. "He
Jealousy sharpened their words. "He
Jealousy sharpened their words. "He keeps you hidden, blind, dependent. Is
keeps you hidden, blind, dependent. Is
keeps you hidden, blind, dependent. Is that love or imprisonment?
that love or imprisonment?
that love or imprisonment? The seed of doubt was planted. They saw
The seed of doubt was planted. They saw
The seed of doubt was planted. They saw it take root and they smiled. As they
it take root and they smiled. As they
it take root and they smiled. As they left, they kissed her cheeks and
left, they kissed her cheeks and
left, they kissed her cheeks and whispered, "Just take a lamp one night.
whispered, "Just take a lamp one night.
whispered, "Just take a lamp one night. See for yourself. If he loves you, what
See for yourself. If he loves you, what
See for yourself. If he loves you, what harm can truth do?" Psyche watched them
harm can truth do?" Psyche watched them
harm can truth do?" Psyche watched them disappear into the wind. And for the
disappear into the wind. And for the
disappear into the wind. And for the first time since arriving in paradise,
first time since arriving in paradise,
first time since arriving in paradise, she couldn't stop shaking. Not from
she couldn't stop shaking. Not from
she couldn't stop shaking. Not from fear, from curiosity.
fear, from curiosity.
fear, from curiosity. That night, Psyche couldn't sleep. She
That night, Psyche couldn't sleep. She
That night, Psyche couldn't sleep. She lay in the dark, wrapped in silk sheets,
lay in the dark, wrapped in silk sheets,
lay in the dark, wrapped in silk sheets, his arms gently curled around her, his
his arms gently curled around her, his
his arms gently curled around her, his breath steady beside hers, but her mind
breath steady beside hers, but her mind
breath steady beside hers, but her mind was loud, louder than his heart, louder
was loud, louder than his heart, louder
was loud, louder than his heart, louder than love. Her sister's words kept
than love. Her sister's words kept
than love. Her sister's words kept repeating like a spell. What if he's a
repeating like a spell. What if he's a
repeating like a spell. What if he's a monster? What if he's using you? What if
monster? What if he's using you? What if
monster? What if he's using you? What if he's not who you think he is?
he's not who you think he is?
he's not who you think he is? She had trusted blindly. She had given
She had trusted blindly. She had given
She had trusted blindly. She had given herself completely to a voice in the
herself completely to a voice in the
herself completely to a voice in the dark. But was that love or simply
dark. But was that love or simply
dark. But was that love or simply surrender? She slipped from the bed,
surrender? She slipped from the bed,
surrender? She slipped from the bed, silent as snowfall. Her bare feet kissed
silent as snowfall. Her bare feet kissed
silent as snowfall. Her bare feet kissed the cold floor, and in her hand she held
the cold floor, and in her hand she held
the cold floor, and in her hand she held a small bronze oil lamp, its wick
a small bronze oil lamp, its wick
a small bronze oil lamp, its wick already lit. Her heart thundered in her
already lit. Her heart thundered in her
already lit. Her heart thundered in her chest as she approached. Her fingers
chest as she approached. Her fingers
chest as she approached. Her fingers trembled as she leaned in. And when the
trembled as she leaned in. And when the
trembled as she leaned in. And when the light reached his face, she gasped. Not
light reached his face, she gasped. Not
light reached his face, she gasped. Not a monster, not a god in disguise. A man
a monster, not a god in disguise. A man
a monster, not a god in disguise. A man beautiful beyond words. Golden curls
beautiful beyond words. Golden curls
beautiful beyond words. Golden curls tangled on the pillow, soft lips curved
tangled on the pillow, soft lips curved
tangled on the pillow, soft lips curved in sleep, and on his back, wings
in sleep, and on his back, wings
in sleep, and on his back, wings feathered, divine, folded like a secret.
feathered, divine, folded like a secret.
feathered, divine, folded like a secret. This was OS, the god of love, and he had
This was OS, the god of love, and he had
This was OS, the god of love, and he had chosen her. her eyes filled with tears,
chosen her. her eyes filled with tears,
chosen her. her eyes filled with tears, not from fear, but from guilt. He had
not from fear, but from guilt. He had
not from fear, but from guilt. He had trusted her, warned her, loved her, and
trusted her, warned her, loved her, and
trusted her, warned her, loved her, and she had doubted. She leaned closer,
she had doubted. She leaned closer,
she had doubted. She leaned closer, wanting to kiss his lips, to whisper an
wanting to kiss his lips, to whisper an
wanting to kiss his lips, to whisper an apology before the light was gone. But
apology before the light was gone. But
apology before the light was gone. But fate is cruel. A single drop of hot oil
fate is cruel. A single drop of hot oil
fate is cruel. A single drop of hot oil spilled from the lamp and touched his
spilled from the lamp and touched his
spilled from the lamp and touched his bare shoulder. He awoke with a cry of
bare shoulder. He awoke with a cry of
bare shoulder. He awoke with a cry of pain and betrayal. His wings flared
pain and betrayal. His wings flared
pain and betrayal. His wings flared open, his eyes wide with heartbreak.
open, his eyes wide with heartbreak.
open, his eyes wide with heartbreak. "You broke your promise," he said, voice
"You broke your promise," he said, voice
"You broke your promise," he said, voice hollow. "You trusted fear more than
hollow. "You trusted fear more than
hollow. "You trusted fear more than love." "I'm sorry," Psyche whispered,
love." "I'm sorry," Psyche whispered,
love." "I'm sorry," Psyche whispered, falling to her knees. "I just wanted to
falling to her knees. "I just wanted to
falling to her knees. "I just wanted to know," Aeros stepped back, his glow
know," Aeros stepped back, his glow
know," Aeros stepped back, his glow dimming. "Now you do." And with that, he
dimming. "Now you do." And with that, he
dimming. "Now you do." And with that, he vanished into the darkness.
vanished into the darkness.
vanished into the darkness. The palace crumbled behind him. The
The palace crumbled behind him. The
The palace crumbled behind him. The invisible world they'd shared unraveled
invisible world they'd shared unraveled
invisible world they'd shared unraveled like smoke.
like smoke.
like smoke. Psyche was left alone on a barren
Psyche was left alone on a barren
Psyche was left alone on a barren hillside, the lamp still warm in her
hillside, the lamp still warm in her
hillside, the lamp still warm in her hand and her heart shattered. She had
hand and her heart shattered. She had
hand and her heart shattered. She had seen the god of love and lost him, not
seen the god of love and lost him, not
seen the god of love and lost him, not to fate, but to doubt. Psyche wandered
to fate, but to doubt. Psyche wandered
to fate, but to doubt. Psyche wandered barefoot and broken across a world that
barefoot and broken across a world that
barefoot and broken across a world that suddenly seemed colder. The lush
suddenly seemed colder. The lush
suddenly seemed colder. The lush gardens, the silken halls, the voice
gardens, the silken halls, the voice
gardens, the silken halls, the voice that once lulled her to sleep, gone. The
that once lulled her to sleep, gone. The
that once lulled her to sleep, gone. The sky offered no answer. The earth gave no
sky offered no answer. The earth gave no
sky offered no answer. The earth gave no comfort. Only her regret remained. Each
comfort. Only her regret remained. Each
comfort. Only her regret remained. Each step was heavy with sorrow. She called
step was heavy with sorrow. She called
step was heavy with sorrow. She called out to Os in forests, in fields, in
out to Os in forests, in fields, in
out to Os in forests, in fields, in rivers, even in dreams. But there was no
rivers, even in dreams. But there was no
rivers, even in dreams. But there was no reply. The god of love had vanished, not
reply. The god of love had vanished, not
reply. The god of love had vanished, not from Olympus, but from her life. In
from Olympus, but from her life. In
from Olympus, but from her life. In desperation, Psyche returned to her
desperation, Psyche returned to her
desperation, Psyche returned to her father's home. But the palace that once
father's home. But the palace that once
father's home. But the palace that once cherished her now whispered with rumors.
cherished her now whispered with rumors.
cherished her now whispered with rumors. Her sisters, triumphant in her misery,
Her sisters, triumphant in her misery,
Her sisters, triumphant in her misery, claimed she had married a demon and lost
claimed she had married a demon and lost
claimed she had married a demon and lost everything. No one believed her tale of
everything. No one believed her tale of
everything. No one believed her tale of love and gods and winged husbands. So
love and gods and winged husbands. So
love and gods and winged husbands. So she left again. This time not out of
she left again. This time not out of
she left again. This time not out of exile, but purpose. She would find OS,
exile, but purpose. She would find OS,
exile, but purpose. She would find OS, no matter how far she had to go, no
no matter how far she had to go, no
no matter how far she had to go, no matter what wrath she might face, even
matter what wrath she might face, even
matter what wrath she might face, even if it meant entering Olympus itself. But
if it meant entering Olympus itself. But
if it meant entering Olympus itself. But mortals don't simply walk into the
mortals don't simply walk into the
mortals don't simply walk into the heavens. So, she sought the only one who
heavens. So, she sought the only one who
heavens. So, she sought the only one who might guide her path, the one who had
might guide her path, the one who had
might guide her path, the one who had started it all, Aphroditi.
started it all, Aphroditi.
started it all, Aphroditi. Yes, Psyche was afraid. The goddess had
Yes, Psyche was afraid. The goddess had
Yes, Psyche was afraid. The goddess had reason to hate her. But if Aeros still
reason to hate her. But if Aeros still
reason to hate her. But if Aeros still loved her, if there was even a sliver of
loved her, if there was even a sliver of
loved her, if there was even a sliver of hope, then Psyche would face even the
hope, then Psyche would face even the
hope, then Psyche would face even the wrath of Olympus to earn redemption.
wrath of Olympus to earn redemption.
wrath of Olympus to earn redemption. She found Aphrodite not in a golden
She found Aphrodite not in a golden
She found Aphrodite not in a golden temple, but in a private garden
temple, but in a private garden
temple, but in a private garden surrounded by mirrors. The goddess
surrounded by mirrors. The goddess
surrounded by mirrors. The goddess looked into her own reflection as if
looked into her own reflection as if
looked into her own reflection as if searching for floors that didn't exist.
searching for floors that didn't exist.
searching for floors that didn't exist. When Psyche approached, Aphrodite didn't
When Psyche approached, Aphrodite didn't
When Psyche approached, Aphrodite didn't turn. "I warned you once," the goddess
turn. "I warned you once," the goddess
turn. "I warned you once," the goddess said coldly. And still you touched what
said coldly. And still you touched what
said coldly. And still you touched what was mine.
was mine.
was mine. Psyche knelt. I love him. Aphrodite
Psyche knelt. I love him. Aphrodite
Psyche knelt. I love him. Aphrodite laughed. You love him? You mean the son
laughed. You love him? You mean the son
laughed. You love him? You mean the son you betrayed? The god you doubted? I was
you betrayed? The god you doubted? I was
you betrayed? The god you doubted? I was foolish, Psyche admitted. But I will do
foolish, Psyche admitted. But I will do
foolish, Psyche admitted. But I will do anything to earn back his trust.
anything to earn back his trust.
anything to earn back his trust. Aphrodite turned, her eyes sharp as
Aphrodite turned, her eyes sharp as
Aphrodite turned, her eyes sharp as blades. Anything?
blades. Anything?
blades. Anything? Psyche nodded. The goddess smiled, but
Psyche nodded. The goddess smiled, but
Psyche nodded. The goddess smiled, but it was not kind. then you will suffer.
it was not kind. then you will suffer.
it was not kind. then you will suffer. You will be tested. And perhaps perhaps
You will be tested. And perhaps perhaps
You will be tested. And perhaps perhaps at the end of your agony, you'll be
at the end of your agony, you'll be
at the end of your agony, you'll be worthy of my son. Thus began a trial not
worthy of my son. Thus began a trial not
worthy of my son. Thus began a trial not of strength, but of devotion, and Psyche
of strength, but of devotion, and Psyche
of strength, but of devotion, and Psyche would have to face it alone. Aphrodite
would have to face it alone. Aphrodite
would have to face it alone. Aphrodite didn't waste time. Her beauty was
didn't waste time. Her beauty was
didn't waste time. Her beauty was legendary, but her cruelty, when
legendary, but her cruelty, when
legendary, but her cruelty, when provoked, was equally divine. If Psyche
provoked, was equally divine. If Psyche
provoked, was equally divine. If Psyche wanted even a chance to see Aeros again,
wanted even a chance to see Aeros again,
wanted even a chance to see Aeros again, she would have to prove her worth
she would have to prove her worth
she would have to prove her worth through a series of impossible trials.
through a series of impossible trials.
through a series of impossible trials. The first task was deceptively simple.
The first task was deceptively simple.
The first task was deceptively simple. Aphroditi led her to a vast storage
Aphroditi led her to a vast storage
Aphroditi led her to a vast storage chamber where mountains of seeds spilled
chamber where mountains of seeds spilled
chamber where mountains of seeds spilled across the floor. Barley, millet,
across the floor. Barley, millet,
across the floor. Barley, millet, lentils, poppy, wheat, and beans all
lentils, poppy, wheat, and beans all
lentils, poppy, wheat, and beans all mixed together into an indistinguishable
mixed together into an indistinguishable
mixed together into an indistinguishable chaos.
chaos.
chaos. By nightfall, Aphrodite said with a
By nightfall, Aphrodite said with a
By nightfall, Aphrodite said with a yawn, "Separate them, every grain, every
yawn, "Separate them, every grain, every
yawn, "Separate them, every grain, every seed, into its proper pile. If you fail,
seed, into its proper pile. If you fail,
seed, into its proper pile. If you fail, you'll never see my son again." Then she
you'll never see my son again." Then she
you'll never see my son again." Then she left, humming to herself. Psyche stared
left, humming to herself. Psyche stared
left, humming to herself. Psyche stared at the impossible task. Even a thousand
at the impossible task. Even a thousand
at the impossible task. Even a thousand hands wouldn't be enough to sort such a
hands wouldn't be enough to sort such a
hands wouldn't be enough to sort such a mess in a day. She knelt anyway and
mess in a day. She knelt anyway and
mess in a day. She knelt anyway and began, picking seed after seed, her
began, picking seed after seed, her
began, picking seed after seed, her fingers shaking. Minutes passed like
fingers shaking. Minutes passed like
fingers shaking. Minutes passed like hours. Her eyes blurred. She wasn't even
hours. Her eyes blurred. She wasn't even
hours. Her eyes blurred. She wasn't even a fraction of the way through. But the
a fraction of the way through. But the
a fraction of the way through. But the gods are always watching. And so are
gods are always watching. And so are
gods are always watching. And so are their creatures.
their creatures.
their creatures. Unseen by psyche, a line of ants had
Unseen by psyche, a line of ants had
Unseen by psyche, a line of ants had been watching her toil. Not just any
been watching her toil. Not just any
been watching her toil. Not just any ants, these were sacred to Deita,
ants, these were sacred to Deita,
ants, these were sacred to Deita, goddess of the harvest. Perhaps they
goddess of the harvest. Perhaps they
goddess of the harvest. Perhaps they pied the girl. Perhaps they were moved
pied the girl. Perhaps they were moved
pied the girl. Perhaps they were moved by love. In a sudden flurry of motion,
by love. In a sudden flurry of motion,
by love. In a sudden flurry of motion, hundreds of tiny legs raced across the
hundreds of tiny legs raced across the
hundreds of tiny legs raced across the floor. The ants formed living rivers,
floor. The ants formed living rivers,
floor. The ants formed living rivers, dividing the seeds with shocking
dividing the seeds with shocking
dividing the seeds with shocking precision. In minutes, the chaos became
precision. In minutes, the chaos became
precision. In minutes, the chaos became order. Barley to one side, lentils to
order. Barley to one side, lentils to
order. Barley to one side, lentils to another, millet in neat pyramids. It was
another, millet in neat pyramids. It was
another, millet in neat pyramids. It was like watching nature itself rewrite the
like watching nature itself rewrite the
like watching nature itself rewrite the laws of time. When Aphrodite returned at
laws of time. When Aphrodite returned at
laws of time. When Aphrodite returned at dusk, she was met not with failure, but
dusk, she was met not with failure, but
dusk, she was met not with failure, but perfection. She narrowed her eyes. "You
perfection. She narrowed her eyes. "You
perfection. She narrowed her eyes. "You had help," she snapped. Psyche bowed her
had help," she snapped. Psyche bowed her
had help," she snapped. Psyche bowed her head. "I only did what I could."
head. "I only did what I could."
head. "I only did what I could." Aphrodite's lips twitched with something
Aphrodite's lips twitched with something
Aphrodite's lips twitched with something between anger and amusement. She hadn't
between anger and amusement. She hadn't
between anger and amusement. She hadn't expected the mortal girl to complete the
expected the mortal girl to complete the
expected the mortal girl to complete the task, much less with grace. But no
task, much less with grace. But no
task, much less with grace. But no matter, there were still many more
matter, there were still many more
matter, there were still many more trials to go, harder ones, deadlier
trials to go, harder ones, deadlier
trials to go, harder ones, deadlier ones. "This was only the beginning," the
ones. "This was only the beginning," the
ones. "This was only the beginning," the goddess warned. If you want to see Aeros
goddess warned. If you want to see Aeros
goddess warned. If you want to see Aeros again, you'll need more than luck. And
again, you'll need more than luck. And
again, you'll need more than luck. And yet Psyche, exhausted, sore, but
yet Psyche, exhausted, sore, but
yet Psyche, exhausted, sore, but standing, nodded.
standing, nodded.
standing, nodded. I'll do whatever it takes.
I'll do whatever it takes.
I'll do whatever it takes. Because love, true love, was worth more
Because love, true love, was worth more
Because love, true love, was worth more than divine comfort or mortal pride. And
than divine comfort or mortal pride. And
than divine comfort or mortal pride. And Psyche's war had only just begun. Psyche
Psyche's war had only just begun. Psyche
Psyche's war had only just begun. Psyche barely had time to rest before Aphrodite
barely had time to rest before Aphrodite
barely had time to rest before Aphrodite handed her the second task. This one
handed her the second task. This one
handed her the second task. This one even cruer in its design.
even cruer in its design.
even cruer in its design. See that river down there?" the goddess
See that river down there?" the goddess
See that river down there?" the goddess asked, pointing to a winding stream
asked, pointing to a winding stream
asked, pointing to a winding stream glinting beneath the afternoon sun. It
glinting beneath the afternoon sun. It
glinting beneath the afternoon sun. It runs beside a meadow where wild rams
runs beside a meadow where wild rams
runs beside a meadow where wild rams graze. Their wool is made of gold. Bring
graze. Their wool is made of gold. Bring
graze. Their wool is made of gold. Bring me a tuft of it, just a handful, but do
me a tuft of it, just a handful, but do
me a tuft of it, just a handful, but do try not to die. She smirked and
try not to die. She smirked and
try not to die. She smirked and vanished, leaving Psyche to face what
vanished, leaving Psyche to face what
vanished, leaving Psyche to face what she knew was more than a simple chore.
she knew was more than a simple chore.
she knew was more than a simple chore. These were no gentle creatures. The
These were no gentle creatures. The
These were no gentle creatures. The golden rams were sacred, their eyes wild
golden rams were sacred, their eyes wild
golden rams were sacred, their eyes wild and their horns sharp as spears. They
and their horns sharp as spears. They
and their horns sharp as spears. They were known to gore anything that entered
were known to gore anything that entered
were known to gore anything that entered their field, tearing intruders apart
their field, tearing intruders apart
their field, tearing intruders apart without warning. They glittered like
without warning. They glittered like
without warning. They glittered like treasure, but guarded it with rage.
treasure, but guarded it with rage.
treasure, but guarded it with rage. Still, Psyche climbed down the hill and
Still, Psyche climbed down the hill and
Still, Psyche climbed down the hill and approached the field.
approached the field.
approached the field. She crouched by the reeds, heart
She crouched by the reeds, heart
She crouched by the reeds, heart pounding, watching the creatures roam.
pounding, watching the creatures roam.
pounding, watching the creatures roam. Their hooves cracked against stones.
Their hooves cracked against stones.
Their hooves cracked against stones. Their growls echoed low and primal.
Their growls echoed low and primal.
Their growls echoed low and primal. There was no way she could survive
There was no way she could survive
There was no way she could survive entering their territory in daylight.
entering their territory in daylight.
entering their territory in daylight. She sank to her knees, tears welling,
She sank to her knees, tears welling,
She sank to her knees, tears welling, fear clawing at her resolve. But once
fear clawing at her resolve. But once
fear clawing at her resolve. But once again, the world watched. A quiet
again, the world watched. A quiet
again, the world watched. A quiet whisper drifted through the tall grass.
whisper drifted through the tall grass.
whisper drifted through the tall grass. A soft voice like reeds swaying in
A soft voice like reeds swaying in
A soft voice like reeds swaying in rhythm. It was a spirit of the river, an
rhythm. It was a spirit of the river, an
rhythm. It was a spirit of the river, an old presence bound to the stream.
old presence bound to the stream.
old presence bound to the stream. Do not enter the field while the sun is
Do not enter the field while the sun is
Do not enter the field while the sun is high, the spirit murmured. The rams rage
high, the spirit murmured. The rams rage
high, the spirit murmured. The rams rage under daylight. But when twilight falls,
under daylight. But when twilight falls,
under daylight. But when twilight falls, they rest in the shade. Wait, and then
they rest in the shade. Wait, and then
they rest in the shade. Wait, and then gather the wool from the thorny branches
gather the wool from the thorny branches
gather the wool from the thorny branches where it has snagged. No beast will miss
where it has snagged. No beast will miss
where it has snagged. No beast will miss it. Hope returned. Psyche waited. Hours
it. Hope returned. Psyche waited. Hours
it. Hope returned. Psyche waited. Hours passed. The golden rams one by one
passed. The golden rams one by one
passed. The golden rams one by one wandered into the trees and settled into
wandered into the trees and settled into
wandered into the trees and settled into slumber. As darkness fell, she crept
slumber. As darkness fell, she crept
slumber. As darkness fell, she crept forward, quiet, careful, and found tufts
forward, quiet, careful, and found tufts
forward, quiet, careful, and found tufts of golden fleece tangled in brambles and
of golden fleece tangled in brambles and
of golden fleece tangled in brambles and bark.
bark.
bark. By moonlight, she gathered the wool and
By moonlight, she gathered the wool and
By moonlight, she gathered the wool and returned to Aphroditi, who narrowed her
returned to Aphroditi, who narrowed her
returned to Aphroditi, who narrowed her eyes at the shimmering handful in
eyes at the shimmering handful in
eyes at the shimmering handful in Psyche's palm.
Psyche's palm.
Psyche's palm. "You live again," the goddess muttered,
"You live again," the goddess muttered,
"You live again," the goddess muttered, curious.
curious.
curious. But Psyche said nothing. No pride, no
But Psyche said nothing. No pride, no
But Psyche said nothing. No pride, no gloating, just silent strength because
gloating, just silent strength because
gloating, just silent strength because love had taught her something even the
love had taught her something even the
love had taught her something even the gods had forgotten.
gods had forgotten.
gods had forgotten. Courage grows quiet, but it endures.
Courage grows quiet, but it endures.
Courage grows quiet, but it endures. And though Aphroditi was not finished
And though Aphroditi was not finished
And though Aphroditi was not finished testing her, Psyche was far from
testing her, Psyche was far from
testing her, Psyche was far from finished fighting. Aphrodite was growing
finished fighting. Aphrodite was growing
finished fighting. Aphrodite was growing frustrated. Psyche had survived tasks
frustrated. Psyche had survived tasks
frustrated. Psyche had survived tasks meant to crush her, using nothing but
meant to crush her, using nothing but
meant to crush her, using nothing but determination and a strange, unshakable
determination and a strange, unshakable
determination and a strange, unshakable luck. The goddess's smile was gone now,
luck. The goddess's smile was gone now,
luck. The goddess's smile was gone now, replaced by cold calculation.
replaced by cold calculation.
replaced by cold calculation. And so, for the third trial, she gave
And so, for the third trial, she gave
And so, for the third trial, she gave Psyche an errand that should have ended
Psyche an errand that should have ended
Psyche an errand that should have ended her story for good. "Fetch me water,"
her story for good. "Fetch me water,"
her story for good. "Fetch me water," she said, not from a well, not from a
she said, not from a well, not from a
she said, not from a well, not from a stream, but from the river sticks
stream, but from the river sticks
stream, but from the river sticks itself.
itself.
itself. psyche pald. The sticks was no ordinary
psyche pald. The sticks was no ordinary
psyche pald. The sticks was no ordinary river. It marked the boundary between
river. It marked the boundary between
river. It marked the boundary between the world of the living and the dead.
the world of the living and the dead.
the world of the living and the dead. Its waters were sacred, cursed, and
Its waters were sacred, cursed, and
Its waters were sacred, cursed, and fatal to touch. Even the gods approached
fatal to touch. Even the gods approached
fatal to touch. Even the gods approached it with fear. Mortals didn't survive its
it with fear. Mortals didn't survive its
it with fear. Mortals didn't survive its banks. They didn't even return.
banks. They didn't even return.
banks. They didn't even return. Still, Psyche nodded. Her journey led
Still, Psyche nodded. Her journey led
Still, Psyche nodded. Her journey led her to the edge of a cliff so steep it
her to the edge of a cliff so steep it
her to the edge of a cliff so steep it seemed carved by the hands of titans.
seemed carved by the hands of titans.
seemed carved by the hands of titans. Far below the river sticks churned like
Far below the river sticks churned like
Far below the river sticks churned like black glass, and from it rose vaporous
black glass, and from it rose vaporous
black glass, and from it rose vaporous curses and the cries of lost souls.
curses and the cries of lost souls.
curses and the cries of lost souls. Its current didn't flow. It coiled like
Its current didn't flow. It coiled like
Its current didn't flow. It coiled like a living serpent. Worse still, guarding
a living serpent. Worse still, guarding
a living serpent. Worse still, guarding the river were monstrous winged beings,
the river were monstrous winged beings,
the river were monstrous winged beings, centuries of the underworld. They
centuries of the underworld. They
centuries of the underworld. They swooped and screamed at anything that
swooped and screamed at anything that
swooped and screamed at anything that moved, claws sharp enough to tear bone
moved, claws sharp enough to tear bone
moved, claws sharp enough to tear bone from flesh. There was no way down, no
from flesh. There was no way down, no
from flesh. There was no way down, no path forward, no hope. She collapsed
path forward, no hope. She collapsed
path forward, no hope. She collapsed beneath a rock ledge, clutching the
beneath a rock ledge, clutching the
beneath a rock ledge, clutching the crystal vial Aphroditi had mockingly
crystal vial Aphroditi had mockingly
crystal vial Aphroditi had mockingly handed her. "Just a sip," the goddess
handed her. "Just a sip," the goddess
handed her. "Just a sip," the goddess had said. "Enough to show you tried."
had said. "Enough to show you tried."
had said. "Enough to show you tried." But then a shimmer. A high-pitched hum
But then a shimmer. A high-pitched hum
But then a shimmer. A high-pitched hum filled the air, and from a crack in the
filled the air, and from a crack in the
filled the air, and from a crack in the stone emerged a tiny creature. An eagle
stone emerged a tiny creature. An eagle
stone emerged a tiny creature. An eagle massive by bird standards, regal and
massive by bird standards, regal and
massive by bird standards, regal and goldeneyed,
goldeneyed,
goldeneyed, sent by Zeus himself, the eagle of
sent by Zeus himself, the eagle of
sent by Zeus himself, the eagle of thunder and kings.
thunder and kings.
thunder and kings. Without a word, it took the vial from
Without a word, it took the vial from
Without a word, it took the vial from Psyche's hand, spread its wings, and
Psyche's hand, spread its wings, and
Psyche's hand, spread its wings, and soared down the deadly cliff. The
soared down the deadly cliff. The
soared down the deadly cliff. The centuries shrieked, but dared not
centuries shrieked, but dared not
centuries shrieked, but dared not attack, for even death respected Zeus's
attack, for even death respected Zeus's
attack, for even death respected Zeus's command. Within moments, the eagle
command. Within moments, the eagle
command. Within moments, the eagle returned, placing the sealed vial filled
returned, placing the sealed vial filled
returned, placing the sealed vial filled with Stixs's shimmering cursed waters
with Stixs's shimmering cursed waters
with Stixs's shimmering cursed waters into Psyche's trembling hands. She
into Psyche's trembling hands. She
into Psyche's trembling hands. She didn't ask why Zeus helped her. Perhaps
didn't ask why Zeus helped her. Perhaps
didn't ask why Zeus helped her. Perhaps Aos had once helped him. Perhaps even
Aos had once helped him. Perhaps even
Aos had once helped him. Perhaps even gods respected Love's endurance.
gods respected Love's endurance.
gods respected Love's endurance. When Psyche returned to Aphroditi, the
When Psyche returned to Aphroditi, the
When Psyche returned to Aphroditi, the goddess accepted the vial with stony
goddess accepted the vial with stony
goddess accepted the vial with stony silence. Psyche had passed again, but
silence. Psyche had passed again, but
silence. Psyche had passed again, but the final trial would take her where
the final trial would take her where
the final trial would take her where even gods fear to go. And not all love
even gods fear to go. And not all love
even gods fear to go. And not all love stories survive a journey into the
stories survive a journey into the
stories survive a journey into the underworld. Aphrodites voice was colder
underworld. Aphrodites voice was colder
underworld. Aphrodites voice was colder than the sticks itself.
than the sticks itself.
than the sticks itself. For your final task, she said, you will
For your final task, she said, you will
For your final task, she said, you will journey to the realm of Hades. There you
journey to the realm of Hades. There you
journey to the realm of Hades. There you will beg Queen Pesphanany for a box of
will beg Queen Pesphanany for a box of
will beg Queen Pesphanany for a box of her beauty. A gift, you see, for me. I'm
her beauty. A gift, you see, for me. I'm
her beauty. A gift, you see, for me. I'm feeling quite worn lately. Your
feeling quite worn lately. Your
feeling quite worn lately. Your existence exhausts me. It was a death
existence exhausts me. It was a death
existence exhausts me. It was a death sentence. Even the boldest mortals
sentence. Even the boldest mortals
sentence. Even the boldest mortals avoided the underworld. The living did
avoided the underworld. The living did
avoided the underworld. The living did not enter Hades realm and return, but
not enter Hades realm and return, but
not enter Hades realm and return, but Psyche no longer hesitated. If the path
Psyche no longer hesitated. If the path
Psyche no longer hesitated. If the path to OS lay through darkness, then
to OS lay through darkness, then
to OS lay through darkness, then darkness would not stop her.
darkness would not stop her.
darkness would not stop her. Guided by whispers from sympathetic
Guided by whispers from sympathetic
Guided by whispers from sympathetic voices, some say demeter, others say
voices, some say demeter, others say
voices, some say demeter, others say invisible demons of kindness, she found
invisible demons of kindness, she found
invisible demons of kindness, she found a hidden entrance, a cave that pierced
a hidden entrance, a cave that pierced
a hidden entrance, a cave that pierced the world's surface like a forgotten
the world's surface like a forgotten
the world's surface like a forgotten scar.
scar.
scar. She brought with her two coins for Karen
She brought with her two coins for Karen
She brought with her two coins for Karen the fairyman, and barley cakes for
the fairyman, and barley cakes for
the fairyman, and barley cakes for Cberus, the three-headed hound. Every
Cberus, the three-headed hound. Every
Cberus, the three-headed hound. Every step deeper drained the warmth from her
step deeper drained the warmth from her
step deeper drained the warmth from her bones. The air was thick, not with
bones. The air was thick, not with
bones. The air was thick, not with smoke, but silence.
smoke, but silence.
smoke, but silence. The souls she passed drifted like
The souls she passed drifted like
The souls she passed drifted like memories, thin, hollow, and unreachable.
memories, thin, hollow, and unreachable.
memories, thin, hollow, and unreachable. At the river Aaron, Karen accepted her
At the river Aaron, Karen accepted her
At the river Aaron, Karen accepted her payment and rode her through still
payment and rode her through still
payment and rode her through still waters stained with forgotten grief.
waters stained with forgotten grief.
waters stained with forgotten grief. When Cerberus appeared, snarling at the
When Cerberus appeared, snarling at the
When Cerberus appeared, snarling at the threshold of Pesphanie's palace, she fed
threshold of Pesphanie's palace, she fed
threshold of Pesphanie's palace, she fed him the cakes. He quieted, licking his
him the cakes. He quieted, licking his
him the cakes. He quieted, licking his bloodstained jaws.
bloodstained jaws.
bloodstained jaws. Inside, Pesphanie sat serene on her
Inside, Pesphanie sat serene on her
Inside, Pesphanie sat serene on her obsidian throne, eyes like polished
obsidian throne, eyes like polished
obsidian throne, eyes like polished garnets.
garnets.
garnets. "You come for beauty," the queen said,
"You come for beauty," the queen said,
"You come for beauty," the queen said, not unkindly. "But at what cost?" "I do
not unkindly. "But at what cost?" "I do
not unkindly. "But at what cost?" "I do not want it for myself," Psyche replied.
not want it for myself," Psyche replied.
not want it for myself," Psyche replied. "I must deliver it to Aphrodite."
"I must deliver it to Aphrodite."
"I must deliver it to Aphrodite." Pesphanie nodded. "Perhaps she too
Pesphanie nodded. "Perhaps she too
Pesphanie nodded. "Perhaps she too understood the madness of love." She
understood the madness of love." She
understood the madness of love." She handed Psyche a small sealed box, plain,
handed Psyche a small sealed box, plain,
handed Psyche a small sealed box, plain, unmarked, and yet unbearably heavy. "Do
unmarked, and yet unbearably heavy. "Do
unmarked, and yet unbearably heavy. "Do not open it," the queen warned. "It is
not open it," the queen warned. "It is
not open it," the queen warned. "It is not meant for your eyes." Psyche thanked
not meant for your eyes." Psyche thanked
not meant for your eyes." Psyche thanked her and turned to leave. The journey
her and turned to leave. The journey
her and turned to leave. The journey back was quiet, but heavier now with
back was quiet, but heavier now with
back was quiet, but heavier now with temptation. The box pulsed in her hands.
temptation. The box pulsed in her hands.
temptation. The box pulsed in her hands. "Surely just a peak couldn't hurt." She
"Surely just a peak couldn't hurt." She
"Surely just a peak couldn't hurt." She told herself no, over and over. But
told herself no, over and over. But
told herself no, over and over. But doubt, like before, crept in. What if
doubt, like before, crept in. What if
doubt, like before, crept in. What if this beauty made her worthy of OS again?
this beauty made her worthy of OS again?
this beauty made her worthy of OS again? What if this was the final key? The
What if this was the final key? The
What if this was the final key? The surface was near. Her heart raced, her
surface was near. Her heart raced, her
surface was near. Her heart raced, her fingers twitched, and as light returned
fingers twitched, and as light returned
fingers twitched, and as light returned to her face for the first time in days,
to her face for the first time in days,
to her face for the first time in days, she opened the box, and darkness
she opened the box, and darkness
she opened the box, and darkness consumed her. The moment Psyche opened
consumed her. The moment Psyche opened
consumed her. The moment Psyche opened the box, expecting light and beauty, a
the box, expecting light and beauty, a
the box, expecting light and beauty, a cold mist spilled from it like a breath
cold mist spilled from it like a breath
cold mist spilled from it like a breath from the grave. It wasn't beauty. It
from the grave. It wasn't beauty. It
from the grave. It wasn't beauty. It wasn't divine radiance. It was sleep.
wasn't divine radiance. It was sleep.
wasn't divine radiance. It was sleep. Not ordinary sleep, but the deathless
Not ordinary sleep, but the deathless
Not ordinary sleep, but the deathless slumber of the underworld crafted by
slumber of the underworld crafted by
slumber of the underworld crafted by Pesphanany to preserve her power, not to
Pesphanany to preserve her power, not to
Pesphanany to preserve her power, not to beautify Aphrodite.
beautify Aphrodite.
beautify Aphrodite. Psyche didn't scream. She didn't
Psyche didn't scream. She didn't
Psyche didn't scream. She didn't collapse. She simply dropped. Her body
collapse. She simply dropped. Her body
collapse. She simply dropped. Her body fell softly onto the grass at the edge
fell softly onto the grass at the edge
fell softly onto the grass at the edge of the mortal world. The sealed box
of the mortal world. The sealed box
of the mortal world. The sealed box beside her, her limbs frozen, her breath
beside her, her limbs frozen, her breath
beside her, her limbs frozen, her breath silenced. She wasn't dead, but neither
silenced. She wasn't dead, but neither
silenced. She wasn't dead, but neither was she alive.
was she alive.
was she alive. Caught in an eternal pause, her heart
Caught in an eternal pause, her heart
Caught in an eternal pause, her heart stilled by her own curiosity.
stilled by her own curiosity.
stilled by her own curiosity. And that might have been the end of
And that might have been the end of
And that might have been the end of psyche. But love has a way of surviving
psyche. But love has a way of surviving
psyche. But love has a way of surviving even death. Far away in Olympus, OS had
even death. Far away in Olympus, OS had
even death. Far away in Olympus, OS had not forgotten her. His wounds had
not forgotten her. His wounds had
not forgotten her. His wounds had healed, but his heart had not. He had
healed, but his heart had not. He had
healed, but his heart had not. He had kept away at his mother's command,
kept away at his mother's command,
kept away at his mother's command, tormented by visions of psyche toiling
tormented by visions of psyche toiling
tormented by visions of psyche toiling through impossible trials. And when he
through impossible trials. And when he
through impossible trials. And when he heard she had entered the underworld, he
heard she had entered the underworld, he
heard she had entered the underworld, he knew she had done it for him. Defying
knew she had done it for him. Defying
knew she had done it for him. Defying Aphroditi, braving death, all for love.
Aphroditi, braving death, all for love.
Aphroditi, braving death, all for love. That was no mortal girl. That was a
That was no mortal girl. That was a
That was no mortal girl. That was a queen.
queen.
queen. Os defied his mother, bursting from
Os defied his mother, bursting from
Os defied his mother, bursting from Olympus in a blaze of wings and gold. He
Olympus in a blaze of wings and gold. He
Olympus in a blaze of wings and gold. He raced through the skies, the clouds
raced through the skies, the clouds
raced through the skies, the clouds splitting at his heels, until he found
splitting at his heels, until he found
splitting at his heels, until he found her, motionless, silent, lying like a
her, motionless, silent, lying like a
her, motionless, silent, lying like a marble statue kissed by the dusk. He
marble statue kissed by the dusk. He
marble statue kissed by the dusk. He fell to his knees beside her, and he
fell to his knees beside her, and he
fell to his knees beside her, and he wept, not tears of sorrow, but of rage,
wept, not tears of sorrow, but of rage,
wept, not tears of sorrow, but of rage, of regret, of love too big for words. He
of regret, of love too big for words. He
of regret, of love too big for words. He lifted the box gently and sealed it
lifted the box gently and sealed it
lifted the box gently and sealed it shut. Then, without hesitation, he
shut. Then, without hesitation, he
shut. Then, without hesitation, he leaned down and kissed her lips. Not a
leaned down and kissed her lips. Not a
leaned down and kissed her lips. Not a magical kiss, not a spell, just a kiss,
magical kiss, not a spell, just a kiss,
magical kiss, not a spell, just a kiss, a promise, a memory, a plea, and her
a promise, a memory, a plea, and her
a promise, a memory, a plea, and her eyes fluttered open. Psyche gasped, the
eyes fluttered open. Psyche gasped, the
eyes fluttered open. Psyche gasped, the sleep lifting like fog, her hands
sleep lifting like fog, her hands
sleep lifting like fog, her hands reached for him before she could even
reached for him before she could even
reached for him before she could even speak. Aeros, she breathed. You came
speak. Aeros, she breathed. You came
speak. Aeros, she breathed. You came back, he whispered. I never stopped
back, he whispered. I never stopped
back, he whispered. I never stopped loving you. He held her tighter than
loving you. He held her tighter than
loving you. He held her tighter than ever before. And in that moment, all the
ever before. And in that moment, all the
ever before. And in that moment, all the gods who had watched, some amused, some
gods who had watched, some amused, some
gods who had watched, some amused, some angered, finally understood. Even the
angered, finally understood. Even the
angered, finally understood. Even the god of love, had met his match.
god of love, had met his match.
god of love, had met his match. Their reunion shook Olympus.
Their reunion shook Olympus.
Their reunion shook Olympus. OS, the god of love, had defied his
OS, the god of love, had defied his
OS, the god of love, had defied his mother. Psyche, a mortal, had defied
mother. Psyche, a mortal, had defied
mother. Psyche, a mortal, had defied death. And together, they had crossed
death. And together, they had crossed
death. And together, they had crossed the boundaries between divine and human,
the boundaries between divine and human,
the boundaries between divine and human, between duty and desire. Such love was
between duty and desire. Such love was
between duty and desire. Such love was dangerous. Aphrodite was livid. She
dangerous. Aphrodite was livid. She
dangerous. Aphrodite was livid. She stormed into the court of the gods,
stormed into the court of the gods,
stormed into the court of the gods, demanding punishment.
demanding punishment.
demanding punishment. This mortal, she cried, has mocked the
This mortal, she cried, has mocked the
This mortal, she cried, has mocked the gods, meddled with sacred laws, and
gods, meddled with sacred laws, and
gods, meddled with sacred laws, and corrupted my son. She must be erased.
corrupted my son. She must be erased.
corrupted my son. She must be erased. But the gods were no longer so certain.
But the gods were no longer so certain.
But the gods were no longer so certain. They had seen Psyche's trials, witnessed
They had seen Psyche's trials, witnessed
They had seen Psyche's trials, witnessed her suffer, persevere, and rise again.
her suffer, persevere, and rise again.
her suffer, persevere, and rise again. Her love had survived what no mortal
Her love had survived what no mortal
Her love had survived what no mortal love ever had. Still, the matter had to
love ever had. Still, the matter had to
love ever had. Still, the matter had to be decided. And so they turned to Zeus.
be decided. And so they turned to Zeus.
be decided. And so they turned to Zeus. The king of the gods sat silent on his
The king of the gods sat silent on his
The king of the gods sat silent on his throne, lightning in one hand, fate in
throne, lightning in one hand, fate in
throne, lightning in one hand, fate in the other. He had watched all of it,
the other. He had watched all of it,
the other. He had watched all of it, from psyches fall to her rise, from her
from psyches fall to her rise, from her
from psyches fall to her rise, from her doubt to her devotion.
doubt to her devotion.
doubt to her devotion. At last, he spoke. There is power, Zeus
At last, he spoke. There is power, Zeus
At last, he spoke. There is power, Zeus said, in a love that endures.
said, in a love that endures.
said, in a love that endures. Aphrodite opened her mouth to protest,
Aphrodite opened her mouth to protest,
Aphrodite opened her mouth to protest, but he raised a hand. You have tested
but he raised a hand. You have tested
but he raised a hand. You have tested her. She has passed more than any mortal
her. She has passed more than any mortal
her. She has passed more than any mortal I have ever seen. She is not unworthy of
I have ever seen. She is not unworthy of
I have ever seen. She is not unworthy of Olympus. She is proof that even mortals
Olympus. She is proof that even mortals
Olympus. She is proof that even mortals can love like gods. Then he turned to OS
can love like gods. Then he turned to OS
can love like gods. Then he turned to OS and Psyche. You want to be together
and Psyche. You want to be together
and Psyche. You want to be together truly forever? They both nodded. Then so
truly forever? They both nodded. Then so
truly forever? They both nodded. Then so be it. With a flick of his hand, Zeus
be it. With a flick of his hand, Zeus
be it. With a flick of his hand, Zeus summoned a goblet filled with ambrosia,
summoned a goblet filled with ambrosia,
summoned a goblet filled with ambrosia, the drink of the gods. He offered it to
the drink of the gods. He offered it to
the drink of the gods. He offered it to Psyche. Drink and you will no longer be
Psyche. Drink and you will no longer be
Psyche. Drink and you will no longer be mortal. Your heart will beat with
mortal. Your heart will beat with
mortal. Your heart will beat with eternity. Your soul will live among us.
eternity. Your soul will live among us.
eternity. Your soul will live among us. But your trials will not be erased. You
But your trials will not be erased. You
But your trials will not be erased. You will carry them as we all carry the
will carry them as we all carry the
will carry them as we all carry the stories that shape us. Psyche took the
stories that shape us. Psyche took the
stories that shape us. Psyche took the goblet. Her hands didn't tremble. She
goblet. Her hands didn't tremble. She
goblet. Her hands didn't tremble. She drank. Warmth spread through her, not
drank. Warmth spread through her, not
drank. Warmth spread through her, not burning, but blooming. Her senses
burning, but blooming. Her senses
burning, but blooming. Her senses expanded. Her heartbeat slowed, then
expanded. Her heartbeat slowed, then
expanded. Her heartbeat slowed, then deepened like a bell tolling across
deepened like a bell tolling across
deepened like a bell tolling across centuries. And just like that, she was
centuries. And just like that, she was
centuries. And just like that, she was divine. No longer mortal, no longer
divine. No longer mortal, no longer
divine. No longer mortal, no longer less.
less.
less. OS took her hand, and in front of all
OS took her hand, and in front of all
OS took her hand, and in front of all Olympus, they were declared husband and
Olympus, they were declared husband and
Olympus, they were declared husband and wife. Love, for once, had not ended in
wife. Love, for once, had not ended in
wife. Love, for once, had not ended in tragedy. It had been crowned.
tragedy. It had been crowned.
tragedy. It had been crowned. The moment Psyche drank the ambrosia,
The moment Psyche drank the ambrosia,
The moment Psyche drank the ambrosia, the transformation was complete. Not
the transformation was complete. Not
the transformation was complete. Not just in body, but in spirit. Her skin
just in body, but in spirit. Her skin
just in body, but in spirit. Her skin shimmerred with divine radiance. Her
shimmerred with divine radiance. Her
shimmerred with divine radiance. Her eyes now holding galaxies rather than
eyes now holding galaxies rather than
eyes now holding galaxies rather than tears.
tears.
tears. The gods who once scoffed at her mortal
The gods who once scoffed at her mortal
The gods who once scoffed at her mortal blood, now watched in awe.
blood, now watched in awe.
blood, now watched in awe. For the first time in Olympus's long
For the first time in Olympus's long
For the first time in Olympus's long memory, a mortal had earned her place
memory, a mortal had earned her place
memory, a mortal had earned her place among them, not by bloodline, but by
among them, not by bloodline, but by
among them, not by bloodline, but by devotion.
devotion.
devotion. She was no longer Psyche the Girl or
She was no longer Psyche the Girl or
She was no longer Psyche the Girl or Psyche the Beautiful. She was now Psyche
Psyche the Beautiful. She was now Psyche
Psyche the Beautiful. She was now Psyche the Immortal, a goddess in her own
the Immortal, a goddess in her own
the Immortal, a goddess in her own right. Even Aphrodite, who had once
right. Even Aphrodite, who had once
right. Even Aphrodite, who had once cursed her, could no longer deny what
cursed her, could no longer deny what
cursed her, could no longer deny what stood before her. A woman who had faced
stood before her. A woman who had faced
stood before her. A woman who had faced death, temptation, betrayal, and
death, temptation, betrayal, and
death, temptation, betrayal, and isolation, and still chosen love over
isolation, and still chosen love over
isolation, and still chosen love over pride. Still, the goddess of love wasn't
pride. Still, the goddess of love wasn't
pride. Still, the goddess of love wasn't quick to forgive. But Aeros, ever his
quick to forgive. But Aeros, ever his
quick to forgive. But Aeros, ever his mother's son and yet fiercely Psyche's
mother's son and yet fiercely Psyche's
mother's son and yet fiercely Psyche's husband, stepped forward.
husband, stepped forward.
husband, stepped forward. "She is no rival to your beauty,
"She is no rival to your beauty,
"She is no rival to your beauty, mother," he said gently. "She is
mother," he said gently. "She is
mother," he said gently. "She is something else entirely, the soul that
something else entirely, the soul that
something else entirely, the soul that understands love. And in that moment,
understands love. And in that moment,
understands love. And in that moment, the tension melted. Not completely, but
the tension melted. Not completely, but
the tension melted. Not completely, but enough." Aphrodites silence was her
enough." Aphrodites silence was her
enough." Aphrodites silence was her surrender. Zeus proclaimed her goddess
surrender. Zeus proclaimed her goddess
surrender. Zeus proclaimed her goddess of the soul. Psyche, whose very name in
of the soul. Psyche, whose very name in
of the soul. Psyche, whose very name in Greek meant both soul and breath of
Greek meant both soul and breath of
Greek meant both soul and breath of life. Her trials had shaped her not into
life. Her trials had shaped her not into
life. Her trials had shaped her not into a statue of perfection, but into the
a statue of perfection, but into the
a statue of perfection, but into the embodiment of what love endures.
embodiment of what love endures.
embodiment of what love endures. A great feast was held on Olympus.
A great feast was held on Olympus.
A great feast was held on Olympus. Nectar flowed like rivers. Stars danced
Nectar flowed like rivers. Stars danced
Nectar flowed like rivers. Stars danced in celebration, and even the fates
in celebration, and even the fates
in celebration, and even the fates smiled at the story they had once woven
smiled at the story they had once woven
smiled at the story they had once woven in whispers. Psyche stood by OS, no
in whispers. Psyche stood by OS, no
in whispers. Psyche stood by OS, no longer uncertain or afraid. She was
longer uncertain or afraid. She was
longer uncertain or afraid. She was equal. She was divine.
equal. She was divine.
equal. She was divine. Together they watched the skies above
Together they watched the skies above
Together they watched the skies above and the mortal world below. Guardians of
and the mortal world below. Guardians of
and the mortal world below. Guardians of love and the soul's journey. And from
love and the soul's journey. And from
love and the soul's journey. And from their union, a daughter was born.
their union, a daughter was born.
their union, a daughter was born. Hidone, goddess of pleasure and delight,
Hidone, goddess of pleasure and delight,
Hidone, goddess of pleasure and delight, symbol of joy, born from the union of
symbol of joy, born from the union of
symbol of joy, born from the union of love and soul.
love and soul.
love and soul. Where once psyche had walked among
Where once psyche had walked among
Where once psyche had walked among thorns and shadows, she now danced in
thorns and shadows, she now danced in
thorns and shadows, she now danced in eternal light. Not because she was
eternal light. Not because she was
eternal light. Not because she was perfect, but because she had loved,
perfect, but because she had loved,
perfect, but because she had loved, fallen, suffered, and risen again. She
fallen, suffered, and risen again. She
fallen, suffered, and risen again. She was proof that even mortals, even the
was proof that even mortals, even the
was proof that even mortals, even the brokenhearted, could reach the heavens,
brokenhearted, could reach the heavens,
brokenhearted, could reach the heavens, one trial at a time. And so, the tale of
one trial at a time. And so, the tale of
one trial at a time. And so, the tale of OS and Psyche, did not end in tragedy,
OS and Psyche, did not end in tragedy,
OS and Psyche, did not end in tragedy, as so many mortal loves do, but in
as so many mortal loves do, but in
as so many mortal loves do, but in transformation, not into myth, but into
transformation, not into myth, but into
transformation, not into myth, but into something far greater. A truth whispered
something far greater. A truth whispered
something far greater. A truth whispered across centuries from temples to
across centuries from temples to
across centuries from temples to bedrooms, from storytellers to dreamers.
bedrooms, from storytellers to dreamers.
bedrooms, from storytellers to dreamers. Love, real love, is not easy. It is
Love, real love, is not easy. It is
Love, real love, is not easy. It is tested. It is doubted. It is wounded.
tested. It is doubted. It is wounded.
tested. It is doubted. It is wounded. But when it endures, it becomes eternal.
But when it endures, it becomes eternal.
But when it endures, it becomes eternal. Psyche's journey had begun with beauty,
Psyche's journey had begun with beauty,
Psyche's journey had begun with beauty, a curse she never asked for. She had
a curse she never asked for. She had
a curse she never asked for. She had been woripped by strangers, envied by
been woripped by strangers, envied by
been woripped by strangers, envied by sisters, manipulated by gods. She had
sisters, manipulated by gods. She had
sisters, manipulated by gods. She had been punished for being loved, then
been punished for being loved, then
been punished for being loved, then punished again for loving back. And yet
punished again for loving back. And yet
punished again for loving back. And yet she never stopped trying. Even when her
she never stopped trying. Even when her
she never stopped trying. Even when her heart broke, even when her faith
heart broke, even when her faith
heart broke, even when her faith cracked, she kept walking. And Aeros,
cracked, she kept walking. And Aeros,
cracked, she kept walking. And Aeros, the god of love, he learned too. That
the god of love, he learned too. That
the god of love, he learned too. That love is not a weapon, not a game, not a
love is not a weapon, not a game, not a
love is not a weapon, not a game, not a secret in the shadows. It is light, yes,
secret in the shadows. It is light, yes,
secret in the shadows. It is light, yes, but only if it is faced. Together they
but only if it is faced. Together they
but only if it is faced. Together they taught even Olympus a lesson it had long
taught even Olympus a lesson it had long
taught even Olympus a lesson it had long forgotten. Love does not belong solely
forgotten. Love does not belong solely
forgotten. Love does not belong solely to the gods. It belongs to anyone
to the gods. It belongs to anyone
to the gods. It belongs to anyone willing to fight for it. In temples
willing to fight for it. In temples
willing to fight for it. In temples across Greece, lovers would offer
across Greece, lovers would offer
across Greece, lovers would offer prayers not just to Aphroditi but to
prayers not just to Aphroditi but to
prayers not just to Aphroditi but to psyche. They would whisper her name
psyche. They would whisper her name
psyche. They would whisper her name before marriages, births, and even
before marriages, births, and even
before marriages, births, and even funerals. Because she wasn't just a
funerals. Because she wasn't just a
funerals. Because she wasn't just a goddess, she was a reminder that the
goddess, she was a reminder that the
goddess, she was a reminder that the soul can survive despair.
soul can survive despair.
soul can survive despair. That love when it falls can rise again.
That love when it falls can rise again.
That love when it falls can rise again. And that no matter how deep the
And that no matter how deep the
And that no matter how deep the underworld, no matter how sharp the
underworld, no matter how sharp the
underworld, no matter how sharp the trial, the heart knows the way back.
trial, the heart knows the way back.
trial, the heart knows the way back. Today, long after temples have crumbled
Today, long after temples have crumbled
Today, long after temples have crumbled and empires have fallen, the story still
and empires have fallen, the story still
and empires have fallen, the story still lives. In the word psyche, meaning soul.
lives. In the word psyche, meaning soul.
lives. In the word psyche, meaning soul. In the word psychology, the study of
In the word psychology, the study of
In the word psychology, the study of that soul. And in every tale where love
that soul. And in every tale where love
that soul. And in every tale where love is tested and triumphs,
is tested and triumphs,
is tested and triumphs, os and psyche live on, not as marble
os and psyche live on, not as marble
os and psyche live on, not as marble statues, but as echoes within all of us.
statues, but as echoes within all of us.
statues, but as echoes within all of us. Every time we choose trust over fear,
Every time we choose trust over fear,
Every time we choose trust over fear, forgiveness over pride, and love over
forgiveness over pride, and love over
forgiveness over pride, and love over silence, we walk their path. And
silence, we walk their path. And
silence, we walk their path. And perhaps, like them, we become a little
perhaps, like them, we become a little
perhaps, like them, we become a little more divine.
Long before she was feared, before
Long before she was feared, before statues froze midscream and serpents
statues froze midscream and serpents
statues froze midscream and serpents whispered across marble floors, Medusa
whispered across marble floors, Medusa
whispered across marble floors, Medusa was a mortal girl, beautiful beyond
was a mortal girl, beautiful beyond
was a mortal girl, beautiful beyond compare. Her beauty was not loud or
compare. Her beauty was not loud or
compare. Her beauty was not loud or proud. It simply existed, uninvited,
proud. It simply existed, uninvited,
proud. It simply existed, uninvited, like sunlight slipping through stone.
like sunlight slipping through stone.
like sunlight slipping through stone. Her hair shimmerred like strands of
Her hair shimmerred like strands of
Her hair shimmerred like strands of midnight silk. Her eyes held the calm of
midnight silk. Her eyes held the calm of
midnight silk. Her eyes held the calm of oceans before storms, and her presence,
oceans before storms, and her presence,
oceans before storms, and her presence, though quiet, unsettled kings and gods
though quiet, unsettled kings and gods
though quiet, unsettled kings and gods alike.
alike.
alike. She was born into a family of monsters,
She was born into a family of monsters,
She was born into a family of monsters, in a time where monsters were worshiped
in a time where monsters were worshiped
in a time where monsters were worshiped and feared in equal measure. Her
and feared in equal measure. Her
and feared in equal measure. Her sisters, Steno and Uriel, were immortal,
sisters, Steno and Uriel, were immortal,
sisters, Steno and Uriel, were immortal, fierce, and monstrous by design. But
fierce, and monstrous by design. But
fierce, and monstrous by design. But Medusa was different. She alone was
Medusa was different. She alone was
Medusa was different. She alone was mortal. She alone could die. And perhaps
mortal. She alone could die. And perhaps
mortal. She alone could die. And perhaps that made her even more precious. But
that made her even more precious. But
that made her even more precious. But Medusa wanted no throne, no lovers, no
Medusa wanted no throne, no lovers, no
Medusa wanted no throne, no lovers, no crown of divine favor. She chose
crown of divine favor. She chose
crown of divine favor. She chose something rarer, devotion.
something rarer, devotion.
something rarer, devotion. As a young woman, she entered the sacred
As a young woman, she entered the sacred
As a young woman, she entered the sacred service of Athena, the virgin goddess of
service of Athena, the virgin goddess of
service of Athena, the virgin goddess of wisdom, war, and restraint. In the
wisdom, war, and restraint. In the
wisdom, war, and restraint. In the echoing marble temple built high on
echoing marble temple built high on
echoing marble temple built high on cliffs above the sea, Medusa swept the
cliffs above the sea, Medusa swept the
cliffs above the sea, Medusa swept the floors, lit the incense, and whispered
floors, lit the incense, and whispered
floors, lit the incense, and whispered prayers long before dawn. She took the
prayers long before dawn. She took the
prayers long before dawn. She took the vows of chastity, purity, and silence.
vows of chastity, purity, and silence.
vows of chastity, purity, and silence. Not because she was forced to, but
Not because she was forced to, but
Not because she was forced to, but because she believed. She admired
because she believed. She admired
because she believed. She admired Athena, not just as a goddess, but as an
Athena, not just as a goddess, but as an
Athena, not just as a goddess, but as an ideal, strong, untouchable, above the
ideal, strong, untouchable, above the
ideal, strong, untouchable, above the chaos of mortal hearts. In time, even
chaos of mortal hearts. In time, even
chaos of mortal hearts. In time, even the people began to whisper that Medusa
the people began to whisper that Medusa
the people began to whisper that Medusa was a living statue of Athena herself.
was a living statue of Athena herself.
was a living statue of Athena herself. Worshippers would sneak glances at her
Worshippers would sneak glances at her
Worshippers would sneak glances at her while pretending to pray. Her face
while pretending to pray. Her face
while pretending to pray. Her face became a symbol, her voice rarely heard,
became a symbol, her voice rarely heard,
became a symbol, her voice rarely heard, her life bound in sacred duty. But
her life bound in sacred duty. But
her life bound in sacred duty. But beauty, even in a temple, is not safe.
beauty, even in a temple, is not safe.
beauty, even in a temple, is not safe. Word of Medusa's grace spread beyond the
Word of Medusa's grace spread beyond the
Word of Medusa's grace spread beyond the temple walls, past the cities, through
temple walls, past the cities, through
temple walls, past the cities, through forests, into the realm of gods, and
forests, into the realm of gods, and
forests, into the realm of gods, and with it came danger. For in Olympus,
with it came danger. For in Olympus,
with it came danger. For in Olympus, desire often wore a divine face, and the
desire often wore a divine face, and the
desire often wore a divine face, and the line between admiration and possession
line between admiration and possession
line between admiration and possession was razor thin. One god in particular
was razor thin. One god in particular
was razor thin. One god in particular took notice. Not a god of wisdom, not a
took notice. Not a god of wisdom, not a
took notice. Not a god of wisdom, not a god of restraint, but a god of seas,
god of restraint, but a god of seas,
god of restraint, but a god of seas, storms, and appetites. And while Medusa
storms, and appetites. And while Medusa
storms, and appetites. And while Medusa kept her vows, fate had already begun to
kept her vows, fate had already begun to
kept her vows, fate had already begun to twist. Because in the realm of gods,
twist. Because in the realm of gods,
twist. Because in the realm of gods, even purity can be punished. And soon,
even purity can be punished. And soon,
even purity can be punished. And soon, Medusa's sanctuary would become her
Medusa's sanctuary would become her
Medusa's sanctuary would become her prison. Far beneath the crashing waves
prison. Far beneath the crashing waves
prison. Far beneath the crashing waves and coral palaces of the deep, Poseidon
and coral palaces of the deep, Poseidon
and coral palaces of the deep, Poseidon ruled the seas with pride, fury, and a
ruled the seas with pride, fury, and a
ruled the seas with pride, fury, and a hunger that was never fully satisfied.
hunger that was never fully satisfied.
hunger that was never fully satisfied. He had tamed monsters, birthed storms,
He had tamed monsters, birthed storms,
He had tamed monsters, birthed storms, and claimed goddesses. But his eyes now
and claimed goddesses. But his eyes now
and claimed goddesses. But his eyes now turned to something far less divine. A
turned to something far less divine. A
turned to something far less divine. A mortal Medusa.
mortal Medusa.
mortal Medusa. Her beauty had reached even the ears of
Her beauty had reached even the ears of
Her beauty had reached even the ears of Olympus. But it was her stillness, her
Olympus. But it was her stillness, her
Olympus. But it was her stillness, her discipline, her untouchable grace that
discipline, her untouchable grace that
discipline, her untouchable grace that obsessed him. She belonged to no man, no
obsessed him. She belonged to no man, no
obsessed him. She belonged to no man, no god, no mortal king. She had chosen a
god, no mortal king. She had chosen a
god, no mortal king. She had chosen a life of devotion, one that placed her
life of devotion, one that placed her
life of devotion, one that placed her far from desire. And perhaps that was
far from desire. And perhaps that was
far from desire. And perhaps that was what tempted Poseidon most. The more she
what tempted Poseidon most. The more she
what tempted Poseidon most. The more she prayed, the more he watched. And one
prayed, the more he watched. And one
prayed, the more he watched. And one evening, when the tide was high and the
evening, when the tide was high and the
evening, when the tide was high and the temple was empty, Poseidon rose from the
temple was empty, Poseidon rose from the
temple was empty, Poseidon rose from the sea. He did not knock. Gods rarely ask
sea. He did not knock. Gods rarely ask
sea. He did not knock. Gods rarely ask permission. He entered Athena's sacred
permission. He entered Athena's sacred
permission. He entered Athena's sacred temple as water pulled beneath his feet.
temple as water pulled beneath his feet.
temple as water pulled beneath his feet. A trail of seaater soaking the marble
A trail of seaater soaking the marble
A trail of seaater soaking the marble floor. Medusa, alone and unsuspecting,
floor. Medusa, alone and unsuspecting,
floor. Medusa, alone and unsuspecting, turned only to find the sea god looming
turned only to find the sea god looming
turned only to find the sea god looming in the shadows, his trident left behind,
in the shadows, his trident left behind,
in the shadows, his trident left behind, but his hunger very much present.
but his hunger very much present.
but his hunger very much present. She called out to Athena, but her cries
She called out to Athena, but her cries
She called out to Athena, but her cries echoed unanswered. She ran, but temples
echoed unanswered. She ran, but temples
echoed unanswered. She ran, but temples built for worship were not made for
built for worship were not made for
built for worship were not made for escape. And there, beneath the cold
escape. And there, beneath the cold
escape. And there, beneath the cold stone gaze of Athena's statue, Poseidon
stone gaze of Athena's statue, Poseidon
stone gaze of Athena's statue, Poseidon defiled what was sacred. It was not a
defiled what was sacred. It was not a
defiled what was sacred. It was not a seduction. It was a violation. When it
seduction. It was a violation. When it
seduction. It was a violation. When it was over, Poseidon vanished, leaving
was over, Poseidon vanished, leaving
was over, Poseidon vanished, leaving nothing but salt and silence behind.
nothing but salt and silence behind.
nothing but salt and silence behind. Medusa, broken, curled beneath her
Medusa, broken, curled beneath her
Medusa, broken, curled beneath her goddess's image, waiting for justice,
goddess's image, waiting for justice,
goddess's image, waiting for justice, for comfort, for anything divine. But
for comfort, for anything divine. But
for comfort, for anything divine. But gods are not always just. When Athena
gods are not always just. When Athena
gods are not always just. When Athena returned to her temple and saw the
returned to her temple and saw the
returned to her temple and saw the desecration, her fury was absolute. But
desecration, her fury was absolute. But
desecration, her fury was absolute. But not at Poseidon, at Medusa.
not at Poseidon, at Medusa.
not at Poseidon, at Medusa. Whether out of pride, denial, or divine
Whether out of pride, denial, or divine
Whether out of pride, denial, or divine law, Athena blamed her priestess for
law, Athena blamed her priestess for
law, Athena blamed her priestess for allowing the temple to be defiled,
allowing the temple to be defiled,
allowing the temple to be defiled, whether she saw Medusa as complicit or
whether she saw Medusa as complicit or
whether she saw Medusa as complicit or simply inconvenient didn't matter. The
simply inconvenient didn't matter. The
simply inconvenient didn't matter. The purity of her sanctuary had been broken.
purity of her sanctuary had been broken.
purity of her sanctuary had been broken. And so the goddess of wisdom passed
And so the goddess of wisdom passed
And so the goddess of wisdom passed judgment not on the god who had
judgment not on the god who had
judgment not on the god who had violated, but on the mortal who had been
violated, but on the mortal who had been
violated, but on the mortal who had been violated. Because even in myth, power
violated. Because even in myth, power
violated. Because even in myth, power protects itself. and Medusa, once a
protects itself. and Medusa, once a
protects itself. and Medusa, once a symbol of sacred beauty, would now be
symbol of sacred beauty, would now be
symbol of sacred beauty, would now be transformed into a warning no one could
transformed into a warning no one could
transformed into a warning no one could ignore.
ignore.
ignore. The temple floor was still stained with
The temple floor was still stained with
The temple floor was still stained with seaater when Athena returned. The
seaater when Athena returned. The
seaater when Athena returned. The incense had long burned out. The silence
incense had long burned out. The silence
incense had long burned out. The silence was heavy, and at its center, Medusa
was heavy, and at its center, Medusa
was heavy, and at its center, Medusa knelt in shame, her head bowed beneath
knelt in shame, her head bowed beneath
knelt in shame, her head bowed beneath the unblinking gaze of her goddess. But
the unblinking gaze of her goddess. But
the unblinking gaze of her goddess. But Athena's eyes were not filled with pity.
Athena's eyes were not filled with pity.
Athena's eyes were not filled with pity. They burned with fury. For her temple,
They burned with fury. For her temple,
They burned with fury. For her temple, her sanctuary of reason, discipline, and
her sanctuary of reason, discipline, and
her sanctuary of reason, discipline, and virgin purity had been defiled. And
virgin purity had been defiled. And
virgin purity had been defiled. And though Poseidon had violated sacred
though Poseidon had violated sacred
though Poseidon had violated sacred ground, it was Medusa who bore the
ground, it was Medusa who bore the
ground, it was Medusa who bore the blame. To Athena, there could be no
blame. To Athena, there could be no
blame. To Athena, there could be no forgiveness. Gods never apologized, and
forgiveness. Gods never apologized, and
forgiveness. Gods never apologized, and temples never forgot. The punishment had
temples never forgot. The punishment had
temples never forgot. The punishment had to be symbolic,
to be symbolic,
to be symbolic, eternal. She stepped down from her
eternal. She stepped down from her
eternal. She stepped down from her statue's pedestal and stood over Medusa,
statue's pedestal and stood over Medusa,
statue's pedestal and stood over Medusa, who trembled, confused, awaiting mercy
who trembled, confused, awaiting mercy
who trembled, confused, awaiting mercy from the very goddess she had worshiped
from the very goddess she had worshiped
from the very goddess she had worshiped for years. But mercy was not given.
for years. But mercy was not given.
for years. But mercy was not given. Instead, Athena's voice echoed like
Instead, Athena's voice echoed like
Instead, Athena's voice echoed like thunder between marble walls. "You have
thunder between marble walls. "You have
thunder between marble walls. "You have brought shame into my house. Let the
brought shame into my house. Let the
brought shame into my house. Let the world see what becomes of beauty that
world see what becomes of beauty that
world see what becomes of beauty that invites destruction."
invites destruction."
invites destruction." With a single gesture, she reached down
With a single gesture, she reached down
With a single gesture, she reached down and touched Medusa's forehead.
and touched Medusa's forehead.
and touched Medusa's forehead. The transformation was immediate. Golden
The transformation was immediate. Golden
The transformation was immediate. Golden hair turned to writhing serpents. Their
hair turned to writhing serpents. Their
hair turned to writhing serpents. Their hissing a cruel mimicry of whispered
hissing a cruel mimicry of whispered
hissing a cruel mimicry of whispered prayers. Her skin lost its warmth. Her
prayers. Her skin lost its warmth. Her
prayers. Her skin lost its warmth. Her gaze became a weapon. Her eyes once soft
gaze became a weapon. Her eyes once soft
gaze became a weapon. Her eyes once soft with sorrow now held a terrible power.
with sorrow now held a terrible power.
with sorrow now held a terrible power. Anyone who looked into them would turn
Anyone who looked into them would turn
Anyone who looked into them would turn to stone. Not enemies, not invaders,
to stone. Not enemies, not invaders,
to stone. Not enemies, not invaders, anyone. It was not a punishment of
anyone. It was not a punishment of
anyone. It was not a punishment of protection. It was isolation. A curse
protection. It was isolation. A curse
protection. It was isolation. A curse disguised as defense. Medusa cried out,
disguised as defense. Medusa cried out,
disguised as defense. Medusa cried out, her voice no longer human. Her tears
her voice no longer human. Her tears
her voice no longer human. Her tears once salt water now dried before
once salt water now dried before
once salt water now dried before falling.
falling.
falling. Her breath became still. Her reflection
Her breath became still. Her reflection
Her breath became still. Her reflection shattered mirrors. And worst of all, she
shattered mirrors. And worst of all, she
shattered mirrors. And worst of all, she could no longer look at another soul
could no longer look at another soul
could no longer look at another soul without destroying it. Athena did not
without destroying it. Athena did not
without destroying it. Athena did not weep. She did not turn away. She simply
weep. She did not turn away. She simply
weep. She did not turn away. She simply watched as her priestess, once beautiful
watched as her priestess, once beautiful
watched as her priestess, once beautiful and devout, became something else
and devout, became something else
and devout, became something else entirely,
entirely,
entirely, a monster.
a monster.
a monster. The temple doors closed behind Medusa as
The temple doors closed behind Medusa as
The temple doors closed behind Medusa as she fled into exile, her cries echoing
she fled into exile, her cries echoing
she fled into exile, her cries echoing through the hills. No home, no temple,
through the hills. No home, no temple,
through the hills. No home, no temple, no sisters, no prayers, just stone
no sisters, no prayers, just stone
no sisters, no prayers, just stone trails in her wake. And from the cliffs
trails in her wake. And from the cliffs
trails in her wake. And from the cliffs of Olympus, Athena returned to her
of Olympus, Athena returned to her
of Olympus, Athena returned to her throne unmoved.
throne unmoved.
throne unmoved. For in the eyes of the gods, punishment
For in the eyes of the gods, punishment
For in the eyes of the gods, punishment need not be fair, only lasting, and
need not be fair, only lasting, and
need not be fair, only lasting, and Medusa's face would last longer than
Medusa's face would last longer than
Medusa's face would last longer than memory. Banished from temple and city,
memory. Banished from temple and city,
memory. Banished from temple and city, Medusa wandered into the wilderness,
Medusa wandered into the wilderness,
Medusa wandered into the wilderness, alone, cursed, and feared. Her steps
alone, cursed, and feared. Her steps
alone, cursed, and feared. Her steps carved a trail of stone across the land.
carved a trail of stone across the land.
carved a trail of stone across the land. Each accidental glance at a passing
Each accidental glance at a passing
Each accidental glance at a passing creature turning it to lifeless marble.
creature turning it to lifeless marble.
creature turning it to lifeless marble. Birds mid-flight, deer in the brush,
Birds mid-flight, deer in the brush,
Birds mid-flight, deer in the brush, even insects that dared meet her gaze,
even insects that dared meet her gaze,
even insects that dared meet her gaze, frozen forever in silence, she sought
frozen forever in silence, she sought
frozen forever in silence, she sought refuge where no man would follow, in the
refuge where no man would follow, in the
refuge where no man would follow, in the distant lands beyond rivers and ruin to
distant lands beyond rivers and ruin to
distant lands beyond rivers and ruin to a bleak windswept island at the edge of
a bleak windswept island at the edge of
a bleak windswept island at the edge of the world, a place untouched by gods or
the world, a place untouched by gods or
the world, a place untouched by gods or mortals.
mortals.
mortals. There she built no shelter. What use was
There she built no shelter. What use was
There she built no shelter. What use was a roof when the stars offered no
a roof when the stars offered no
a roof when the stars offered no comfort? What use were walls when her
comfort? What use were walls when her
comfort? What use were walls when her enemies had once been her protectors?
enemies had once been her protectors?
enemies had once been her protectors? The cave she entered was already half
The cave she entered was already half
The cave she entered was already half filled with statues, longforgotten
filled with statues, longforgotten
filled with statues, longforgotten warriors, beasts, or perhaps even fellow
warriors, beasts, or perhaps even fellow
warriors, beasts, or perhaps even fellow wanderers who met her eyes for a moment
wanderers who met her eyes for a moment
wanderers who met her eyes for a moment too long. And so began her second life,
too long. And so began her second life,
too long. And so began her second life, not as a priestess, but as a pariah.
not as a priestess, but as a pariah.
not as a priestess, but as a pariah. Medusa no longer wept. Tears belonged to
Medusa no longer wept. Tears belonged to
Medusa no longer wept. Tears belonged to the girl she once was. The girl who
the girl she once was. The girl who
the girl she once was. The girl who believed in justice, who offered incense
believed in justice, who offered incense
believed in justice, who offered incense to Athena, who thought love could be
to Athena, who thought love could be
to Athena, who thought love could be earned through loyalty.
earned through loyalty.
earned through loyalty. That girl had died on the temple floor.
That girl had died on the temple floor.
That girl had died on the temple floor. In her place stood something else, not a
In her place stood something else, not a
In her place stood something else, not a monster, but a woman shaped by betrayal.
monster, but a woman shaped by betrayal.
monster, but a woman shaped by betrayal. Her serpents whispered to her in dreams,
Her serpents whispered to her in dreams,
Her serpents whispered to her in dreams, not in words, but in instincts, warnings
not in words, but in instincts, warnings
not in words, but in instincts, warnings of intruders, echoes of approaching
of intruders, echoes of approaching
of intruders, echoes of approaching footsteps. Her hair had become her
footsteps. Her hair had become her
footsteps. Her hair had become her guardians. Her eyes, her curse, her
guardians. Her eyes, her curse, her
guardians. Her eyes, her curse, her soul, a flickering memory. She began
soul, a flickering memory. She began
soul, a flickering memory. She began carving the walls of her cave with
carving the walls of her cave with
carving the walls of her cave with images, faces, hands, the temple she
images, faces, hands, the temple she
images, faces, hands, the temple she once served. Even her sisters, her
once served. Even her sisters, her
once served. Even her sisters, her memories were fading, and stone was all
memories were fading, and stone was all
memories were fading, and stone was all she had left. Occasionally, heroes would
she had left. Occasionally, heroes would
she had left. Occasionally, heroes would come, lured by stories of a cursed
come, lured by stories of a cursed
come, lured by stories of a cursed maiden or tempted by the challenge of
maiden or tempted by the challenge of
maiden or tempted by the challenge of slaying a beast. They believed she was
slaying a beast. They believed she was
slaying a beast. They believed she was evil, that by killing her they might
evil, that by killing her they might
evil, that by killing her they might rise in glory. But none of them
rise in glory. But none of them
rise in glory. But none of them returned. They underestimated her. Not
returned. They underestimated her. Not
returned. They underestimated her. Not just her power, but her pain. And yet,
just her power, but her pain. And yet,
just her power, but her pain. And yet, with each death, Medusa felt less like a
with each death, Medusa felt less like a
with each death, Medusa felt less like a victim and more like the very monster
victim and more like the very monster
victim and more like the very monster the world imagined. Her humanity had not
the world imagined. Her humanity had not
the world imagined. Her humanity had not died, but it was fading. And the gods,
died, but it was fading. And the gods,
died, but it was fading. And the gods, they had already looked away. Far from
they had already looked away. Far from
they had already looked away. Far from Medusa's cave, in the bustling
Medusa's cave, in the bustling
Medusa's cave, in the bustling citystates and sacred temples of Greece,
citystates and sacred temples of Greece,
citystates and sacred temples of Greece, her name began to change. No longer
her name began to change. No longer
her name began to change. No longer spoken in mourning, it passed from mouth
spoken in mourning, it passed from mouth
spoken in mourning, it passed from mouth to mouth like a warning, distorted,
to mouth like a warning, distorted,
to mouth like a warning, distorted, retold, and reshaped.
retold, and reshaped.
retold, and reshaped. Medusa, the Gorgon. Medusa, the cursed
Medusa, the Gorgon. Medusa, the cursed
Medusa, the Gorgon. Medusa, the cursed temptress. Medusa, whose gaze turns men
temptress. Medusa, whose gaze turns men
temptress. Medusa, whose gaze turns men to stone. Her past as a devoted
to stone. Her past as a devoted
to stone. Her past as a devoted priestess, a mortal girl who served the
priestess, a mortal girl who served the
priestess, a mortal girl who served the gods, was buried beneath myth. In its
gods, was buried beneath myth. In its
gods, was buried beneath myth. In its place rose a monster's tale, a creature
place rose a monster's tale, a creature
place rose a monster's tale, a creature with serpent hair whose eyes held the
with serpent hair whose eyes held the
with serpent hair whose eyes held the wrath of the underworld. They didn't
wrath of the underworld. They didn't
wrath of the underworld. They didn't tell of Poseidon's violation. They
tell of Poseidon's violation. They
tell of Poseidon's violation. They didn't mention Athena's cruel
didn't mention Athena's cruel
didn't mention Athena's cruel punishment. The gods roles were edited
punishment. The gods roles were edited
punishment. The gods roles were edited out, smoothed over by priests and poets
out, smoothed over by priests and poets
out, smoothed over by priests and poets who preferred their gods spotless and
who preferred their gods spotless and
who preferred their gods spotless and their monsters clearly marked. Children
their monsters clearly marked. Children
their monsters clearly marked. Children were warned to obey their parents or
were warned to obey their parents or
were warned to obey their parents or Medusa would come in the night. Soldiers
Medusa would come in the night. Soldiers
Medusa would come in the night. Soldiers carved her image onto shields, not to
carved her image onto shields, not to
carved her image onto shields, not to honor her, but to mock her. Her face
honor her, but to mock her. Her face
honor her, but to mock her. Her face became a symbol of fear, a cautionary
became a symbol of fear, a cautionary
became a symbol of fear, a cautionary tale, and yet her image spread. Artists
tale, and yet her image spread. Artists
tale, and yet her image spread. Artists painted her on pottery. Her twisted
painted her on pottery. Her twisted
painted her on pottery. Her twisted silhouette danced across mosaics. Her
silhouette danced across mosaics. Her
silhouette danced across mosaics. Her snarling face was carved into temple
snarling face was carved into temple
snarling face was carved into temple walls, not in reverence, but as a weapon
walls, not in reverence, but as a weapon
walls, not in reverence, but as a weapon used by the very gods who had cast her
used by the very gods who had cast her
used by the very gods who had cast her out. Medusa from exile could only feel
out. Medusa from exile could only feel
out. Medusa from exile could only feel the weight of their words. She didn't
the weight of their words. She didn't
the weight of their words. She didn't ask to become legend. She didn't ask to
ask to become legend. She didn't ask to
ask to become legend. She didn't ask to be feared. She had simply survived. And
be feared. She had simply survived. And
be feared. She had simply survived. And survival to those in power is
survival to those in power is
survival to those in power is threatening.
threatening.
threatening. On the mainland, some whispered of her
On the mainland, some whispered of her
On the mainland, some whispered of her as more than a monster.
as more than a monster.
as more than a monster. Old women in mountain villages left
Old women in mountain villages left
Old women in mountain villages left offerings near caves, murmuring that
offerings near caves, murmuring that
offerings near caves, murmuring that Medusa protected women who had been
Medusa protected women who had been
Medusa protected women who had been hurt. They didn't fear her. They pied
hurt. They didn't fear her. They pied
hurt. They didn't fear her. They pied her. They called her guardian of the
her. They called her guardian of the
her. They called her guardian of the wronged. But these voices were soft, and
wronged. But these voices were soft, and
wronged. But these voices were soft, and the roar of hero myths drowned them out.
the roar of hero myths drowned them out.
the roar of hero myths drowned them out. Medusa remained hidden, unaware of how
Medusa remained hidden, unaware of how
Medusa remained hidden, unaware of how deeply her name had split. Monster to
deeply her name had split. Monster to
deeply her name had split. Monster to some, martyr to others. What she did
some, martyr to others. What she did
some, martyr to others. What she did know was this. No matter how far she
know was this. No matter how far she
know was this. No matter how far she hid, they would keep coming. Men with
hid, they would keep coming. Men with
hid, they would keep coming. Men with swords and shining armor. Men who
swords and shining armor. Men who
swords and shining armor. Men who thought killing her meant glory. Men who
thought killing her meant glory. Men who
thought killing her meant glory. Men who had never cared who she was, only what
had never cared who she was, only what
had never cared who she was, only what she had become. And somewhere a new
she had become. And somewhere a new
she had become. And somewhere a new challenger was already being born. A boy
challenger was already being born. A boy
challenger was already being born. A boy who would grow into a man, a hero, and
who would grow into a man, a hero, and
who would grow into a man, a hero, and her final visitor.
her final visitor.
her final visitor. While Medusa lived in exile, her legend
While Medusa lived in exile, her legend
While Medusa lived in exile, her legend spreading like wildfire. A boy named
spreading like wildfire. A boy named
spreading like wildfire. A boy named Perseus was born to a different kind of
Perseus was born to a different kind of
Perseus was born to a different kind of silence, a prison of prophecy.
silence, a prison of prophecy.
silence, a prison of prophecy. His mother, Danier, had been locked away
His mother, Danier, had been locked away
His mother, Danier, had been locked away in a bronze tower by her father, King
in a bronze tower by her father, King
in a bronze tower by her father, King Acryus, desperate to stop a prophecy
Acryus, desperate to stop a prophecy
Acryus, desperate to stop a prophecy that her son would one day cause his
that her son would one day cause his
that her son would one day cause his death.
death.
death. But the gods don't respect mortal locks.
But the gods don't respect mortal locks.
But the gods don't respect mortal locks. Zeus came to Denia, not with love, but
Zeus came to Denia, not with love, but
Zeus came to Denia, not with love, but as golden rain, slipping past walls and
as golden rain, slipping past walls and
as golden rain, slipping past walls and warnings. From that divine encounter,
warnings. From that divine encounter,
warnings. From that divine encounter, Perseus was born. When the king
Perseus was born. When the king
Perseus was born. When the king discovered the child, he dared not kill
discovered the child, he dared not kill
discovered the child, he dared not kill a son of Zeus directly. So he cast
a son of Zeus directly. So he cast
a son of Zeus directly. So he cast mother and infant into the sea, sealed
mother and infant into the sea, sealed
mother and infant into the sea, sealed in a wooden chest, a quiet execution
in a wooden chest, a quiet execution
in a wooden chest, a quiet execution wrapped in cowardice. But the sea, ruled
wrapped in cowardice. But the sea, ruled
wrapped in cowardice. But the sea, ruled by Poseidon, carried them not to death,
by Poseidon, carried them not to death,
by Poseidon, carried them not to death, but to refuge. They washed ashore on the
but to refuge. They washed ashore on the
but to refuge. They washed ashore on the island of Sarapos, where a fisherman
island of Sarapos, where a fisherman
island of Sarapos, where a fisherman took them in. Dier raised Perseus in
took them in. Dier raised Perseus in
took them in. Dier raised Perseus in hiding, teaching him strength, humility,
hiding, teaching him strength, humility,
hiding, teaching him strength, humility, and the silence of survival.
and the silence of survival.
and the silence of survival. She never spoke Zeus's name. She never
She never spoke Zeus's name. She never
She never spoke Zeus's name. She never told her son what kind of god had sired
told her son what kind of god had sired
told her son what kind of god had sired him. Years passed. Perseus grew into a
him. Years passed. Perseus grew into a
him. Years passed. Perseus grew into a sharpeyed young man, clever, strong, but
sharpeyed young man, clever, strong, but
sharpeyed young man, clever, strong, but untested. And then came the king of
untested. And then came the king of
untested. And then came the king of Sarapos, Polyctes.
Sarapos, Polyctes.
Sarapos, Polyctes. He wanted Daier for himself. Perseus
He wanted Daier for himself. Perseus
He wanted Daier for himself. Perseus stood in the way. The king, feigning
stood in the way. The king, feigning
stood in the way. The king, feigning kindness, invited Perseus to a feast.
kindness, invited Perseus to a feast.
kindness, invited Perseus to a feast. Each guest was to bring a gift. Perseus,
Each guest was to bring a gift. Perseus,
Each guest was to bring a gift. Perseus, poor and proud, brought nothing.
poor and proud, brought nothing.
poor and proud, brought nothing. Polyctis sneered. Then bring me the head
Polyctis sneered. Then bring me the head
Polyctis sneered. Then bring me the head of Medusa.
of Medusa.
of Medusa. Laughter followed. It was meant to
Laughter followed. It was meant to
Laughter followed. It was meant to humiliate him.
humiliate him.
humiliate him. But Perseus, stung by pride and unaware
But Perseus, stung by pride and unaware
But Perseus, stung by pride and unaware of the truth behind the name, accepted.
of the truth behind the name, accepted.
of the truth behind the name, accepted. The gods watched with interest. Athena,
The gods watched with interest. Athena,
The gods watched with interest. Athena, perhaps still nursing guilt over what
perhaps still nursing guilt over what
perhaps still nursing guilt over what she'd done to Medusa, saw an
she'd done to Medusa, saw an
she'd done to Medusa, saw an opportunity.
opportunity.
opportunity. She would aid this boy, not for justice,
She would aid this boy, not for justice,
She would aid this boy, not for justice, but for balance. She and Hermes came to
but for balance. She and Hermes came to
but for balance. She and Hermes came to Perseus in dreams, whispering guidance.
Perseus in dreams, whispering guidance.
Perseus in dreams, whispering guidance. They gave him tools, winged sandals to
They gave him tools, winged sandals to
They gave him tools, winged sandals to fly, a polished shield like a mirror, an
fly, a polished shield like a mirror, an
fly, a polished shield like a mirror, an adamantine sword, and the helm of Hades
adamantine sword, and the helm of Hades
adamantine sword, and the helm of Hades to vanish from sight. But no gift came
to vanish from sight. But no gift came
to vanish from sight. But no gift came without purpose. Perseus had been chosen
without purpose. Perseus had been chosen
without purpose. Perseus had been chosen not just to kill a monster, but to
not just to kill a monster, but to
not just to kill a monster, but to complete a myth. One that began not with
complete a myth. One that began not with
complete a myth. One that began not with him, but with a girl alone in a temple,
him, but with a girl alone in a temple,
him, but with a girl alone in a temple, praying to gods who never listened.
praying to gods who never listened.
praying to gods who never listened. Perseus set off with divine tools at his
Perseus set off with divine tools at his
Perseus set off with divine tools at his side and the weight of a king's
side and the weight of a king's
side and the weight of a king's challenge on his shoulders. But finding
challenge on his shoulders. But finding
challenge on his shoulders. But finding Medusa was not as simple as crossing
Medusa was not as simple as crossing
Medusa was not as simple as crossing land or sea. Her location had been
land or sea. Her location had been
land or sea. Her location had been buried by time, hidden even from the
buried by time, hidden even from the
buried by time, hidden even from the gods who had cursed her. To find her,
gods who had cursed her. To find her,
gods who had cursed her. To find her, Perseus needed answers that no mortal
Perseus needed answers that no mortal
Perseus needed answers that no mortal could give. He sought out the Gray.
could give. He sought out the Gray.
could give. He sought out the Gray. Three ancient sisters who shared a
Three ancient sisters who shared a
Three ancient sisters who shared a single eye and a single tooth between
single eye and a single tooth between
single eye and a single tooth between them. They were older than gods, draped
them. They were older than gods, draped
them. They were older than gods, draped in shadow and spite, living in the void
in shadow and spite, living in the void
in shadow and spite, living in the void between light and nightmare. They knew
between light and nightmare. They knew
between light and nightmare. They knew where Medusa slept, for they were her
where Medusa slept, for they were her
where Medusa slept, for they were her kin.
kin.
kin. Perseus didn't beg. He didn't plead. He
Perseus didn't beg. He didn't plead. He
Perseus didn't beg. He didn't plead. He waited until one of the sisters passed
waited until one of the sisters passed
waited until one of the sisters passed the eye to another and snatched it from
the eye to another and snatched it from
the eye to another and snatched it from their hands.
their hands.
their hands. "Tell me," he demanded, holding their
"Tell me," he demanded, holding their
"Tell me," he demanded, holding their only vision hostage, or remain blind
only vision hostage, or remain blind
only vision hostage, or remain blind forever.
forever.
forever. They hissed, but they spoke. They told
They hissed, but they spoke. They told
They hissed, but they spoke. They told him of a distant island beyond mortal
him of a distant island beyond mortal
him of a distant island beyond mortal maps, past crags that tore ships to
maps, past crags that tore ships to
maps, past crags that tore ships to splinters, where stone statues littered
splinters, where stone statues littered
splinters, where stone statues littered the shores like fallen soldiers. An
the shores like fallen soldiers. An
the shores like fallen soldiers. An island where no birds sang and no stars
island where no birds sang and no stars
island where no birds sang and no stars dared linger. The lair of Medusa. And so
dared linger. The lair of Medusa. And so
dared linger. The lair of Medusa. And so Perseus flew, sandals slicing through
Perseus flew, sandals slicing through
Perseus flew, sandals slicing through clouds, heart pounding, not with fear,
clouds, heart pounding, not with fear,
clouds, heart pounding, not with fear, but anticipation.
but anticipation.
but anticipation. He saw himself returning to Sarapos with
He saw himself returning to Sarapos with
He saw himself returning to Sarapos with a head in his hands, triumphant, dier
a head in his hands, triumphant, dier
a head in his hands, triumphant, dier proud, polyctis humbled. He did not yet
proud, polyctis humbled. He did not yet
proud, polyctis humbled. He did not yet question the story he'd been told, that
question the story he'd been told, that
question the story he'd been told, that Medusa was a monster, that she deserved
Medusa was a monster, that she deserved
Medusa was a monster, that she deserved to die.
to die.
to die. The gods had prepared him, but they had
The gods had prepared him, but they had
The gods had prepared him, but they had not warned him. They had not said that
not warned him. They had not said that
not warned him. They had not said that her cave was lined with the remains of
her cave was lined with the remains of
her cave was lined with the remains of men who called themselves heroes.
men who called themselves heroes.
men who called themselves heroes. They had not said that her eyes were not
They had not said that her eyes were not
They had not said that her eyes were not cruel, only cursed. and they had not
cruel, only cursed. and they had not
cruel, only cursed. and they had not said that her face beneath the serpents
said that her face beneath the serpents
said that her face beneath the serpents behind the myth still carried the shape
behind the myth still carried the shape
behind the myth still carried the shape of a woman once full of faith.
of a woman once full of faith.
of a woman once full of faith. As he flew across the sea, the winds
As he flew across the sea, the winds
As he flew across the sea, the winds howled louder as if trying to speak. But
howled louder as if trying to speak. But
howled louder as if trying to speak. But Perseus heard only silence, a silence
Perseus heard only silence, a silence
Perseus heard only silence, a silence the gods knew well. Because when you
the gods knew well. Because when you
the gods knew well. Because when you create a monster, the last thing you
create a monster, the last thing you
create a monster, the last thing you want is for someone to hear her speak.
want is for someone to hear her speak.
want is for someone to hear her speak. When Perseus landed on the shores of the
When Perseus landed on the shores of the
When Perseus landed on the shores of the island, the world seemed to hold its
island, the world seemed to hold its
island, the world seemed to hold its breath. No breeze, no bird song, only
breath. No breeze, no bird song, only
breath. No breeze, no bird song, only statues, hundreds of them, scattered
statues, hundreds of them, scattered
statues, hundreds of them, scattered like fallen warriors across the cliffs
like fallen warriors across the cliffs
like fallen warriors across the cliffs and crags. Their faces were twisted in
and crags. Their faces were twisted in
and crags. Their faces were twisted in terror, mouths frozen midscream, eyes
terror, mouths frozen midscream, eyes
terror, mouths frozen midscream, eyes wide with the last thing they ever saw,
wide with the last thing they ever saw,
wide with the last thing they ever saw, her. He stepped over stone limbs and
her. He stepped over stone limbs and
her. He stepped over stone limbs and shattered shields, his sword sheathed,
shattered shields, his sword sheathed,
shattered shields, his sword sheathed, his mirrored shield held tight. Athena
his mirrored shield held tight. Athena
his mirrored shield held tight. Athena had warned him, "Never look at her
had warned him, "Never look at her
had warned him, "Never look at her directly. Use reflection. Be swift. Be
directly. Use reflection. Be swift. Be
directly. Use reflection. Be swift. Be silent." But what the goddess hadn't
silent." But what the goddess hadn't
silent." But what the goddess hadn't said was why the statues looked not just
said was why the statues looked not just
said was why the statues looked not just terrified, but surprised. As if in their
terrified, but surprised. As if in their
terrified, but surprised. As if in their final second, they'd realized they were
final second, they'd realized they were
final second, they'd realized they were wrong. Perseus moved deeper into the
wrong. Perseus moved deeper into the
wrong. Perseus moved deeper into the cavern, wings folding behind him. The
cavern, wings folding behind him. The
cavern, wings folding behind him. The air was thick with damp moss, snake
air was thick with damp moss, snake
air was thick with damp moss, snake musk, and something else. Sorrow. The
musk, and something else. Sorrow. The
musk, and something else. Sorrow. The serpents hissed before he saw her. A low
serpents hissed before he saw her. A low
serpents hissed before he saw her. A low symphony of warning and weariness. Then
symphony of warning and weariness. Then
symphony of warning and weariness. Then she appeared, not charging, not roaring,
she appeared, not charging, not roaring,
she appeared, not charging, not roaring, not even aware. Medusa slept, coiled on
not even aware. Medusa slept, coiled on
not even aware. Medusa slept, coiled on a bed of stone, arms curled around
a bed of stone, arms curled around
a bed of stone, arms curled around herself like a child. Her face in the
herself like a child. Her face in the
herself like a child. Her face in the mirrored shield was peaceful, fragile. A
mirrored shield was peaceful, fragile. A
mirrored shield was peaceful, fragile. A strange beauty lingered, though her
strange beauty lingered, though her
strange beauty lingered, though her features were half hidden beneath the
features were half hidden beneath the
features were half hidden beneath the tangle of venomous serpents that rested
tangle of venomous serpents that rested
tangle of venomous serpents that rested for now in slumber.
for now in slumber.
for now in slumber. She did not look like a monster. She
She did not look like a monster. She
She did not look like a monster. She looked like someone who had been left
looked like someone who had been left
looked like someone who had been left behind.
behind.
behind. Perseus hesitated.
Perseus hesitated.
Perseus hesitated. This was not the roaring beast sung
This was not the roaring beast sung
This was not the roaring beast sung about in legends, not the terror painted
about in legends, not the terror painted
about in legends, not the terror painted on urns and shields. She was just a
on urns and shields. She was just a
on urns and shields. She was just a woman, cursed, asleep, and utterly
woman, cursed, asleep, and utterly
woman, cursed, asleep, and utterly alone.
alone.
alone. But the gods had given him a task. He
But the gods had given him a task. He
But the gods had given him a task. He remembered his mother. He remembered the
remembered his mother. He remembered the
remembered his mother. He remembered the mocking voice of Polyctis. He remembered
mocking voice of Polyctis. He remembered
mocking voice of Polyctis. He remembered glory. And so he raised the sword, his
glory. And so he raised the sword, his
glory. And so he raised the sword, his eyes fixed on the mirrored shield. He
eyes fixed on the mirrored shield. He
eyes fixed on the mirrored shield. He took one step closer. A snake lifted its
took one step closer. A snake lifted its
took one step closer. A snake lifted its head. Medusa stirred, her eyes
head. Medusa stirred, her eyes
head. Medusa stirred, her eyes fluttered, still closed. She did not
fluttered, still closed. She did not
fluttered, still closed. She did not scream. She did not fight. She barely
scream. She did not fight. She barely
scream. She did not fight. She barely breathed. And in that moment, Perseus
breathed. And in that moment, Perseus
breathed. And in that moment, Perseus struck. The blade hissed through the air
struck. The blade hissed through the air
struck. The blade hissed through the air with a divine edge. Silence followed.
with a divine edge. Silence followed.
with a divine edge. Silence followed. When her head fell into the satchel
When her head fell into the satchel
When her head fell into the satchel lined with bronze scales, the island
lined with bronze scales, the island
lined with bronze scales, the island exhaled.
exhaled.
exhaled. The curse was done. Or so he thought.
The curse was done. Or so he thought.
The curse was done. Or so he thought. Because you can kill a body, but not a
Because you can kill a body, but not a
Because you can kill a body, but not a story. And Medusa's story was just
story. And Medusa's story was just
story. And Medusa's story was just beginning.
beginning.
beginning. Perseus didn't linger. With Medusa's
Perseus didn't linger. With Medusa's
Perseus didn't linger. With Medusa's head sealed in the enchanted satchel,
head sealed in the enchanted satchel,
head sealed in the enchanted satchel, its gaze still potent even in death, he
its gaze still potent even in death, he
its gaze still potent even in death, he rose into the sky, sandals beating
rose into the sky, sandals beating
rose into the sky, sandals beating against the clouds, but the silence of
against the clouds, but the silence of
against the clouds, but the silence of the island clung to him. Not a silence
the island clung to him. Not a silence
the island clung to him. Not a silence of victory, something colder. The head
of victory, something colder. The head
of victory, something colder. The head still pulsed with quiet power, though
still pulsed with quiet power, though
still pulsed with quiet power, though severed, it was not lifeless.
severed, it was not lifeless.
severed, it was not lifeless. The snakes writhed, tongues flickering,
The snakes writhed, tongues flickering,
The snakes writhed, tongues flickering, sensing the world beyond the bag. Her
sensing the world beyond the bag. Her
sensing the world beyond the bag. Her eyes remained open, unblinking, capable
eyes remained open, unblinking, capable
eyes remained open, unblinking, capable of petrifying anything that dared peer
of petrifying anything that dared peer
of petrifying anything that dared peer within.
within.
within. Perseus didn't look. He dared not. The
Perseus didn't look. He dared not. The
Perseus didn't look. He dared not. The gods had given him a weapon now, a
gods had given him a weapon now, a
gods had given him a weapon now, a divine trump card. But he began to feel
divine trump card. But he began to feel
divine trump card. But he began to feel uneasy carrying it. As he flew across
uneasy carrying it. As he flew across
uneasy carrying it. As he flew across the ocean, creatures of shadow stirred
the ocean, creatures of shadow stirred
the ocean, creatures of shadow stirred in the waves. For this act, though
in the waves. For this act, though
in the waves. For this act, though heroic in the mortal realm, had awakened
heroic in the mortal realm, had awakened
heroic in the mortal realm, had awakened old pacts. Medusa's death had not gone
old pacts. Medusa's death had not gone
old pacts. Medusa's death had not gone unnoticed.
unnoticed.
unnoticed. Deep in the sea, her slayer had
Deep in the sea, her slayer had
Deep in the sea, her slayer had disturbed the balance. Poseidon felt it.
disturbed the balance. Poseidon felt it.
disturbed the balance. Poseidon felt it. Athena knew it. The fates wo quietly.
Athena knew it. The fates wo quietly.
Athena knew it. The fates wo quietly. And far above Olympus, a storm began to
And far above Olympus, a storm began to
And far above Olympus, a storm began to gather. Still, Perseus pressed on. His
gather. Still, Perseus pressed on. His
gather. Still, Perseus pressed on. His thoughts were consumed with what came
thoughts were consumed with what came
thoughts were consumed with what came next. He would return to Sarapos. He
next. He would return to Sarapos. He
next. He would return to Sarapos. He would silence King Polyctis, free his
would silence King Polyctis, free his
would silence King Polyctis, free his mother, restore his name. He would be a
mother, restore his name. He would be a
mother, restore his name. He would be a hero. That's what the stories promised.
hero. That's what the stories promised.
hero. That's what the stories promised. But the weight of the satchel told
But the weight of the satchel told
But the weight of the satchel told another tale. He remembered the mirrored
another tale. He remembered the mirrored
another tale. He remembered the mirrored shield and the face he'd seen. She
shield and the face he'd seen. She
shield and the face he'd seen. She hadn't snarled. She hadn't lunged. She'd
hadn't snarled. She hadn't lunged. She'd
hadn't snarled. She hadn't lunged. She'd been sleeping.
been sleeping.
been sleeping. Was that truly a monster? Or had he
Was that truly a monster? Or had he
Was that truly a monster? Or had he killed a warning wrapped in
killed a warning wrapped in
killed a warning wrapped in misunderstanding?
misunderstanding?
misunderstanding? He pushed the thought aside. The gods
He pushed the thought aside. The gods
He pushed the thought aside. The gods had guided him, hadn't they? But as the
had guided him, hadn't they? But as the
had guided him, hadn't they? But as the wind howled louder, Perseus noticed
wind howled louder, Perseus noticed
wind howled louder, Perseus noticed something odd. The head was humming. Not
something odd. The head was humming. Not
something odd. The head was humming. Not a sound, but a sensation. As if it still
a sound, but a sensation. As if it still
a sound, but a sensation. As if it still remembered the world, as if the soul of
remembered the world, as if the soul of
remembered the world, as if the soul of Medusa, cursed, betrayed, mutilated,
Medusa, cursed, betrayed, mutilated,
Medusa, cursed, betrayed, mutilated, still looked outward, still aware, still
still looked outward, still aware, still
still looked outward, still aware, still waiting. And though Perseus would go on
waiting. And though Perseus would go on
waiting. And though Perseus would go on to slay monsters, rescue maidens, and
to slay monsters, rescue maidens, and
to slay monsters, rescue maidens, and carve his name into the stars, he would
carve his name into the stars, he would
carve his name into the stars, he would never again sleep soundly. Because
never again sleep soundly. Because
never again sleep soundly. Because sometimes, at night, he swore he heard
sometimes, at night, he swore he heard
sometimes, at night, he swore he heard the faint rattle of snakes beneath his
the faint rattle of snakes beneath his
the faint rattle of snakes beneath his bed roll. And sometimes he dreamed not
bed roll. And sometimes he dreamed not
bed roll. And sometimes he dreamed not of victory, but of a girl kneeling in a
of victory, but of a girl kneeling in a
of victory, but of a girl kneeling in a temple, begging the gods to protect her.
temple, begging the gods to protect her.
temple, begging the gods to protect her. Perseus returned to Sarapos with
Perseus returned to Sarapos with
Perseus returned to Sarapos with windswept hair, divine armor, and the
windswept hair, divine armor, and the
windswept hair, divine armor, and the head of a legend tucked under his cloak.
head of a legend tucked under his cloak.
head of a legend tucked under his cloak. The people greeted him with cheers,
The people greeted him with cheers,
The people greeted him with cheers, unaware of what lay in the satchel,
unaware of what lay in the satchel,
unaware of what lay in the satchel, unaware of what it had cost. But King
unaware of what it had cost. But King
unaware of what it had cost. But King Polyctis was no fool. He had never
Polyctis was no fool. He had never
Polyctis was no fool. He had never expected the boy to survive. His
expected the boy to survive. His
expected the boy to survive. His challenge had been a death sentence
challenge had been a death sentence
challenge had been a death sentence wrapped in mockery. So when Perseus
wrapped in mockery. So when Perseus
wrapped in mockery. So when Perseus stroed into the palace, head held high.
stroed into the palace, head held high.
stroed into the palace, head held high. The king's sneer quickly turned to
The king's sneer quickly turned to
The king's sneer quickly turned to unease.
unease.
unease. You brought me a gift? Polyctis mocked,
You brought me a gift? Polyctis mocked,
You brought me a gift? Polyctis mocked, trying to hold on to control. Perseus
trying to hold on to control. Perseus
trying to hold on to control. Perseus nodded once. A token of your request.
nodded once. A token of your request.
nodded once. A token of your request. And with that, he opened the satchel.
And with that, he opened the satchel.
And with that, he opened the satchel. For a brief second, Polyctis met the
For a brief second, Polyctis met the
For a brief second, Polyctis met the gaze of Medusa. Just a second. It was
gaze of Medusa. Just a second. It was
gaze of Medusa. Just a second. It was enough. Stone cracked through his skin
enough. Stone cracked through his skin
enough. Stone cracked through his skin like frost on glass. His eyes froze
like frost on glass. His eyes froze
like frost on glass. His eyes froze wide. His final breath was trapped
wide. His final breath was trapped
wide. His final breath was trapped behind lips turned to granite. The king,
behind lips turned to granite. The king,
behind lips turned to granite. The king, so smug, so cruel, was now nothing more
so smug, so cruel, was now nothing more
so smug, so cruel, was now nothing more than a statue. The room erupted in
than a statue. The room erupted in
than a statue. The room erupted in screams. Couriers fled. Some fell to
screams. Couriers fled. Some fell to
screams. Couriers fled. Some fell to their knees. Perseus remained silent,
their knees. Perseus remained silent,
their knees. Perseus remained silent, his expression unreadable. His mother,
his expression unreadable. His mother,
his expression unreadable. His mother, Dia, rushed to embrace him, finally
Dia, rushed to embrace him, finally
Dia, rushed to embrace him, finally free.
free.
free. And still, Perseus said nothing about
And still, Perseus said nothing about
And still, Perseus said nothing about the girl in the cave. To them, Medusa
the girl in the cave. To them, Medusa
the girl in the cave. To them, Medusa was a monster defeated, a tool used, an
was a monster defeated, a tool used, an
was a monster defeated, a tool used, an obstacle overcome. No one asked who she
obstacle overcome. No one asked who she
obstacle overcome. No one asked who she had been, but Perseus remembered. The
had been, but Perseus remembered. The
had been, but Perseus remembered. The way her body fell, the way her face in
way her body fell, the way her face in
way her body fell, the way her face in the mirror had not snarled, but pleaded.
the mirror had not snarled, but pleaded.
the mirror had not snarled, but pleaded. Still the story spread quickly. Songs
Still the story spread quickly. Songs
Still the story spread quickly. Songs were sung, temples raised. Perseus was
were sung, temples raised. Perseus was
were sung, temples raised. Perseus was called Gorgon Slayer, champion of the
called Gorgon Slayer, champion of the
called Gorgon Slayer, champion of the gods, breaker of curses. They etched his
gods, breaker of curses. They etched his
gods, breaker of curses. They etched his name into marble. never once carving
name into marble. never once carving
name into marble. never once carving hers beside it. In his later years, he'd
hers beside it. In his later years, he'd
hers beside it. In his later years, he'd placed Medusa's head on Athena's shield
placed Medusa's head on Athena's shield
placed Medusa's head on Athena's shield by the goddess's own command.
by the goddess's own command.
by the goddess's own command. Her face, once scorned, was now turned
Her face, once scorned, was now turned
Her face, once scorned, was now turned outward as a weapon of divine justice.
outward as a weapon of divine justice.
outward as a weapon of divine justice. But not justice for her, justice for
But not justice for her, justice for
But not justice for her, justice for others. Even in death, Medusa served.
others. Even in death, Medusa served.
others. Even in death, Medusa served. Even in silence, her power remained. And
Even in silence, her power remained. And
Even in silence, her power remained. And Perseus, the golden hero, walked beneath
Perseus, the golden hero, walked beneath
Perseus, the golden hero, walked beneath that shield for years to come. Every
that shield for years to come. Every
that shield for years to come. Every victory won with the face of the woman
victory won with the face of the woman
victory won with the face of the woman he had slain. He was loved. She was
he had slain. He was loved. She was
he had slain. He was loved. She was feared. And neither could change the
feared. And neither could change the
feared. And neither could change the roles the gods had written for them.
roles the gods had written for them.
roles the gods had written for them. After Perseus's triumph, Athena summoned
After Perseus's triumph, Athena summoned
After Perseus's triumph, Athena summoned him to Olympus, not just to praise him,
him to Olympus, not just to praise him,
him to Olympus, not just to praise him, but to claim what had always belonged to
but to claim what had always belonged to
but to claim what had always belonged to her. Not the sword, nor the sandals, nor
her. Not the sword, nor the sandals, nor
her. Not the sword, nor the sandals, nor the helm of Hades. She wanted the head,
the helm of Hades. She wanted the head,
the helm of Hades. She wanted the head, the head of Medusa.
the head of Medusa.
the head of Medusa. Perseus obeyed, offering the satchel
Perseus obeyed, offering the satchel
Perseus obeyed, offering the satchel without question. And with practiced
without question. And with practiced
without question. And with practiced grace, Athena took the severed head of
grace, Athena took the severed head of
grace, Athena took the severed head of her former priestess, and affixed it to
her former priestess, and affixed it to
her former priestess, and affixed it to her shield, her eegis, turning it into a
her shield, her eegis, turning it into a
her shield, her eegis, turning it into a weapon of legend. The Gorgon's face,
weapon of legend. The Gorgon's face,
weapon of legend. The Gorgon's face, once radiant, once innocent, now snarled
once radiant, once innocent, now snarled
once radiant, once innocent, now snarled in frozen rage from the bronze curve of
in frozen rage from the bronze curve of
in frozen rage from the bronze curve of the goddess's arm. Wherever Athena
the goddess's arm. Wherever Athena
the goddess's arm. Wherever Athena marched, war followed. Enemies turned to
marched, war followed. Enemies turned to
marched, war followed. Enemies turned to stone at the sight of it.
stone at the sight of it.
stone at the sight of it. Cities fell. Statues of the eegis spread
Cities fell. Statues of the eegis spread
Cities fell. Statues of the eegis spread across temples and coinage. Her shield
across temples and coinage. Her shield
across temples and coinage. Her shield became both warning and banner.
became both warning and banner.
became both warning and banner. But no one ever asked why Medusa had
But no one ever asked why Medusa had
But no one ever asked why Medusa had been cursed in the first place. Athena,
been cursed in the first place. Athena,
been cursed in the first place. Athena, the goddess of wisdom, carried the face
the goddess of wisdom, carried the face
the goddess of wisdom, carried the face of a woman she had once punished. Not as
of a woman she had once punished. Not as
of a woman she had once punished. Not as a reminder, not out of guilt, but as a
a reminder, not out of guilt, but as a
a reminder, not out of guilt, but as a symbol of divine power, of what happens
symbol of divine power, of what happens
symbol of divine power, of what happens when mortals overstep. Yet some
when mortals overstep. Yet some
when mortals overstep. Yet some whispered differently. Some said Athena
whispered differently. Some said Athena
whispered differently. Some said Athena was not reclaiming a weapon, but
was not reclaiming a weapon, but
was not reclaiming a weapon, but granting Medusa immortality.
granting Medusa immortality.
granting Medusa immortality. That by placing her on the Aegis, she
That by placing her on the Aegis, she
That by placing her on the Aegis, she ensured Medusa would never be forgotten.
ensured Medusa would never be forgotten.
ensured Medusa would never be forgotten. that the girl who had once cried in her
that the girl who had once cried in her
that the girl who had once cried in her temple was now etched into eternity
temple was now etched into eternity
temple was now etched into eternity where even the gods had to carry the
where even the gods had to carry the
where even the gods had to carry the consequences of their actions.
consequences of their actions.
consequences of their actions. But the truth, the truth as always with
But the truth, the truth as always with
But the truth, the truth as always with gods was layered in paradox. Athena had
gods was layered in paradox. Athena had
gods was layered in paradox. Athena had condemned Medusa for shaming her temple
condemned Medusa for shaming her temple
condemned Medusa for shaming her temple and now she wielded that same shame as a
and now she wielded that same shame as a
and now she wielded that same shame as a trophy. The transformation was complete.
trophy. The transformation was complete.
trophy. The transformation was complete. Medusa had been a priestess, then a
Medusa had been a priestess, then a
Medusa had been a priestess, then a victim, then a monster, now a weapon, an
victim, then a monster, now a weapon, an
victim, then a monster, now a weapon, an icon. And yet, somewhere in the curve of
icon. And yet, somewhere in the curve of
icon. And yet, somewhere in the curve of that sculpted jaw, in the tragic slant
that sculpted jaw, in the tragic slant
that sculpted jaw, in the tragic slant of her petrified eyes, something still
of her petrified eyes, something still
of her petrified eyes, something still lived, something the world couldn't
lived, something the world couldn't
lived, something the world couldn't unsee.
unsee.
unsee. Because even as she turned armies to
Because even as she turned armies to
Because even as she turned armies to stone, there were always a few, just a
stone, there were always a few, just a
stone, there were always a few, just a few, who looked upon her face and didn't
few, who looked upon her face and didn't
few, who looked upon her face and didn't see a monster. They saw a question, a
see a monster. They saw a question, a
see a monster. They saw a question, a protest, a warning. And that is a power
protest, a warning. And that is a power
protest, a warning. And that is a power no blade could match. Medusa's face now
no blade could match. Medusa's face now
no blade could match. Medusa's face now stared outward from Athena's eegis,
stared outward from Athena's eegis,
stared outward from Athena's eegis, unblinking, eternal. To most, it was a
unblinking, eternal. To most, it was a
unblinking, eternal. To most, it was a symbol of divine terror, of enemies
symbol of divine terror, of enemies
symbol of divine terror, of enemies turned to stone, of battles won with a
turned to stone, of battles won with a
turned to stone, of battles won with a single glance. But to those who looked
single glance. But to those who looked
single glance. But to those who looked closer, that gaze held something more
closer, that gaze held something more
closer, that gaze held something more than fury. It held memory. It held
than fury. It held memory. It held
than fury. It held memory. It held injustice.
injustice.
injustice. It held the truth no temple scroll ever
It held the truth no temple scroll ever
It held the truth no temple scroll ever dared to write. Through the centuries,
dared to write. Through the centuries,
dared to write. Through the centuries, warriors marched behind that shield,
warriors marched behind that shield,
warriors marched behind that shield, unaware that the face they wielded once
unaware that the face they wielded once
unaware that the face they wielded once belonged to a woman who had never raised
belonged to a woman who had never raised
belonged to a woman who had never raised a hand in violence. Her curse, gifted by
a hand in violence. Her curse, gifted by
a hand in violence. Her curse, gifted by the gods, had become a tool of empire.
the gods, had become a tool of empire.
the gods, had become a tool of empire. The weaponization of her trauma was
The weaponization of her trauma was
The weaponization of her trauma was complete. Still, her eyes continued to
complete. Still, her eyes continued to
complete. Still, her eyes continued to see.
see.
see. Long after her voice had been silenced,
Long after her voice had been silenced,
Long after her voice had been silenced, her gaze bore witness to a thousand
her gaze bore witness to a thousand
her gaze bore witness to a thousand battles. She watched kings rise and
battles. She watched kings rise and
battles. She watched kings rise and fall. She saw temples crumble and heroes
fall. She saw temples crumble and heroes
fall. She saw temples crumble and heroes turn cruel. She saw altars raised to men
turn cruel. She saw altars raised to men
turn cruel. She saw altars raised to men who had called her a monster and prayers
who had called her a monster and prayers
who had called her a monster and prayers whispered by women who understood what
whispered by women who understood what
whispered by women who understood what she had lost.
she had lost.
she had lost. And sometimes those women left
And sometimes those women left
And sometimes those women left offerings.
offerings.
offerings. Tiny clay serpents placed at hidden
Tiny clay serpents placed at hidden
Tiny clay serpents placed at hidden shrines. A lock of hair wrapped in
shrines. A lock of hair wrapped in
shrines. A lock of hair wrapped in cloth. A whispered name buried in the
cloth. A whispered name buried in the
cloth. A whispered name buried in the dark. Not out of fear,
dark. Not out of fear,
dark. Not out of fear, but remembrance.
but remembrance.
but remembrance. Because long before Medusa became a
Because long before Medusa became a
Because long before Medusa became a cautionary tale, she had been a
cautionary tale, she had been a
cautionary tale, she had been a protector. Her cave had become a
protector. Her cave had become a
protector. Her cave had become a graveyard of wouldbe conquerors. Yes,
graveyard of wouldbe conquerors. Yes,
graveyard of wouldbe conquerors. Yes, but also a sanctuary. A place no man
but also a sanctuary. A place no man
but also a sanctuary. A place no man could enter and survive. A place where
could enter and survive. A place where
could enter and survive. A place where the hunted became untouchable. In time,
the hunted became untouchable. In time,
the hunted became untouchable. In time, her legend fractured. To some, she
her legend fractured. To some, she
her legend fractured. To some, she remained the Gorgon. To others, she
remained the Gorgon. To others, she
remained the Gorgon. To others, she became something else entirely, a symbol
became something else entirely, a symbol
became something else entirely, a symbol of resistance, a goddess of wrath and
of resistance, a goddess of wrath and
of resistance, a goddess of wrath and wounded justice, a spirit that stood
wounded justice, a spirit that stood
wounded justice, a spirit that stood between the powerless and the predators.
between the powerless and the predators.
between the powerless and the predators. Her myth bent and twisted as myths do,
Her myth bent and twisted as myths do,
Her myth bent and twisted as myths do, but the core remained. A woman wronged.
but the core remained. A woman wronged.
but the core remained. A woman wronged. A woman reshaped by pain. A woman whose
A woman reshaped by pain. A woman whose
A woman reshaped by pain. A woman whose story had been stolen, but whose stare
story had been stolen, but whose stare
story had been stolen, but whose stare could never be taken away. And so her
could never be taken away. And so her
could never be taken away. And so her gaze endured across paintings,
gaze endured across paintings,
gaze endured across paintings, sculptures, shields, coins, and dreams.
sculptures, shields, coins, and dreams.
sculptures, shields, coins, and dreams. And in every retelling, someone new
And in every retelling, someone new
And in every retelling, someone new would pause. Someone would ask, "Was she
would pause. Someone would ask, "Was she
would pause. Someone would ask, "Was she really the monster?" And in that
really the monster?" And in that
really the monster?" And in that question, Medusa lived again. Centuries
question, Medusa lived again. Centuries
question, Medusa lived again. Centuries passed. Empires crumbled. New gods rose
passed. Empires crumbled. New gods rose
passed. Empires crumbled. New gods rose and fell, but Medusa endured not as
and fell, but Medusa endured not as
and fell, but Medusa endured not as flesh and blood, but as symbol and
flesh and blood, but as symbol and
flesh and blood, but as symbol and shadow. Her face, chiseled into marble
shadow. Her face, chiseled into marble
shadow. Her face, chiseled into marble and cast in bronze, migrated across
and cast in bronze, migrated across
and cast in bronze, migrated across cultures. In Bzantium, in Rome, in
cultures. In Bzantium, in Rome, in
cultures. In Bzantium, in Rome, in forgotten corners of the world, her
forgotten corners of the world, her
forgotten corners of the world, her image lingered just beneath the surface
image lingered just beneath the surface
image lingered just beneath the surface of myth and memory.
of myth and memory.
of myth and memory. But something strange happened over
But something strange happened over
But something strange happened over time. The tale began to split. In one
time. The tale began to split. In one
time. The tale began to split. In one version, she remained the monster, the
version, she remained the monster, the
version, she remained the monster, the Gorgon, the serpent-haired killer who
Gorgon, the serpent-haired killer who
Gorgon, the serpent-haired killer who turned men to stone with a glare. Her
turned men to stone with a glare. Her
turned men to stone with a glare. Her head became a talisman against evil,
head became a talisman against evil,
head became a talisman against evil, mounted above doors, gates, and armor.
mounted above doors, gates, and armor.
mounted above doors, gates, and armor. Soldiers carried her into war, hoping
Soldiers carried her into war, hoping
Soldiers carried her into war, hoping her legend would strike fear deeper than
her legend would strike fear deeper than
her legend would strike fear deeper than any spear. But another story quietly
any spear. But another story quietly
any spear. But another story quietly grew alongside it, one whispered by
grew alongside it, one whispered by
grew alongside it, one whispered by poets, philosophers, and women whose
poets, philosophers, and women whose
poets, philosophers, and women whose voices rarely made it into scrolls. In
voices rarely made it into scrolls. In
voices rarely made it into scrolls. In this story, Medusa was not a beast to be
this story, Medusa was not a beast to be
this story, Medusa was not a beast to be slain, but a wronged woman, punished for
slain, but a wronged woman, punished for
slain, but a wronged woman, punished for beauty, cursed for a crime committed
beauty, cursed for a crime committed
beauty, cursed for a crime committed against her.
against her.
against her. This version didn't roar, it murmured.
This version didn't roar, it murmured.
This version didn't roar, it murmured. It asked why a goddess of wisdom would
It asked why a goddess of wisdom would
It asked why a goddess of wisdom would punish her own servant, why the god of
punish her own servant, why the god of
punish her own servant, why the god of the sea would face no consequence, why
the sea would face no consequence, why
the sea would face no consequence, why so many men sought to kill her when she
so many men sought to kill her when she
so many men sought to kill her when she simply wanted to be left alone. In
simply wanted to be left alone. In
simply wanted to be left alone. In taverns, in libraries, in hidden corners
taverns, in libraries, in hidden corners
taverns, in libraries, in hidden corners of temples, these questions bloomed like
of temples, these questions bloomed like
of temples, these questions bloomed like weeds in cracks of marble. And slowly,
weeds in cracks of marble. And slowly,
weeds in cracks of marble. And slowly, the image of Medusa began to shift
the image of Medusa began to shift
the image of Medusa began to shift again. She became a mirror, not of
again. She became a mirror, not of
again. She became a mirror, not of terror, but of truth. Women began to see
terror, but of truth. Women began to see
terror, but of truth. Women began to see themselves in her. Survivors of
themselves in her. Survivors of
themselves in her. Survivors of violence, victims of silence, souls
violence, victims of silence, souls
violence, victims of silence, souls forced to wear the label of monster
forced to wear the label of monster
forced to wear the label of monster simply for being feared. Her serpents
simply for being feared. Her serpents
simply for being feared. Her serpents were no longer a punishment, but a
were no longer a punishment, but a
were no longer a punishment, but a crown. Her eyes not a curse, but a
crown. Her eyes not a curse, but a
crown. Her eyes not a curse, but a defense sharpened by betrayal. Even now,
defense sharpened by betrayal. Even now,
defense sharpened by betrayal. Even now, in modern tales and art, Medusa rises
in modern tales and art, Medusa rises
in modern tales and art, Medusa rises again, not to petrify, but to testify.
again, not to petrify, but to testify.
again, not to petrify, but to testify. She stares from paintings with grief and
She stares from paintings with grief and
She stares from paintings with grief and fury. Her story is retold not to glorify
fury. Her story is retold not to glorify
fury. Her story is retold not to glorify Perseus, but to ask why he was called a
Perseus, but to ask why he was called a
Perseus, but to ask why he was called a hero at all, because myths evolve. And
hero at all, because myths evolve. And
hero at all, because myths evolve. And sometimes the monster is not the one
sometimes the monster is not the one
sometimes the monster is not the one with fangs, but the one holding the
with fangs, but the one holding the
with fangs, but the one holding the sword. And in every generation that
sword. And in every generation that
sword. And in every generation that dares to question the old story,
dares to question the old story,
dares to question the old story, Medusa blinks just once and watches them
Medusa blinks just once and watches them
Medusa blinks just once and watches them begin to understand.